<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Andrew Duckworth</title>
  <subtitle>Designer, artist</subtitle>
  <id>https://grillopress.github.io/</id>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2019-12-05T07:30:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Don't forget to stretch your design</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/12/05/stretch-your-design.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/12/05/stretch-your-design.html</id>
    <published>2019-12-05T07:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-12-05T08:10:59+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A common set of questions I ask designers when reviewing work is how their design stretches to cover different scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When things are empty. When things go wrong. On different devices. But also for variable data or poor quality data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A designer should ensure they have a solid design for a common path, but it&amp;rsquo;s easy to design for unrealistically good examples or data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A long time ago I was tasked with redesigning a few websites for a communications team. Part of the work was a clearer, more accessible web design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I designed some of the system and reviewed it against the live website, it dawned on me the how vastly different some of the news article headings were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the h1s were full paragraphs. Working with the team I knew this wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to change anytime soon. And even if it did, the years of news articles would still need to be accommodated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My large clear font worked great for most of the website, but it didn&amp;rsquo;t stretch to this part of the website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To remedy this I first set up a web crawler to download every article into a spreadsheet. I could then analyse the size and shape of the data my design had to stretch to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My design was much better for it. My design was now more flexible and able to cope with real data. It was no longer so brittle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be sure to &lt;a href="#"&gt;design for real data&lt;/a&gt; and real user journeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can either design for data so good it&amp;rsquo;ll never exist. Or accommodate what a user will really experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your design will have to stretch to getting data back from APIs in FULL SCREAMING UPPERCASE. And some users seeing 1 category, and others seeing 32. Or comms teams who like to write full paragraphs as a heading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t forget to stretch your design.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Design for real data</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/12/05/design-for-real-data.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/12/05/design-for-real-data.html</id>
    <published>2019-12-05T07:29:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-12-05T08:28:19+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s vital to design for real data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don&amp;rsquo;t, your service or product design is artwork. And your design will not be implemented. However well it tests. Because it can&amp;rsquo;t be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When designing any service that needs to interact with data from a database you have to accommodate the quality and business process rules for that data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designing for real data is vital when you have to accommodate data from other sources or APIs. Ones not originally designed for being shown to your users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When tackling a data and APIs you need to ask:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what&amp;rsquo;s the source of data?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s the original purpose of that data?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who looks after the database?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how is it kept up to date?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how consistent is that data?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what&amp;rsquo;s the exact format of data?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what&amp;rsquo;s the most (length, number of items etc.) something can be? What&amp;rsquo;s the least?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what are some real examples you could use?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding the real shape of data will let you ask why. &lt;a href="#"&gt;Stretch your design&lt;/a&gt;. And potentially create moments to really transform services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A colleague &lt;a href="#"&gt;Sam&lt;/a&gt; recently finished a project rethinking data collection. Part of her process she looked at previous submissions. As she did, she could point to failings and data quality issues. Which provided real evidence for change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can either design for data so good it&amp;rsquo;ll never exist. Or accommodate what a user will really experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s hard work. But it&amp;rsquo;s where the work really is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do the hard work to design for real data.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Find the right words to get the job done</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/10/22/use-the-right-words.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/10/22/use-the-right-words.html</id>
    <published>2019-10-22T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-10-22T23:33:49+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;About a year ago a designer helped fill in for a couple of weeks when I was on leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They mentioned that one of the development teams I worked with didn&amp;rsquo;t know some design thinking terminology, and it surprised them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially as I worked with them for over a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from inspiring some mild imposter syndrome, it got me thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things I like to do is make teams know the outcomes we&amp;rsquo;re trying to create. And the problems we&amp;rsquo;re trying to solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s why I do &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2017/12/10/hypothesis-driven-design.html"&gt;hypothesis driven design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there&amp;rsquo;s a difference between working in the right way and dictating the exact words and ways we explain things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s about finding the right words to help each other understand how to get to a solution. Or what&amp;rsquo;s blocking one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From colleagues to stakeholders to users. You have to lean on commonly understood things. As well as what the people you&amp;rsquo;re working with say and label things as.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to use &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2018/12/19/trying-a-new-format-for-hypotheses.html"&gt;a set format for hypotheses&lt;/a&gt; and I use this to document my work. And when I get my work reviewed by colleagues I tend to talk through them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;m not going to talk about hypothesis driven design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than talking about double diamonds, design thinking and hypotheses. It&amp;rsquo;s important to start by using the words and concepts of the team or individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a time and a place to introduce new things. But no one wants to be lectured at. Find the right words to get the job done.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Start it right</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/10/10/start-it-right.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/10/10/start-it-right.html</id>
    <published>2019-10-10T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-10-10T23:10:43+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve spent a fair amount of time doing discoveries in the last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some better than others. And I&amp;rsquo;ve learnt loads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that helps frame discoveries better is &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/10/08/make-it-about-a-decision.html"&gt;shaping them around a decision&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this well it’s best to kick off your discoveries with an “inception” meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An inception is a project kickoff session.  Everyone who is part of the discovery team should be there. As well as any decision maker or stakeholder too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This meeting helps you define the right scope and what you need to go find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A format for an inception that has worked for me and other teams I&amp;rsquo;ve helped is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is a discovery?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What problem or task have we been given?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our discovery is to decide [x]?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To make that decision, we need to know what?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What should we do to find out what we need to know?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This format helps get your team focused on the right things. And gives you the space to define what decision you&amp;rsquo;re going to tackle. As well as the steps you&amp;rsquo;re going to take to make that decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have a shared understanding of what decision you’re helping make. Or of what you need to do to support that decision, it’s nearly impossible to do any project justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No discovery should start without understanding what issue you&amp;rsquo;re exploring. Nor should they continue without you understanding what decision you are helping make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After defining the policy intent or issue to a decision you should discuss as a team what you need to know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding what a team needs to know is the most important part. This can range from &amp;ldquo;who are our users&amp;rdquo; to more specific technical issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you only have an hour together, you should spend half your time talking through what you know. And what you need to find out. As well as prioritising what to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you&amp;rsquo;ve defined as a group what you want to find out, you can define some activities you&amp;rsquo;ll likely do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This part might be flexible. But it helps push forward your team from things to find out, to what we can do about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Continuous inception&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no reason to only do this sort of activity at the start of project either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the last summer I joined a discovery project several weeks in and struggled a little with the scope. By resetting it with the whole team I caught up but the team could also pivot on what they’d already found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That meeting shaped the next few weeks and helped us come to a different, better decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get your discovery going by setting the direction. By starting, or restarting, it right.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Make it about a decision</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/10/08/make-it-about-a-decision.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/10/08/make-it-about-a-decision.html</id>
    <published>2019-10-08T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-10-10T22:16:10+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Whether you&amp;rsquo;re looking at solving a big problem or a part of a product or service that isn&amp;rsquo;t performing, discoveries are a key.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discoveries are intense periods of learning and exploring. They help you to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;question what opportunities there are&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what issues your users are facing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what problems you should try to solve&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They can last weeks or months. And you can even chain several together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of every good discovery is a decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To build a service or not. To pursue a solution. To prioritise a problem or not. To go forward with a piece of work or not. To solve an issue in a certain way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By working from a decision it&amp;rsquo;s easier for a team to know what to do. What sort of evidence they need. And what level of confidence they should be comfortable with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on a decision also gives talented teams space. If you&amp;rsquo;re deciding to build a service or not, a &amp;ldquo;no&amp;rdquo; may also highlight what should be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a team is told to build a thing or deliver a feature, making the first step a discovery and a decision means the team can carve the space to do the work to choose if the direction is correct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Framing discoveries as a decision helps transfer power to the team on the ground. Which will help deliver the outcomes behind any ask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I&amp;rsquo;ve made a discovery about a decision, what to do has always been clearer. And speaking truth to power easier, because that was the outcome agreed upon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make your next period of intense research and design about a decision.  It&amp;rsquo;ll help give you space to do your best work. And deliver better outcomes for your business.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Let your design breathe</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/08/05/let-your-design-breathe.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/08/05/let-your-design-breathe.html</id>
    <published>2019-08-05T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-08-05T07:14:46+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It can be easy to get caught up in a furious cycle of design research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategy is delivery. And delivery puts pressure on to test your designs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you&amp;rsquo;re developing a service against tight deadlines or with a large team, that can mean testing a lot. Of things, ideas and changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the alternative being not testing things. Or not challenging designs, the pressure is real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you can find yourself sucked into a rapid cycle of testing session after session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s easy to find yourselves designing in small incremental steps. And not making big iterative changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you have to vary your pace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask any developer and they&amp;rsquo;ll tell you the times they&amp;rsquo;ve spent hours failing to solve a problem. Only to solve it in minutes the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s better to give yourself some time. And challenge things with larger iterative designs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you&amp;rsquo;ve got to let it breathe.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
