<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2018-09-14T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 15</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/09/14/weeknotes-15.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/09/14/weeknotes-15.html</id>
    <published>2018-09-14T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-09-14T19:11:30+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Trying to keep these even leaner. Going to just focus on a couple of themes from a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Paper forms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a personal crusade with paper forms right now. We have three for patients and soon have some for prisoners (filled in by prison medical staff on behalf of a prisoner).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re not good enough. People can muddle through them. But they&amp;rsquo;re not the standard we need to be hitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the back of a great session at the design huddle with Caroline Jarrett I had a strong action plan. I even tweeted it for feedback:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Any other solid ways of researching paper forms?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re doing:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;+ looking at real paper form submissions&lt;br&gt;+ working with team who get forms and action them&lt;br&gt;+ user lab focused on paper forms&lt;br&gt;+ Challenging the need for stuff in the forms 😁&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Andrew Duckworth (@AndrewDuck_) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AndrewDuck_/status/1039789320792666112?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;September 12, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And got even greater feedback and connections to people willing to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happily the programme agreed to do everything to make them better. With a bit of campaigning we&amp;rsquo;ve got access to the current filled in forms and will review them next Wednesday as a team. We&amp;rsquo;ve also booked in a lab and potentially some pop-up testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve created a clean form system. Brutally simple graphic design system. Now to make our process brutally simple for our users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Design meet up!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week it was the quarterly all-hands design meet. In London this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoy going to London. That said, though the venue was great, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t as iconic or scenic a walk this time. And it was also a rather painfully long day. Thanks trains!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the day I got to express my inner artiste:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;The best name badge I ever did have. Thank you &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AndrewDuck_?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@AndrewDuck_&lt;/a&gt; 🦄 &lt;a href="https://t.co/cH2DBkcFRu"&gt;pic.twitter.com/cH2DBkcFRu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Louise Mushet (@louisemushet) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/louisemushet/status/1039883809553084416?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;September 12, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And hang with lots of cool people. (Special shout out to Louise Mushet who made the day extra fun without a few of my design besties!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the day the rapid paced 5 min show and tells worked well in quickly letting everyone show a thing. Be present. Be the centre of attention. But they also are just too short and leave no room for chats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I nicked time in each talk to ask a question. So when people were swapping over I&amp;rsquo;d ask a question. But they left me wanting more. Much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you get together so many smart people I feel you have to give space to comments. That freeform discussion space is where designers shine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunch was amazing. Hat tip to Pete &amp;ldquo;Two sheds but actually I only have one right now because I gave my son a shed&amp;rdquo; Smith. We had to walk for it but I had a great plate of chicken kabab and chips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all it was a great day. Loads of smart, fun people in the room. Really well put together by the London design gang!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Stuff for admin users&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that popped up at the design away day. And reviewing some work recently, is the attitude towards professional/admin users by designers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something I&amp;rsquo;ve heard elsewhere was lots of excuses how &amp;ldquo;that&amp;rdquo; group of users are different. Like they can&amp;rsquo;t be overworked. Distracted. Confused. Need full love and attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happily we have lots of designers who care. But plenty don&amp;rsquo;t. Plenty just throw away solid patterns because things aren&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;citizen facing&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like admin staff aren&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;citizens&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, if a user does a thing 20 times a day, certain patterns may need to be tweaked. Tweaked not destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designers should be responding to user needs not preconceptions. And it makes me shudder when those preconceptions don&amp;rsquo;t have a date with user testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does your user do that thing 20 times a day?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked this question recently to a designer and the answer was 3 times a year. That isn&amp;rsquo;t an interface that they know by heart. That isn&amp;rsquo;t an interface they have muscle memory developed for.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 14</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/08/06/weeknotes-14.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/08/06/weeknotes-14.html</id>
    <published>2018-08-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-08-12T20:39:35+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the day with the regular UX meeting. Talked about the lab for the next day. Timing wise and what we need to cover is pretty tight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prototype ready to go. Added some behaviour to simulate live timings and behaviour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I typically don’t simulate things like spinners and delay in a prototype. The idea being that a prototype is testing a hypothesis. Not your ability to make it seem like live. But what we’re testing is behaviour influenced by time. Delay. And the impact of failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re exploring adding an extra way to find your credentials. Right now, we have a high percentage chance of finding users’ contact details. But, we are asking that they use their NHS number. We’re exploring alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alternatives that may not suit everyone. And introduce new potential failures. But also make the service easier to use first time for many more people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spent a lot of the day chatting with a colleague Ben. Lots of fun but also sharing research and ideas. Images, designer collaboration. Ensuring styles stay consistent. Helping new and emerging services learn from what has gone before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In that vein, reached out to a colleague. Offered some help on a few things that I felt weren’t quite right. Planned to work together and get stuff going in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All day in the lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nine people through three prototypes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exploring how we could open up the way people authenticate using the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had people from NHS England, Department of Health and NHS Digital observe together. As well as some very senior stakeholders. Which was great to see. A result of hard work campaigning and pushing a user-centred agenda.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some interesting moments in the lab but not as much clarity as hoped for the path forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One moment was when a user said they preferred a version they struggled with. One of the programme manager&amp;rsquo;s asked &amp;ldquo;why?&amp;rdquo;. It was a great teaching moment that what people ask for, isn&amp;rsquo;t always what works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day after the lab. Planned some initial steps forward with the service’s authentication design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extensive talk with the researchers to plan some A/B testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Off project work. Working on a more aligned style for a colleague. Simpler screens. One thing at a time. Not one field. But one ask for the user. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter if your users are skilled administrators.  You treat them with the same care and attention you would on any other project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extremely busy day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught up with a colleague Dan who used to be on my project. Was great to catch up and talk through his work and catch up him up on some of the things I’d been up to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walked over to my new office. Tagged along with a researcher Lucy who I enjoy chatting with. She’ll be on a project that I will lead design on. Looking forward to working with her and another researcher Will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;New office is nice. Have a whole floor to ourselves and lots of whitespace. And a football goal!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walked into a crisis. Something in the “do later” column was now “get it done yesterday”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Went over to another office to attend a meeting I had set up. Originally to sketch out the interaction flow, but now more of a crisis meeting. Productive meeting. Got to eek out the problems we need to tackle. A shared response as well as way forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back over to the new office and walked into a technical deep-dive. Some possible ways forward immediately became problematic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was intense. But enjoyable as well. A team pulling together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Played a little football together and then broke for lunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After lunch across Leeds once again to meet the researchers and talk through our A/B testing scenarios. We mapped out our ideas. Where we needed to split users. Type of activity you can tie yourself up in knots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back again across Leeds to the new office. Again walking into a few more discussions. A few more constraints uncovered. A direction forward starting to take shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked from home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spent most of the day working on a framework to help do all the A/B testing. Just simple JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Added it to my prototype and cut two versions to test. Created a landing page for the experiment as well as a end page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shared the prototype with the researchers. Now to chuck 250 people at it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 13</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/07/20/weeknotes-13.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/07/20/weeknotes-13.html</id>
    <published>2018-07-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-07-26T08:05:27+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finished off the short-term roadmap for NHSUK development work. Shared it and asked for feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Met up with the Thunderbird product owner. Heard about a better direction for a large piece of work coming out of discovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attended a Programme patient facing services meeting. Part of a regular Monday meetup. We talked about the various work streams. NHS app integration. Analytics on the service. User journeys on our NHSUK landing pages. Measuring how successful our authentication work has been. And the numbers I dug out about the two-factor element of our service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good meeting. Tough things to discuss. But cracking on. Making things better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the meeting caught up with our content designer. We talked about my “hub” page concept and his content audit and how to best take those two things forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught up with the developers and then walked to the Citizen, NHS app and National data opt-out cross-service meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pitched what I saw as the model of interaction we should be striving for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had prepared for this meeting by talking lots. Understanding constraints on all sides (design, technical, delivery).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Three NHS services in a room. Talking through making things easier. Better. Exploring possibilities and making plans to test things. What I joined &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/NHSDigital?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@NHSDigital&lt;/a&gt; to do&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Andrew Duckworth (@AndrewDuck_) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AndrewDuck_/status/1018889390473478147?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;July 16, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the day collecting all the improvements we’d made since going into public beta.  For a report to the Department of Health and Social Care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A large chunk being accessibility improvements. Still lots more to make. But rewarding how much we’ve made the service better already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designed a “scheduled maintenance” page for the service. As the service matures, we’re refining the messages people see when things go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chased up some work we’re relying on another team to complete. Bit of career management. Training courses. For myself and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started a presentation about the reasons why we should move to a new content architecture. As much an exercise to get myself prepared as anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designed an interaction flow for the service. Exploration of the app/service integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we’re distributed around offices, we have two weekly calls for design and research. We talked at length what we saw as the biggest problems facing the service. Came out with an update to our service polls. Had a great session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards we had an authentication review. A vital meeting to dig into our biggest problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a range of potential solutions. In the meeting we thrashed through the pros and cons of each approach. Outcome of the meeting was a sprint based on testing a two-track authentication approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the meeting one of the user researchers said to me “You were really on it!”. Made me laugh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asked the programme if there was any possibility we could get a graduate designer to join the team. Got a pretty quick yes. Wrote up the form. Sold the opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spent the rest of the day sketching flows and screens for the next prototype iteration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the morning catching up with some of the user centred design team from the Digital Delivery Centre. Then talked service design with Tero and Simon. Integration between Citizen ID and National data opt-out. Both short-term and long-term visions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asked the person in charge of the graduate programme if the form was any good. He submitted immediately and said it was great… Finger’s crossed!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed the new NHSUK grid system. Found a place we’d need an override. Opened an issue for the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bit of admin with the weekly design huddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started a new prototype series to explore the alternative authentication approaches. Was nice to be doing something with my kit again. Although I was ripping lots of things out, I have it all well set up. Integrated some of the NHS number finder code into the kit to get me ahead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be easy as a designer to want to switch tools. To move to the next thing. Though there is much I want to improve in my kit. It works and I’m productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attended sprint planning with the Thunderbird team. Talked the delivery team through the design hypotheses behind the future authentication work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also talked through some of the work we’d need to do around the two-factor code screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is often a bit of tension when new work is iterative rather than incremental. A move from 1.0 to 2.0. But understanding the why. The outcomes that are desired makes the jump easier to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great session as ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the day with a content architecture review. Ian the content designer had crafted up the content and pages he thought vital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We walked through the hub pages together. Noted a couple of changes. He sent them over ready for a new hub page prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spent the rest of the day working on the new authentication prototype series.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 12</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/07/13/weeknotes-12.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/07/13/weeknotes-12.html</id>
    <published>2018-07-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-07-17T14:06:26+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked from home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finalised some personal development paperwork. For myself and a user researcher I career manage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Updated the service prototype. Asked the team a couple of questions about what I saw as gaps in the content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quick chat with the programme manager. Future direction of the landing pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got stuck into the new NHSUK redesign team&amp;rsquo;s work. Exploring how our landing pages would fit right now. But also what we are planning on creating long term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head&amp;rsquo;s down type of day on the future of the service. Content architecture. Site structure and redesign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked through the day to designers about their work. What was going on. What they&amp;rsquo;ve seen and bouncing ideas between us all. Ideas are always stronger for sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little bit of admin for the weekly design huddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Updated the release prototype with a couple of extra changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Published my article about how &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2018/06/26/things-are-different-in-live.html"&gt;Things are different in live&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another day full of work on the future of the service&amp;rsquo;s landing pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helped a colleague collect some details for Expo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shared the new landing page direction with the wider team. Talked through the last round of user research and how to reflect what we learnt into our start page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught up quite a bit with the NHSUK redesign team over slack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fired up the accessibility tools to verify a fix on the live solution. Getting better with the tools but the learning curve is immense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Met with Pedro, a designer on the NHS app team. Talked through the app. Design decisions on the National Data Opt-out. And how we integrate the service into the app to ensure users have control over their data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught up with the Thunderbird team. Learnt that we were going to lose some talented people from the team. Not great news to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hosted the design huddle. We had Dave Evans talk to us about &amp;ldquo;publications&amp;rdquo;. Was a great chat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Enjoyed today&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/NHSDigital?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@NHSDigital&lt;/a&gt; design meetup talk by &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/devansXD?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@devansXD&lt;/a&gt; (co-presenting here with the wonderful &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/McVities?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@McVities&lt;/a&gt; Jaffacakes) &lt;a href="https://t.co/sROQENUZNF"&gt;pic.twitter.com/sROQENUZNF&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Andrew Duckworth (@AndrewDuck_) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AndrewDuck_/status/1017479408783953921?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;July 12, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A consistent issue across NHS Digital projects is a need to make navigating content work for people. Either in-page or across pages. It was great to hear from Dave what they had found designing for complex reports and publications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards had a quick accessibility review with the Citizen ID team. How to make errors discoverable and clear for all people. Another great huddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finished the day by writing up instructions for the NHSUK CMS team for an upcoming update on the train home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the day catching up on an email thread about the performance of our two-factor process. With the help of Adam from the Thunderbird team, dug out some of our log data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The development team had been asked a question two weeks ago about an issue. Though the numbers were fine there, I felt there was a subtle difference if we looked at an earlier stage of the journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I shared the data with the head of programme and the rest of the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The numbers helped focus the team from &amp;ldquo;let&amp;rsquo;s find out what we can improve about the two-factor journey for an unknown set of users&amp;rdquo;. To &amp;ldquo;we know users struggle on this page, right here&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that met up with colleague (Dan) for a service review. And hypothesis generation session.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dan was the junior designer on the service before and we ran a similar exercise when I joined the team (October 2017). Tables turned slightly as it was he who was asking me about the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We ran through the service questioning everything. Digging into compromises. Half solved issues. Alternatives and data. We asked the obvious questions. We did this screen by screen. Element by element.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as deconstructing things, we also created new ideas. Looking at alternatives. Considering other options we crafted up countless new ideas and things to try.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was mentally draining and though. But great fun. We grabbed a pizza at lunch and took a pause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterwards we&amp;rsquo;ll rank and sort all the ideas and questions. Which will give us our backlog of design work for the service. We&amp;rsquo;ll then share the backlog with other people in the team. Reorder, add things. Then get cracking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the end of the day took a call from Tero, service designer on another team, to go through what we felt was our goals for a meeting on Monday.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 11</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/07/06/weeknotes-11.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/07/06/weeknotes-11.html</id>
    <published>2018-07-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-07-09T12:04:13+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Skipped Weeknotes 10. The arrival of Evelyn Ada Duckworth over that weekend meant those notes didn’t get turned into a blog post. Written but not published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First day back from paternity leave. Working from home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sent an email to the programme team with some context about the birth etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Appreciate the environment and warm response from everyone in NHS Digital. Makes it easier to come back as well as plan some more time with my family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrote up some stuff for my personal development review. Found it tough going. Took inspiration from Matt Edgar and put in some tweets about my work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Took some time to go through some emails and prioritise work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arranged meetings through the week to catch up on work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medical appointment for myself at lunch. A very painful one but sorting a long-term issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked through the user research show and tell I missed as well as accessibility review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed the new designer job descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked from home again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrote up some more personal review stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spent some time working on a new prototype content architecture for my service. We have hit a point where we need to expand what we point people to. As new needs emerge and services are developed, we need to be able to easily scale the site&amp;rsquo;s structure to handle this. Right now, we are hitting the natural scaling limit of the pattern we are using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Went through a couple of stories on Jira and cleaned them up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Created a new interaction flow for a potential service integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First day back in the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cleaned up an issue on Jira for the development team. Got a lovely card and gift from the Thunderbird team. Really appreciated it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Checked up on the status of a ticket that really improves the user journey of our service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught up with the product manager for Thunderbird. She&amp;rsquo;s now in control for the two programme projects. Had a good catch up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arranged with a colleague to do a “hypothesis backlog generation” session. He had worked on the service before and we’re going to run a session we did when I arrived. Blog post coming soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked through with a colleague some page navigation work. Shared research and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cleaned up a developer point on a ticket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Met up with the service owner and programme manager. We talked roadmap, future integrations and design work. They mentioned how much they needed me in the next few months which was nice to hear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught up quickly with the user research team. Quick word before the lab on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jumped into a call with the delivery manager for the NHS app. Arranged to meet up with the design and research team in the next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked through links and downloads with a colleague tasked to explore those issues. Shared some scenarios and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NHS 70th birthday. Tweeted about my little service Easter egg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Happy birthday NHS! My little Easter egg for today was making my service&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;date of birth&amp;rdquo; helper text the same as the NHS &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nhs70?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#nhs70&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/KZEbEQLVcE"&gt;pic.twitter.com/KZEbEQLVcE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Andrew Duckworth (@AndrewDuck_) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AndrewDuck_/status/1014764183555100675?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;July 5, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early start with a usability lab. The lab focused on mobile users and digging behind some numbers. The hypothesis was that many of our users preferred not to start the transaction on mobile. We wanted to see if that was true, and if so, why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also wanted to evidence if the service was easy to use on mobile. And that we weren&amp;rsquo;t the cause of people avoiding using mobile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things we saw in the lab:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People really love the NHS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most people are willing to trade off personal data for the greater good&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giving people a sense of control, even if they don&amp;rsquo;t choose to use it, influences people&amp;rsquo;s willingness to share data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making authentication straightforward, clear and obvious increases people&amp;rsquo;s confidence in an organisation&amp;rsquo;s ability to handle sensitive data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Service comprehension remains high&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having a dropdown/reveal near the service start green button caused a little confusion on mobile. Proximity appeared to cause more issues on mobile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many of our users just prefer their laptops over mobiles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon I walked over to the design huddle. Ben talked us through some of his research on icons. It was a great talk. Ben is one of my favourite people at NHS Digital. His talk was great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Late on remembered to share some data with a colleague. Couple of heatmaps showing how people ignore thumbnails on download pages. People prefer links. People just don&amp;rsquo;t click or hover over thumbnails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of a thumbnail is in creating a pool of focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shorter work day due to my longer Thursday. Meetings most of the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quick update with the developer team and then lots of chats. Talked to the NHSUK redesign team about folding in work. Lots of stuff to do here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chatted to Ben about hub pages and differing styles of navigation. The key being consistent but also mixing things up when the need arrises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s very easy as a designer, with the whole website in your head, to over-value uniformity. Users don&amp;rsquo;t notice small differences. They notice if what they want to do is hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught up with Matt (Head of Design). Chatted about my service and how it is going since live. Family. And how to make your siblings like you (by peeing up walls as an infant).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Things are different in live</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/06/26/things-are-different-in-live.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/06/26/things-are-different-in-live.html</id>
    <published>2018-06-26T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-07-10T14:07:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In May I had the privilege of hearing about the great work done by the NHS Business Services Authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the talk the team mentioned a particular question that encountered a lot of distrust during testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked if they’d seen the same since going public. They hadn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This matched a recent experience with research into the National Data Opt-out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a few issues that when under the magnifying glass of user labs, got an increased emphasis. Emphasis we didn’t see since going public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t to say everything has been like this. The things people liked in labs, they liked in the public service. And the things that annoyed them (and us) in labs, annoyed them since going public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a strength of user labs that they let you solve the issues that stop people from using your service. And you find speed bumps and things that lead people astray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they won’t iron out every issue. They also don’t reflect going public either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing we found performing better has been our “interruption card” component.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a screen that acts as the sinew between the landing page and transactional service. This page lays out how to do the thing online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea behind it was to clear up the process of one-time authentication that’s needed. We found in Alpha that we had a sizeable user group that hadn’t done two-factor authentication before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the lab, these things performed okay. Some people zoomed past them. Some slowed down and got the info they needed to understand the journey they were about to take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a ringing endorsement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the issue was most users were happy to share their data with the NHS for research and planning purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evaluating the component became difficult. We saw some users zoom through things they may have taken more time over at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though it didn’t stop the zoomers in the lab, it did seem to support some users. We kept it for the public service. Partially because of a hunch that on scale it would prove its worth. And also because the evidence was that it did alright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since going public, the indications have been that it’s been working better. Tracking cursor movements has seen lots of users track and read the text on the card. User journey recordings also show it. Likewise, with user feedback on that page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empowering users is about them understanding what they are doing. And why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of letting users know how to do a thing is that they understand what to expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t alway need to surface process, but we’re glad we have. It stopped users questioning why we were asking for their details to stop data being shared. It stopped some users feeling out of control and unable to use the online service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll never know for sure if something works. Things are different in live.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
