<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2018-01-20T20:30:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>This week's links</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/01/20/weekly-links.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/01/20/weekly-links.html</id>
    <published>2018-01-20T20:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2018-01-21T00:08:39+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;"This week's links" is a collection of things I found, got told about, re-read and shared elsewhere this week&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The last week was a pretty intense one at work with a full day in a usability lab and a day working on design principles for the NHS on Thursday. I also helped handle some more junior designer recruitment stuff as well as plan the next iteration of the prototype I am working on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond work, life was not so great. The week ended on a high note finding out that we will be welcoming a daughter to the family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a summary and link to some of the things that I have been reading and thinking about in the last week:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class='weekly-link-list'&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Put field labels above forms and wait before a user submits a form to provide error feedback&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Not a new one, but I shared
&lt;a href="https://www.hindawi.com/journals/ahci/2011/202701/" target="_blank"&gt;Working towards Usable Forms on the World Wide Web: Optimizing Date Entry Input Fields &lt;/a&gt;
to a collegue over Slack.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Essentially, the range of studies it summarizes indicates that you should put field labels above forms if you want users to complete forms quickly and with less stress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also reports that users make significantly more errors if you validate your fields inline as your user inputs their data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not a portfolio-pretty approach, but let a user submit a form then provide them with feedback on whether it is correct. This approach also rewards keeping forms short and taking users through your service one thing at a time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='link-to'&gt;
Read more:
&lt;a href="https://www.hindawi.com/journals/ahci/2011/202701/" target="_blank"&gt;Working towards Usable Forms on the World Wide Web: Optimizing Date Entry Input Fields &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The NHS belongs to the people&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-nhs-constitution-for-england/the-nhs-constitution-for-england" target="_blank"&gt;NHS Constitution &lt;/a&gt;
is a ridiculously inspiring document.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is the guiding principles of the NHS. The aims and goals of the NHS and what it stands for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was officailly published in 2013 but built on things like the founding principles of the NHS, the Patient's Charter and similar documents. It has since also been updated, with 2015 being the latest revision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first line is "The NHS belongs to the people".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have worked for the NHS for a while and whilst I knew parts of it and seen it quoted around and on posters, it wasn't until the last year that I really sat down to read it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you work for the NHS or have any sort  of love for it, I recommend reading part if not all of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The NHS Constitution was on the forefront of my mind this week as I was at a meeting to help draft up some design principles for the NHS.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At a previous meeting an NHS Digital colleague Nicola, mentioned the NHS Constitution as a guiding light for any principles.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As we worked on reviewing some design principles I brought them up again as I thought Nicola's point was spot on and that the NHS Constitution be something we should take inspiration from and use as a guiding light for any principles.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='link-to'&gt;
Read more:
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-nhs-constitution-for-england/the-nhs-constitution-for-england" target="_blank"&gt;NHS Constitution &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Stay focused on the user. It doesn’t matter how much experience you gain as a UX Designer, our main job is to solve user needs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Since before Christmas I have been helping our with junior designer recruitment.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wanted to make sure I was giving constructive career feedback to unsuccessful candidates which lead me to read Cinthya Mohr's
&lt;a href="https://medium.com/google-design/tips-for-starting-or-growing-your-career-as-a-ux-designer-ad8dbf1eb2d6" target="_blank"&gt;Tips for starting or growing your career as a UX designer. &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key process I use before doing anything is to reach out to people who I know who have done things before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also like to google things to see what other people learnt and what advice they'd give.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One key area where I thought some prospective juniors could do with some pointers is how they explain their design process and in particular the process behind a key portfolio piece.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cinthya's piece did a really good job of laying out how to build a narrative for portfolio peices that really resonated with what I wanted to see from the designers I interviewed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='link-to'&gt;
Read more:
&lt;a href="https://medium.com/google-design/tips-for-starting-or-growing-your-career-as-a-ux-designer-ad8dbf1eb2d6" target="_blank"&gt;Tips for starting or growing your career as a UX designer. &lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Kanban for interaction design</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/01/08/kanban_for_interaction_design.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/01/08/kanban_for_interaction_design.html</id>
    <published>2018-01-08T21:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2018-01-12T20:01:38+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
Recently at work I have been using a Kanban board with a colleague to manage our design work.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Although early days, we have found it to be a real help and it has garnered some interest beyond the project we are on.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started the board with the following goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Track what each other is working on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Record our design reviews and comments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Better develop our design process (using hypotheses)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Record design decisions and evidence for them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Show our process to the rest of the project&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be able to (visually) organise and  priortise design work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Involve our Product Owner in priortising what design work was being focused on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you are the sole designer/UX person, it is valuable to be able to communicate with other people on a project what you are working on and your current priorities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The board has helped us structure our work and track it better, as well as expose that workflow to other members of the team.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has also shown us where our design bottlenecks are, and what things we need to swarm on together to speed up and get done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It takes discipline to maintain but provides real value if you do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id='so_what_is_kanban'&gt;So, what is Kanban?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you've worked on a software project before, you may have encountered
&lt;a href='https://www.atlassian.com/agile/kanban'&gt;Kanban boards.&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a Kanban board, items (jobs, tasks or anything) are written on cards which sit on a board in a set of columns. Each column has a label indicating the cards status or activity. The cards move across the board as they change status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simplest Kanban boards are structured in three columns of "todo", "doing", "done". Often this board structure then evolves with a "backlog" or "ideas" column preceeding the todo column for ideas to be stored.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='todo-board'&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;h3 class='h4 title'&gt;
Ideas
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;h3 class='h4 title'&gt;
Todo
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;h3 class='h4 title'&gt;
Doing
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;h3 class='h4 title'&gt;
Done
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many workflows ours didn't feel like it fit with this simplisitic structure. But we did feel like this technique could help us structure our work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id='how_we_implemented_kanban'&gt;How we implemented Kanban&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step we took was to sketch out the phases a bit of design work would go through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To test if it would work we realised we needed to get this on a whiteboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found some whiteboard space (a precious commodity) and started to draw our board up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We both knew this was going to be a long journey. There was also a risk of exposing our work too early and receiving too much input too soon. It's better to get something up and public. The risk was worth the reward.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;First implementation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After going backwards and forwards over the column names, we sketched out our board and added some cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt='A Kanban board drawn on a whiteboard' src='/images/boards/first_iteration.jpg'&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea behind the columns were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol id='first-implementation'&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Backlog&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The is where our ideas live. Design hypotheses. Components to look into and explore. Things to optimise. Bugs or "That's not great is its".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Elaborate&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phase where we are actively working on a problem, but exploring the shape and size of it. Looking at current solutions and the reasons they exist, as well as other people's.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Refine&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we are refining our ideas into testable chunks of work. Sketching paper prototypes. Thinking how a problem might be solved but an iterative area of work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Build&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The stage where we formally think an idea is worth pursuing. We have a hypothesis, we have refined it and now want to build something formally to test and review&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Review&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Formal review time. Either with a fellow designer or a member of the product team (or programme or beyond).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Test/Evaluate&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time to get it in front of people and work out if it has the desired outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Done&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All work finished. Idea explored, built, reviewed, tested with users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got something up. And the second we did we saw what we felt was right, but also what we felt was missing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We didn't know where and by whom something was reviewed. Nor did we get a good sense of what was bouncing around after review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also wanted to ensure our process was repeatable. Repeating high value things like documenting design decisions. We wanted to have that explicit, rather than implicit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As designers we're part of the board and ceremonies for the development team. Our work feeds into the Scrum/Kanban flow of the development board, but we help with frontend tickets too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was clear immediately that the development board of the project we were on had informed us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had copied some of the naming conventions and flow. It felt like it captured some of what we wanted to do, but not enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Exposing the workflow&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had started using the board. As we used it and explained it, it felt like there needed to be an iterative pattern or process in the middle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In hindsight, this is where we got a little too complicated early on. We knew we would see real value in exposing the iterative nature of our work. We struggled to find that balance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Having looked for other examples of designers using Kanban, I stumbled across
&lt;a href='/'&gt;this blog post about Kanban&lt;/a&gt;.
It explained how Conceptboard had used it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought the Z-shaped pattern quite interesting.  It showed the iterative pattern of a design artefact going through rounds of review and refinement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Inspired by this, we created a less-conventional Kanban design that looked like the below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='z-board'&gt;
&lt;div class='backlog'&gt;
&lt;h3 class='h4 title'&gt;
Backlog
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class='research'&gt;
&lt;h3 class='h4 title'&gt;
Research
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class='design'&gt;
&lt;h3 class='h4 title'&gt;
Design
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class='inner-row'&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
Prototype
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class='inner-row'&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
Refine
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class='review'&gt;
&lt;h3 class='h4 title'&gt;
Review
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class='inner-row'&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
Design
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class='inner-row'&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
Project
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class='inner-row'&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
External
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class='done'&gt;
&lt;h3 class='h4 title'&gt;
Done
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class='inner-row'&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
Documented
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class='inner-row'&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
Shared
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class='inner-row'&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
Deployed
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea behind this structure is that important sub-phases of design are exposed. The flow of a card on this board is still left to right but if a card merited it, it could fall through additional phases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A card that goes through review would jump from
&lt;strong&gt;Design - Prototype&lt;/strong&gt;
to
&lt;strong&gt;Review - Design&lt;/strong&gt;
moving after that again into the
&lt;strong&gt;Design&lt;/strong&gt;
column but this time in the
&lt;strong&gt;Refine&lt;/strong&gt;
cell.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cards would now move through a Z-shape or in a circular fashion. Their iterative journey surfaced.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our second feature was the drawing out of what wanted to make sure we did with each bit of design work. The process of documenting and sharing our work and then getting it in a product (prototype or production).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at this now it is easy for us to see the faults.  At the time we were so close to it, it took us time to step back and see what was working and what wasn't.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We sacrificed the simplicity of our board to expose the iterative flow. We had completely messed up any notion of done by filling things in that column rather.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Wider feedback&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I now felt ready to ask for some feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I grabbed an experienced service designer I knew and walked him through the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was great to hear he loved what we were doing. He also poked and prodded the thinking behind everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Taking the time to explain your concept is often the quickest way to expose the holes in your thinking. This is because you have to explain your idea without your hidden assumptions and background knowledge.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The complicated nature of the flow was clear.  Not in the fact that the designer couldn't understand and appreciate the flow, but that he was completely unsure of how it would work by looking at it.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another interesting point the service designer made was about our prioritisation of cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I mentioned that we wanted to have a sense of what was more important. Our idea was to rank cards and show that on the board with high priority cards being at the top of the
&lt;strong&gt;Backlog&lt;/strong&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
As I was talking through the board the head of the user research profession walked by. She asked a couple of questions too. A real reminder of the amazing place that I get to work where I can casually talk to two amazing, talented and experienced individuals about a sub-project I am passionate about.
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Designing the card&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we had been iterating our board we had been taking real design tasks through them. The design of our cards hadn't received much love or attention at this stage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first our cards consisted of their title.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we added a short description.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We started to toy with the idea of colour indicating the type of design work. This was something that the developer board of our project did well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I grabbed our Product Owner to walk them through the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
They appreciated the clarity into our process and what we were working on. The ability to influence and ensure things he saw down the line would be accommodated.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They added that it would be valuable for them to be able to see where design issues or tasks came from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This felt like that a great idea. On each card we added a "referral" tag. This one-line tag, indicated where the problem or task came from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='kanban-card'&gt;
&lt;div class='title'&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;
Title of the Kanban card
&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class='stickers'&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class='desc'&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Description of the hypothesis, thing to explore or issue raised
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class='referrer'&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Originator of idea/issue (Project, Lab etc.)
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We now had a stronger structure for our cards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this stage, it felt like an optimisation too far to use coloured cards. We knew there was value to that system of categorisation. But it felt like a premature optimisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also had plenty of space left on the card to add things like tags, avatars and Jira numbers. And plenty of time to have finer grained categories too, further down the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Simplifying it&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The board now felt like it was adding value. The cards were now easier to understand and the board was explicit at which stage our work was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The development team we sit in has a very experienced Scrum Master. I felt the board and my ability to explain it was now at a point where I could expose it further and to more rigorous examination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We grabbed some time and took them through the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The board received more love. But the Scrum Master also noted two things they would change:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The board column structure was too hard to understand at first glance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We didn't really have a real done column&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would have been easy to argue with the Scrum Master and say that an iterative process cannot be displayed in a linear fashion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, this was the third or fourth time we had heard something similar about the visual structure. Every time we explained it, people understood it. But we wanted this board to expose something about how we worked to our project and the wider organisation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Asking the Scrum Master about other ways of displaying iterations he mentioned the use of sticky dots.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea seemed like a very neat way of indicating what had been reviewed and by whom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking this opportunity we went back to basics. We explained our work flow and design process to the Scrum Master who scribbled on the board as we did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src='/images/boards/analysing_the_flow.jpg'&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had another iteration&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Another iteration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The outcome of the session with the Scrum Master meant we had an alternative way of displaying our iterative process as well as some tweaks to our columns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We drew up our board and made a few tweaks again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src='/images/boards/another_iteration.jpg'&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our new column structure was:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol id='another-iteration'&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Backlog&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The is where our ideas live. Design hypotheses. Components to look into and explore. Things to optimise. Bugs or "That's not great is its".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the product team, we routinely rank and evaluate items here. Ensuring everything has been designed and tested before being put into the product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To illustrate something is more important, it sits higher up the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Research&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phase where we are actively working on a problem, but exploring the shape and size of it. Looking at current solutions and the reasons they exist, as well as other people's.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Design&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we are exploring and then refining our ideas into testable chunks of work. From sketching paper prototypes to screens or HTML.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If an item has a sticky note, it has been reviewed and an indicator of an item going through some further refinement or exploration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Design Review&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Formal review time. With another designer. The idea here being that we stage a time for each and every piece of design work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Comments and suggestions are made and then saved. A sticky dot with the reviewer's initials are added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the item is deemed to need some further work, it can go back to the design column. If it is ready for wider review or would benefit from it, it moves forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Wider Review&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Review with the wider team/s. This ranges from informal to formal reviews with the product team to more formal processes including the wider programme, other organisations and entities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this stage, as with the design review column, a sticky dot is added. The name or initials of the reviewers are added.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The card then can return to design or move forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Document&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A staging area where we either create or collect our design artefacts together in one place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also add a design hypothesis (or two) to each ticket to surface our assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;User test&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time to get it in front of people and work out if it has the desired outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Done&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All work finished. Idea explored, built, reviewed, tested with users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Bottlenecks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We found two bottlenecks very quickly with this process. Design review and document.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The bottlenecks were faults of our own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking time to formally review, rather than quick glances, slowed things down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is easy to review design work and not question enough with a colleague. To give a quick glance and a supportive remark.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As well as make the time to thoroughly review things, it was clear that we needed to pass through things to review quicker as well. There is always the temptation to hold onto things until they are perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes reviewing harder. It also takes a lot longer and can stall other work you or colleagues have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The board highlighted that we needed to review early and often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Documenting things well can be a tough task. The board revealed to us we weren't documenting as we went enough and this added another bottleneck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer is of course "be better at documenting" but also make it easier to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Using a
&lt;a href="/2017/12/10/hypothesis-driven-design.html" target="_blank"&gt;hypotheses driven design method&lt;/a&gt;
we adopted a lean way of articulating our design decisions and what we were aiming to test with each change.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also used the comments section of a corresponding Jira card to document our review as well as attach any screenshots, PDFs, sketch files or links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because we made it easier to document our design decisions, we got better at documenting as we went.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Benefits of using Kanban&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our journey using the Kanban board has only just begun but we've seen some real value already.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With it we're able to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Track what each other is working on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Easily record our design reviews and comments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Involve our team in our process&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuously inspect our process and decisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make better stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It has played a core part of integrating our design process into the wider product and team. It has improved us as designers. It has organised and evolved our process. It has made it easier to work together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're considering using one, do it!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hypothesis driven design</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2017/12/10/hypothesis-driven-design.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2017/12/10/hypothesis-driven-design.html</id>
    <published>2017-12-10T12:10:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2017-12-29T16:30:51+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the team I work in, we have adopted a formal way of doing "Hypothesis Driven Design".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hypothesis driven design is where you design solutions and test them with your users. Advancing your understanding and business solution though each design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hypothesis driven design isn't new. It is having an idea and testing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many designers work in a hypothesis driven way but don't write their ideas down. This implicit way of coming up with an idea and then testing it is less than ideal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A hunch or a gut feel is a great start. But it isn't a repeatable, sharable method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Hypothesis as the articulation of intent&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hypotheses can be big or small. They are statements that can cover things like changing the colour of a button. Or a wider user need or story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A hypothesis is a statement. A statement of your current understanding and what change you expect to see. A hypothesis is an articulation of your intent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A written hypothesis exists to communicate your thinking. As well as letting you and others test your thinking. To verify it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we expect a certain user outcome if we change our button, is this the best way to do that? If we expect a certain outcome, did that happen when we tested it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A good hypothesis is testable and verifiable. It can be true or false. A written hypothesis lets others see, test and verify your thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the team I work in, we write our hypotheses using a formal language. We use:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class='list-unstyled list-hypothesis-statement'&gt;
&lt;li&gt;[Context]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If [some action]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Then [outcome for users]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Because [reason for outcome]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The context let's us frame why we are trying to solve a particular problem. We found this made writing easier. It also made them easier to understand when we returned to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your context could come from data. A hunch. A user lab. Other people. Or a mixture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example could be:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;'In lab 5 users struggled to navigate between pages. No user used the native browser back button. The researcher had to intervene to return to the homepage".&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of the statement frames what we are going to do, what impact that'll have on the user and why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One line suffices for each.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing these statements surfaces your reasoning behind your design decisions. It makes you a better designer. It acts as documentation. It helps you communicate the intent behind your design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Where our statements live&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We use a Kanban board to track our design work. We write our hypotheses as our design work matures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then attach the hypothesis statements as comments to our cards in Jira.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before any design artefact is given to a developer or tested, it must have a hypothesis attached to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we review our design work, we review the hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The prototypes we build are a collection of hypotheses. Some proven, some not. When we test our prototype with users, we see if our expectations are true or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes our hypotheses miss the mark. This can be because our design wasn't clear enough in rendering our intent. Or because our intent doesn't match what our users want or need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The benefits of using hypothesis driven design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hypothesis driven design is a process that generates easy to understand documentation. A log of your design thinking and decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing design hypotheses isn't always pleasurable. It can be tough to get them exactly right. But they make you a better designer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The act of articulating your design choice further refines your design. And your skills as a designer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By using a hypothesis driven design process you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class='list-benefits-of-hypothesis-driven-design'&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Articulate your thinking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide others with understanding of your thinking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a framework to test your designs against&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop a standard way of documenting your work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make better stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Other people's things on hypothesis driven design&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href='https://medium.com/@melhambo/use-a-hypothesis-backlog-to-capture-and-refine-your-problems-6ed0c4d499a2'&gt;Using a hypothesis backlog (Kanban board)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href='https://medium.com/leading-service-design/everything-is-hypothesis-driven-design-1986a4638285'&gt;Everything is hypothesis driven design&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>YAWYSCA or Yet Another Why You Should Code Article</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2017/09/04/why_every_one_should_code.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2017/09/04/why_every_one_should_code.html</id>
    <published>2017-09-04T23:50:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2017-12-03T12:32:55+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;
tl;dr I fall within the “yes you should learn to code” camp. I do so because it has both immediate and related benefits to everyone and computer science itself.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
Reasons to think everyone should learn to code…
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
Great developers can come from everywhere
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There are countless good and great developers and computer scientists who’ve come from a variety of backgrounds, not just a comp-sci background, that it is possible that anyone could pick it up and be good at it. Stepping outside of computer science, think of art as a discipline. Not every great artist was classically trained. Not every classically trained artist was great. Henri Matisse came to painting after getting a job at a bank (I’m sure there are better examples, an accomplished art historian, I am not!).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So, for you all you know, you could be a great developer. Or your friend or relative  or whoever.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And for the good of computer science, it is worth encouraging everyone to get involved. If a great developer etc. can come from anywhere, the more we encourage people to dip their toe, the greater the chance we have on finding that Matisse.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
Learning to code, like other crafts, can teach you something about yourself
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I’m a big fan of the notion that learning/doing things provides the room to improve as a person as well as space to learn about yourself. Coding is hard. Coding brings up problems. Hitting adversity and how to deal with that, teaches you things. I think this has made me a better person and better at creating and sourcing solutions (never mind improving my google-fu).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It has also exposed some things I don’t like about myself. I pride myself on being a problem solver, but sometimes I can be a problem avoider. This is sometimes a virtue (like NOT saying something when someone isn’t ready to hear it) but it can also be a vice (not saying anything at all, even when those thoughts could help the person in the long run). Learning to code exposed this to me. This has/will no doubt make me a better person. More aware.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This isn’t necessarily a benefit of learning to code that is integral to it, but like many crafts it constantly provides roadblocks (and unlike gardening, starting from scratch is just a remove directory command not four days back-breaking work!) and roadblocks have the chance of offering the chance to develop as a person.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;
Learning to code is a tangible benefit
&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In terms of more direct benefits of learning to code, it can provide you with concrete problem solving skills. A person I used to work with used to say “learning computer science changed how I solved problems”. They meant that since learning to code, they approached issues in a more systematic and structured methodology.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Similarly, if you learn to code and want to create something interesting (like an app that latches onto a moment in time) then you are able to do so. You have the ability to talk and tell a computer how exactly how to do something you want.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
But more than the ability to think in more logical ways or to express yourself and your imagination, you can make a damn fine stab at a career with coding. You can earn serious money even without being in the top 1% of your industry.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
From prototyping designs, creating scripts for spreadsheets, designing simple plugins for CMSes, to building highly available, distributed systems, coding can give you an extraordinary career. It pays really well, offers a massive range of roles that fit skill and personality types as well as work from home and start-up/entrepreneur possibilities. Coding/programming may have many issues and sins as an industry (which industry doesn’t?), but it does offer amazing opportunities.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;
But not EVERYONE is going to be good at it!
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
And that is fine. Not everyone is good at gardening, painting or pottery but I doubt we’d discuss whether anyone should give those activities a try.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Everyone should give coding a try. It has many tangible and intangible benefits.  Many people can make a living from it. Some people will be quite good at it. A few may even be great and make great things!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
If you fail, try again or try something else.
&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
