<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Andrew Duckworth</title>
  <subtitle>Designer, artist</subtitle>
  <id>https://grillopress.github.io/</id>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2021-05-12T08:30:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Shaping design work (with STAR)</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2021/05/12/shaping-work-with-star.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2021/05/12/shaping-work-with-star.html</id>
    <published>2021-05-12T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2021-05-13T19:12:58+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shaping design work for others, rather than tackling it yourself is a hard balancing act. Shape the work too much and people are too constrained. Too little and people get lost. Or scope is so large it’s difficult to show progress and value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not something a formula can solve. But there are things you can use to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve started to use a format when writing up and shaping design work. This was in response to at times feeling like some work was better shaped than others. And what an ideal statement of design work would be if I got something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format I’ve started to use is STAR. This isn’t a new thing. Though it wasn&amp;rsquo;t designed for shaping work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The STAR format helps write up case studies as well as structure interview responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It stands for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="list-unstyled"&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Situation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Task&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Activity/Action&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Result&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a sort of narrative helper. Useful to structure retrospective stories of how someone tackled something. And what results they got. STAR isn’t the only format, there’s a quite few around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with any narrative structure, it’s not only useful for when you’ve done something. It can help shape what you, or other people, can do to tackle work. Before you’ve done it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s something I’ve only started to use. But I’m finding it helpful. To get my thoughts in order. To direct teams and individual teams to kick start work. Big and small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How I use the format to shape design work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use the format to brake down work into each section. Which together helps create the size and shape of the work. This can then help someone to tackle work. Or act as material for kick off workshops and other meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also doesn’t have to be completely formed and can be created together as a group. And there’s no reason it needs to 1 person&amp;rsquo;s work. Or 1 role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Situation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many stories. Start at the beginning. Writing down all known facts about a problem or opportunity. This might be something like a preliminary problem statement. Or. It could be a raw set of constraints and hunches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve found it works better to throw in a few lines of what’s going wrong. And the issue that is being caused over a formal problem statement. But that might be a personal thing. I try too hard to get problem statements perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the situation section I also like to be clear where a request has come from. If it’s a policy, something observed in user research or a request from a product manager. Then say it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an opportunity needs some selling then that needs to be clear. Either internal buy in or validation. It helps teams know what they’ve got to do next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a request has a rigid scope that is also worth calling out. Again, it helps teams know what the situation is. And if it’s a “go do it” sort of situation and the reason is less than clear. That should be clear. It helps the team understand what to do. And how other people will understand the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Task&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial scope of work. This helps make it clear what I’m expecting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;m open to challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the section I leave the lightest. I like to use a phrase with a verb that defines the scope of the task. So something like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Understand why 25% of users are dropping off at the file upload page”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Design how we add second factor authentication to the sign up flow”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The verb acts to say what the scope is. Understand/design/review etc. This shapes the work of the team. Where the limits are. If it’s about understanding, that means we review as a team with next steps. If it is design, there’s a sense that we need to work on showing what the future should look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Activity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the part where you shape the sort of things you or the team should do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve shaping work for others, this is the most sensitive section. And where you want to be most aware of how much direction your team needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For teams with some experience you can call out the key milestones. Things like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create range of options for how to tackle [problem]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agree with product team which option to take forward&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take design through assurance workshop &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For very experienced teams you could give even less. This section allows you and them to talk about process and must-dos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For people or more junior teams you can be even more specific and shape how to tackle a problem. And the order. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Map existing entry points&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review user research into entry points&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compile analytics for bounce rates and journeys&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review how other sites provide entry points&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create presentation summarising findings and next steps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review work with [team] at team huddle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key of course isn’t to dictate exactly what to do. It’s to create a strategy for how to solve a problem or make the most of an opportunity. For those with less experience, you give them their tactics. For those with more, you let them devise the tactics, but make sure key things are still covered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this section, whether for yourself, an experienced team or not, you’ve made the tactics clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the situation tells you where you are. And the task how far you want to travel. Then activity is a description of what to bring when you travel. And what route to take. What&amp;rsquo;s left is the ultimate destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section makes clear the outcomes or results you think the work should create. What we should achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the traditional STAR method, it&amp;rsquo;s about measuring success. In this model, it’s about the outcomes you want to create.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s about asking “How do you want to judge success?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can range from metrics like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Reduced drop offs at checkout page by x%”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To task based things like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Got buy-in to redesign triage flow”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find sketching the results out also helps shape the activities too. And it can be useful to write this before the activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with the others, this section is another conversation starter with a team to get a shared sense of success. Of what done looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Creating a size and shape of work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After working through this format. You should have a good sense of the size and shape of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a documented sense of what you know, how far you want to go, what you need to do and what outcomes you want to create from a bit of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format can be a workshop. A team effort or solo enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve found it helpful to shape work for others. To make things clear. And context obvious. Particularly compared to projects that I’ve not used this format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself needing to shape your own work or work for others. Use a format to structure your shaping. Try a format like STAR.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>1 to 1s</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2021/04/20/1-to-1s.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2021/04/20/1-to-1s.html</id>
    <published>2021-04-20T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2021-04-20T21:46:18+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I haven’t had a career full of great experiences of being managed and coached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve worked with lots of brilliant people. But a good manager is not something I’ve commonly experienced. And when I have had good managers they weren’t in similar professions or did similar work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m currently leading and managing a team of 13. So when it’s come to trying to be a good manager there wasn’t a limitless well to go to of examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of what good management or coaching I’ve experienced, I have felt like people had time for me. And had my back. And this is something I want everyone to feel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have things like &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2018/01/08/kanban_for_interaction_design.html"&gt;Kanban boards&lt;/a&gt;, slack channels and weekly huddles. But the 1 to 1 has been the most useful tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking about my experience of “being managed” in other teams, 1 to 1s often felt like boxes to tick. Or a scrambled meeting to be fit in very busy diaries. Or they are done so infrequently that there’s too much to say, so nothing valuable is said at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking to and reading other people’s experiences of managing/being managed, something that was vital was the feeling that the time was important to the manager. That it was dedicated time. More important than the latest part of a service that was on fire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the experience I wanted for my team. Reflecting on how I wanted my team to feel about 1 to 1s with me, I wanted the team to feel:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I was engaged&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That this time was more important than any other thing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That I would be honest, realistic and open&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That they could raise anything to me. Even about me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you can’t just ask the question and expect the answers to flow. To get a process right, I made sure to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Talk to others and look at people’s blogs about 1 to 1s&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Starting with a few people then growing each week&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build in the process a way for the team to shape the agenda not me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have some saved questions. So when something was asked or raised I had ways of coaching. And when nothing was directly raised I could check in on their work and happiness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Write a log of my meetings to see what worked and what did not&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 1 to 1s have been really rewarding. And important to unblocking issues and getting things done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have found out lots of new things about my team. And issues have been raised that wouldn’t have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who I would have said weren’t ambitious or wanted to do more. Had raised hunger. Juniors who I thought wanted more experience in a particular role, wanted experience in another area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I look forward to my 1 to 1s with the team. And from the feedback I’ve got, they do too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re managing or leading a team. Approach your 1 to 1 process like you would any design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t directly manage someone but have a position of seniority or leadership. Bring them in as part of your routine project work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re new to management. Start with 1 to 1s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1 to 1s work if you do the work. Give them the focus they and your team deserve. And don’t be afraid to get things wrong and the change them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Related stuff&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things I read that were useful:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://jasonevanish.com/2014/05/29/101-questions-to-ask-in-1-on-1s/"&gt;101 questions to ask in 1 to 1s&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com/servant-leadership/be-a-manager-3b0e39d87179"&gt;Be a manager&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.designbetter.co/design-leadership-handbook/managing-design-team"&gt;Managing design teams&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Don't let your design system seem complete</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2021/03/26/dont-let-your-design-system-seem-complete.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2021/03/26/dont-let-your-design-system-seem-complete.html</id>
    <published>2021-03-26T07:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2021-04-20T21:31:17+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tosin and Henry from the &lt;a href="https://service-manual.nhs.uk/"&gt;NHS service manual team&lt;/a&gt; shared their recent work at last Thursday’s design huddle &lt;a href="#link-1" id=link-1-ref&gt;&lt;span hidden&gt;Link to explanation of design huddles &lt;/span&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. They covered their work on understanding and improving contributions to the service manual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They shared some of their research. Talking about reasons people don’t contribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the reasons were time, not knowing what &lt;em&gt;contributing&lt;/em&gt; meant and how to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reason revealed after was a feeling that the service manual was “put together by experts”. People feel intimidated. By the manual and from contributing. And that components/patterns were untouchable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This matched something I had been thinking about recently. That the level of authority and professionalism in a design system helps sell it so teams use it. But increases the perception things are fixed. Done. And not open to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shouldn’t be a surprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more professional and finished something is, the less likely people are to add to it. Maybe a typo here and there. This happens with prototypes all the time. The more polished something is, you reduce the type of feedback you get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you do get more fundamental feedback. It’s often a total rejection. Rather than an iteration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when you present something less polished, you get more radical feedback. Feedback that feeds on an idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a fundamental tension for any service manual and design system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The issue with the service manual is, to get people using it. You need to express the same sort of authority and completeness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t sell a design system with a sense of things not being thought of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But doing so you also create a barrier for contribution. Because things look complete. Done. And done by “experts”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s almost an impossible task. But every design system has to balance polish that sells implementation with openness to new ideas. And a sense that components or patterns aren’t final. They’re open to iteration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m looking forward to seeing how the NHS service manual team tackle that balance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you own or feed into a design system. Make sure there’s a sense of openness to change. Be okay to give openness to feedback higher prominence. And show how things are in a state of development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And make sure you do the hard work to dispel that a design system is only created by design system experts. It&amp;rsquo;s created and improved by any and every team that uses it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t let your design system seem complete&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;hr&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="#link-1-ref" id=link-1&gt;&lt;span hidden&gt;Link back to body of text &lt;/span&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; The design huddle is an hour where all designers from NHS Digital get together and share their work or ask for help&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Win the space to design services </title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2021/03/19/win-space-to-design.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2021/03/19/win-space-to-design.html</id>
    <published>2021-03-19T07:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2021-03-19T22:46:39+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve watched a lot of service designers working in programmes and projects where they’re fighting against the tide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re doing that every single day, it&amp;rsquo;s terrible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been very lucky to enjoy the space to do design. And though it’s tempting to think I’m super awesome, something that’s important is winning the space to design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different things can win you the space to do design. From senior buy-in, making the impossible seem possible, to getting stuff made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Leaving aside the reality of senior buy-in, I find that making immediate and visible impact on the frontend of a service is a key building block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By that I mean:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Redesigning a form. Paper or otherwise&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating prototypes that become working code&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Solutions/tweaks to problems identified in live&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Helping explain issues the business or user encounters in live &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A service designer doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be the one to do this work. Though it helps to build trust in a designer. It’s okay to benefit from other people doing this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there’s nothing that sells the value of designers in a room than things like making a transaction less rubbish. Giving a better shape to a product than when no designer was involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something I’m a big fan of is the &lt;a href="https://danskdesigncenter.dk/en/design-ladder-four-steps-design-use"&gt;“Danish Design Centre’s design ladder”&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a model for explaining how companies use design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From not doing it, to it being a form giving act to it shaping strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key thing is to remember that where an organisation, programme or project is, isn’t fixed. And every success can be exploited to get design involved earlier. And more thoughtfully and completely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you find yourself swimming against the tide. Try a smaller scope. A more focused place to make changes. Not every team will be sold on doing things differently. And sometimes that means taking a longer path by starting with the forms. Even if you want to start with strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you know, your users will thank you. It’s a great place to start. And it’ll help you guide the project to doing other things too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re a product/interaction designer. Don’t be afraid to keep pushing to be involved in more. Going beyond just form giving. If you’re a service designer. Don’t be afraid to start in the product and take a team on a journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve lost count of the projects where I joined to help with a website or form and ended changing how a service was delivered or organisation was structured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Win the space to design services.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>A common mistake teams make is designing for a context their users don't have</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2020/12/22/designing-for-context-users-dont-have.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2020/12/22/designing-for-context-users-dont-have.html</id>
    <published>2020-12-22T07:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2021-01-03T14:26:54+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Under time pressure it’s easy to design a service that works for those that understand a problem. But not those that do not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last week or so a team released a question in a service that made sense to people who were doing something daily. But, how the question was written meant that people who did it once a week thought it applied to them. It did not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The team were working under intense pressure. And getting a true outside perspective was hard. They lost sight of the fact that the large majority of the service’s users wouldn’t know the context of their work. Their policy and their question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People answered wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s easy to make this mistake. We&amp;rsquo;ve all made it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There can be many ways a team develops this blindspot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overconfidence&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lack of time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Last minute changes to scope&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Restrictions who you can talk to&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;User research only with users with knowledge of a policy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few questions you can ask yourself or your team to try and guard against making this mistake. Such as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is this service used by people who don’t need to see this question/feature? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What number of people will understand this question? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does this question or flow cater to the majority or a minority of journeys?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is how we are wording a question presume a certain knowledge? And is that knowledge going to be common amongst our users? &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When tasked with rapidly adding an important new journey or new feature it can be easy to give the new thing massive prominence. But new does not mean it’s something that the majority will use. Nor understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can, explore your new feature or question with those that understand. And those that don’t. Your biggest issues will always come from those that don’t understand. From those who don’t match the context you expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the very least ask yourself, is this a feature or question something that the majority will know about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it is not, try to restrict who sees it. Or guard the question by optimising for the 80% journey. Not the minority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understand if your design works for those without context.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Let your headings do the hard work</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2020/07/02/let-your-headings-do-the-hard-work.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2020/07/02/let-your-headings-do-the-hard-work.html</id>
    <published>2020-07-02T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2020-07-02T22:14:40+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The most common improvement I tell teams to make is to tell the user what they need to do in the h1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your h1 will be one of the first things that a user reads. It frames the whole page and everything inside it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though teams know this, I often see the most important thing buried in a paragraph somewhere else. Or in some colourful box trying to compete against the h1 for attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than competing against your h1 by using callout boxes. Let your heading do the hard work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a service is unavailable, or no results were found, put that in the h1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Beyond questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you only have one question on the page, it can be easier for teams to be clear what the user needs to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Which is why &lt;a href="/2019/01/31/one-thing.html"&gt;doing one thing per page&lt;/a&gt; makes it easier to be clear to your user what they need to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to say I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen many teams have a h1 that is different to the question and input on a page. If you find yourself doing this. Make the h1 the question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But sometimes you need to provide several options. Or more information to support a question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you&amp;rsquo;re not writing a heading as a question. Use a verb in your heading to help the user know what you&amp;rsquo;re asking them to do. For example check, enter, tell, select or choose&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing this makes it clear that you want the users to do something. And what it is that you want them to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you don&amp;rsquo;t want the user to do something, but need them to know something. Make the h1 tell the main story. Do not bury the important details. Tell them their message has been sent, appointment cancelled or that you have refunded them £6.99.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t make your h1 compete with the important details. Make it &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; important thing. And never leave the user guessing that you want them to do a thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let your headings do the hard work&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
