<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Andrew Duckworth</title>
  <subtitle>Designer, artist</subtitle>
  <id>https://grillopress.github.io/</id>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2019-06-10T08:30:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Make things open</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/06/10/make-things-open.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/06/10/make-things-open.html</id>
    <published>2019-06-10T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-06-19T22:44:57+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In the last week or so, Sam has written the opt-out service’s accessibility statement. An accessibility statement is a page that explains what accessibility testing you&amp;rsquo;ve done. And any defects you are working through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a big fan of working in the open and being open about your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When planning the work Sam and myself said the definition of done should be to open up our work to our colleagues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So as part of the acceptance criteria we agreed that we’d share the statement on slack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Working in the open&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In writing the statement we made a point of being open. Getting help from several places through our entire process. We had:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read the full policy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Asked the UK Government slack community what they were doing. And to check my understanding of the policy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Looked through an early access version of the GDS template&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Held a design meet up about it to discuss as designers what we were doing and our position on it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aligned our work with what our colleagues around NHS Digital and GDS were doing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Talked the delivery team through the design decisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had also leant on the expertise of users with access needs through our testing partner DAC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Sam had finished writing the accessibility statement she shared it on slack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Opportunities to be open&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the principles I love is &amp;ldquo;make things open, it makes things better&amp;rdquo;. I see it as a ways of working principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many opportunities to be open about your work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using baking a cake as an example there are many stages of being open:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’m hungry, what should I eat? &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; I have these ingredients, what should I cook?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’m thinking about cooking a cake. What cake should I cook?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’m making this cake, any advice? &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; Would you like to do it with me?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’m cooking a cake, does this look right?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I’ve cooked my cake, what do you think? (Would you like a slice?)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My cakes are very dense, what could I do that&amp;rsquo;s different?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Here’s what I did to cook that cake&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is every opportunity to be open with your work. Be it with your team, or those beyond it. Choose an opportunity. It may not be as delicious as cake, but being working in the open makes your work better.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Week 08</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/31/discovery-notes-08.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/31/discovery-notes-08.html</id>
    <published>2019-05-31T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-06-19T22:46:29+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;All over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovery finished. Our work has been compiled into a board report. Planning to write it up publicly eventually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not this week. &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Week 07</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/24/discovery-notes-07.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/24/discovery-notes-07.html</id>
    <published>2019-05-24T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-05-28T08:14:40+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s difficult now would have been impossible before&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Week started in crunch mode trying to get the prototype ready for the lab on Tuesday. Most of the bits were there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly I was all across Leeds for a lot of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed the prototype with Sam. She took lead on the part of the prototype for the last lab activity. We sketched out the flow together. Two questions but if they answered yes to any one of them the system would get a little more complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She did an amazing job. There was some tricky logic to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Lots of likes but no needs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the lab users were very complimentary about the prototype service. But none of them had thought, never mind tried, to solve the issue it was attempting to meet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their politeness about the service was nice. But it was all &lt;em&gt;nice&lt;/em&gt; to have and nothing they&amp;rsquo;d drop things to do. Or need to do before they could drop things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be very easy to be persuaded by people saying they&amp;rsquo;d use a service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or that something they&amp;rsquo;re interacting with is interesting and means something to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But people say things but behave very differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The user is in a strange room with strange people interacting with a strange system asking strange things. It&amp;rsquo;s natural behaviour to be nice and say pleasant things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key of course is to really watch people&amp;rsquo;s behaviour. Before and after interacting with a thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The service wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to meet any need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
  &lt;img src="/images/real-needs.png"/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Some sort of visual metaphor for users solving problems because they have a need &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The strategy is delivery (but not this thing)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, there&amp;rsquo;s no strong need for the service. It makes our system more coherent. But it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t do much better than:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improved signposting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;better content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fixing some plumbing and internal processes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &amp;ldquo;online&amp;rdquo; service wouldn&amp;rsquo;t deliver the benefits in a sustainable way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course trust, accountability and openness with health data isn&amp;rsquo;t a thing you decide not to do. But there are more effective steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving people control and sight of their health records is, from what we&amp;rsquo;ve seen from people, the better first step.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Week 06</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/17/discovery-notes-06.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/17/discovery-notes-06.html</id>
    <published>2019-05-17T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-05-21T07:41:20+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Very busy week. Wake up at 4 in the morning thinking about work type of busy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some good news (eventually) on Monday. Now a &lt;em&gt;senior&lt;/em&gt; designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend asked what that means. Doing the same things I think. And helping out on a new project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did a lot of user research as a team this week. Two pop-ups and two workshops. With a lab and a patient panel planned the week after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Busy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s hard work making this simple&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of time spent discussing, exploring and trying to make the log of where NHS digital shares data simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Found it hard to make it simple to grasp what data has been shared, to who and why. Without adding unimportant noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In isolation the things aren&amp;rsquo;t difficult. But the ordering and interconnected bits are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one data sharing agreement you may have your data shared as part of 40 different datasets. All to help a local area evaluate and plan services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size, shape and structure of every data sharing agreement is unique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just don&amp;rsquo;t want people to have to know how the system works to see how the system is working for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;d also help if the content wasn&amp;rsquo;t so academic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Your job is to help the organisation make better decisions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About a year ago a team from GDS came to the digital delivery centre and I walked round with them for a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talked a little about adopting more agile ways of working within programmes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the guests asked a good question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;How are you helping the programme make better decisions?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t a question I didn&amp;rsquo;t have an answer to. But it was one of those that stuck with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The depth to which you can answer this question is a sign of your impact as a designer or researcher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working in agile ways means you make decisions more often. You respond to change. You test things. You make change possible and at a lower cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a designer you ask questions and force decisions. But you need to be purposeful about your work and ask yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What decision is my work helping to make?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I help make that decision?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I help make the best decision for the user and the organisation?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re likely to get pushback when you start working like this. More so if you&amp;rsquo;re working beyond how something &amp;ldquo;looks&amp;rdquo; or how the interface works. People will challenge why a designer is caring about certain decisions or business process. But your job is to challenge thought processes and deliver value. If you&amp;rsquo;re not challenging you&amp;rsquo;re probably not designing for a better outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday we had a show and tell that I felt forced a decision and delivered the evidence to make a better choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end we&amp;rsquo;d agreed what evidence was left to capture and what we needed to do to finalise a decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But also how to communicate that finding beyond our organisation so the whole system stops repeating the same research and finding the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Week 05</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/10/discovery-notes-04.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/10/discovery-notes-04.html</id>
    <published>2019-05-10T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-05-13T23:41:03+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Failed to make any notes for the last week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some stuff happening that made it emotionally quite exhausting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Better API&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovery wise I finally cracked the API I was exploring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turned out I was seeing a spreadsheet that was only a summary. What someone thought was what I would be interested in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fields were right but some of the details I wanted were missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Went from “your data was part of the A&amp;amp;E dataset” to tracking exact bits of data shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a user this means we could be clearer about what identifiable stuff is shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of “we shared details that personally identify you” we can give more context. Postcodes were shared because the study was about a specific area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looked like the API available would need lots of love. Processes might still do. But less to overhaul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Getting stuff out of my head&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest sins you see in meetings is overeager solution designing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Is this a problem?” is often lost the second you have a solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean, if you have a solution, course there’s a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than criticising people it’s helpful to ask questions to get back to the problem. Or take a solution as a set of assumptions or research questions to tackle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond meetings solutions can hang around in the mind. Particularly when trying to explore if a problem is significant or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was causing some issues for me when exploring the API. It was quite easy to think of solutions to things that aren’t needed. And take what’s possible and engineer experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of this rattled around my mind all week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Took Friday to purge some of it. Get it out on paper. Sketch some components and flows so they didn’t rattle around and get in the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the ideas and solutions are down I&amp;rsquo;m not worrying about them. They&amp;rsquo;re a bunch of assumptions and I&amp;rsquo;m taking them as material to form research questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put things to bed by getting them out of your head.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Prototyping in shorthand</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/04/writing-shorthand.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/04/writing-shorthand.html</id>
    <published>2019-05-04T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-05-09T08:34:40+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in my last &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/03/discovery-notes-03.html"&gt;discovery notes&lt;/a&gt; I like to write up pages in a shorthand method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t something that only I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was helping out in services week for &amp;ldquo;formapalooza&amp;rdquo; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Ralph_Hawkins"&gt;Ralph Hawkins&lt;/a&gt; spoke about the format he used in Google docs to write pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format follows the shapes of interface elements using:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;div class="dl_element"&gt;
    &lt;dt&gt;Radio buttons&lt;/dt&gt;
    &lt;dd&gt;(&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;)&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="dl_element"&gt;
    &lt;dt&gt;Checkboxes&lt;/dt&gt;
    &lt;dd&gt;[&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;]&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="dl_element"&gt;
    &lt;dt&gt;Input fields&lt;/dt&gt;
    &lt;dd&gt;[&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;]&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="dl_element"&gt;
    &lt;dt&gt;Buttons&lt;/dt&gt;
    &lt;dd&gt;[ Continue ]&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do this too. But I like to add a few markdown elements as well, so &lt;code&gt;#&lt;/code&gt;&amp;lsquo;s for headings. So:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="list-unstyled"&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;# Heading one&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;## Heading two&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;### Heading three&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means I like to write pages like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
# Make your choice

You need to choose what you're going to have for tea.

It's really important.

## What do you want for tea?

( ) Curry
( ) Chips and sausages
( ) Pizza

[ Continue ]

&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Write in this format or similar in a sharable doc and you’ve got a way for a whole team to work together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can even use document editor styles like links.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using shorthand makes it easy for two designers to collaborate on screens. Or for other members of the team or other teams to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use Google docs, word or a notes app. It’s a quick way of prototyping screens and flows. It’ll help you focus on the important bits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the words and questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the structure and flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and ultimately, if your service meets a need&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
