<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2018-05-25T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 07</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/05/25/weeknotes-07.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/05/25/weeknotes-07.html</id>
    <published>2018-05-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-05-29T21:18:11+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started early.  Created two prototypes. Exploring different cookie consent banners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One with a simplified yes/no choice. Another that gave users more control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shared the prototypes with the rest of the “Cookie cutters” for feedback. Rather than chuck some hypotheses and proto-personas at the group, I arranged a call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shared the “NHS number” prototype with that team as well. Got given the analytics code to add and talked through research options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my daily standup with Thunderbird I had the research planning call. Discussed the hypotheses behind the two versions of the cookie banner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hadn’t ever worked with the researchers before. You take for granted the chemistry you have with people. But the team was great and we quickly got on the same page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked through the ideas. Shaped the research plan. Some questions were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What users thought the banner was about?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What (if anything) they thought the banner was asking them to do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How they interacted with the banner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did they know what cookies were?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much did they know about GDPR?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which prototype model did they prefer? Why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What did they understand they were agreeing to?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What they understood by &amp;ldquo;third-party&amp;rdquo; and other terms?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan was to get people with a range of digital skills through a pop-up in a library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The researchers, Ana and Antonia, thought testing a third prototype would help them. So I got to crafting it while they shared the updated research plan in the Cookie cutter slack group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jumped onto verifying the service for go-live. Caught an issue with the footer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started an interaction flow in Sketch for the NHS number prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Took a call with programme about cookies and analytics for the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked to a developer on the gov.uk slack about why they needed their NHS number. They’d asked in a channel where you could find it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Late in the day heard back from the researchers with the pop-up results. We got six people through. Between the two concepts, users preferred having more immediate control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users understood what was being asked of them. And had heard about &amp;ldquo;cookies&amp;rdquo;. But they felt somewhat confused over the implications of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of this issue was that I had thrown the words together. And they weren’t great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other issue was that we were exploring the need for consent to advert placement/tracking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a scenario where you are asking people a simpler question, the binary yes/no option would excel. But, we had a scenario where we had finer grained layers. And as such, people liked that to be transparent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next iteration was then to fold in what we had learnt about simplifying the language. As well as drilling further into how to let people make an informed decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More prototyping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dug into the cookies we were using. How to categorise them to something that’s easy to understand and doesn’t rely on web concepts or web terms. Tried to simplify things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We shifted to terms we thought were more commonly understood. Things like “social media”. (Yes, still too vague&amp;hellip;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explored addition concepts like “just in time” consent. This was more of a proof of concept. Not something we tested immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finished off the NHS number service interaction flow. Added more detail on errors and loops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got the final feedback on pop-up sessions for the latest prototypes. Progress on simplifying the concepts we are trying to get across to people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our design worked well. But we had an issue again with the language. Recent Facebook and Cambridge Analytica stories changed how people perceived a few terms. Moving in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improved the cookie banner based on the user feedback. Packaged up the prototype for implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the morning met up with a colleague from London to talk navigation. Love chatting to Graham but don’t get to talk face to face much. Nice change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Met up with Ben. Took the opportunity to grab lunch. Talked through some stuff we were working on. Respecting context in interaction design amongst other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked to Adam from the Cookie cutter crew. Caught up with the implementation of the cooke banner. He&amp;rsquo;d made great progress on two versions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Said hello to an NHS graduate I met during the GDS course. Caught up how she was. What she is moving onto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught up with Ruth the product owner for the new NHS number service. Talked through where the service could live if it is a goer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shared the wireflow kit I used to create the NHS number interaction flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though not announced until Friday, the Thunderbird team put the service live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All things healthy and good to go. Nice moment. Particularly for a small team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Took a bit of time to go deeper into the error validation and messaging for the NHS number prototype. With a small window until MVP it’s key to explore the end to end journey. Dead-ends and things we left too late on my current service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked to a content designer colleague about help text and dropdowns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shared some stuff we found in user testing. She also suggested some stuff. Improvements for the service and new prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got sight of some of the launch day comms. It had changed quite a bit from last time. The plan was to announce the service in every national newspaper. As well as places like radio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of speakers for the weekly design meetup had had to drop out. Life got in the way. I presented on a recent issue. Had planned for the chat to end with a sketching session. But debate and discussion took us to a more strategic than interface level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launch day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colleagues collected newspaper cuttings and shared where they had seen the service advertised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did a little more on error messages. This time some validation rules for the prototype and then wording on end-pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helped the Thunderbird team on a range of issues and queries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chased up on some questions I had asked. Given some content for the service but bounced it back asking for clarification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Went for lunch with the team and later in the day some drinks. Celebrated launching a service with a small, talented and motivated team.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 06</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/05/18/weeknotes-06.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/05/18/weeknotes-06.html</id>
    <published>2018-05-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-05-20T17:37:20+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivery Centre UX team update. Caught up in a meeting beforehand so turned up a few minutes late. Always enjoy hearing what colleagues are up to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later on got a very direct design requirement. One that came with the caveat that without it, no live service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me it was a solution we had no idea of the impact of that tried to solve a problem we had little to no evidence for. Pushed back but got told in no uncertain terms it wasn&amp;rsquo;t up for negotiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knocked me for six.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crafted up some HTML for a new privacy notice for the Thunderbird team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a great discussion with the Thunderbird developers later about an API we use. A small chat with the team. Thrashing out and balancing user experience and technical possibility. A great team co-design session amongst a sea of uncertainty and confusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of those moments you feel like as a team you could conquer anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Catch up meeting with the user research team first thing. Talking through some things that will be coming our way. Mitigating some issues going forward and planning the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got an answer back RE: cookies and stuff for the 25th. Plot thickens a little but a clearer choice forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got asked a question. In light of the requirement on Monday I felt the need to state my opinion. Without reservation. Took my time to highlight precedence and GDS standards. Squashed the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Felt empowered I must admit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saw the impact of Monday&amp;rsquo;s design requirement&amp;rsquo;s on the service when a few colleagues opened the most recent prototype. It was a little bit like watching a car crash. It was a brutal insight into the confusion the design change will have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I thought I was losing sleep over the issue before, this really worried me. On the train home I started drafting notes on how to reverse this requirement. Or mitigate some of the confusion it was causing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the day finishing off an email highlighting my case against the requirement. Built a case. Laid out the various ways forward. And prayed the email landed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helped kickstart a small project team &amp;ldquo;cookie cutters&amp;rdquo; swarm on stuff for the 25th May and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jumped on various issues throughout the day. Lots of pivots and changes. Many unneeded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prepared the ground work for a different project prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meeting with lead researcher and product owner on new &amp;ldquo;NHS number&amp;rdquo; project. Talked about a few issues. Doing one thing per page and the central hypothesis behind the first prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walked through something I had crafted together on the train into Leeds. Benefit of having a prototyping kit where you can glue things together to test and explore ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changed up how I built this one in response to picking through the GDS kit. Doing more of the routing stuff on the server rather than on the frontend. Will see if it makes it more flexible for me or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had to jump onto an urgent call. At the end of the call reiterated my points about the requirement I disagreed with. Laid out my position. Final decision was with the senior responsible officer (SRO) later in the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ran across to the NHS Digital design away day. Heard lots of interesting stories. Saw lots of great designs in response to many challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got to meet up with lots of friends and the cool people from NHS BSA again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really enjoyed the guest talk from the NHS BSA team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saw a pattern throughout the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those that shared their work early and often had a maturity and coherence to their work compared to those that didn&amp;rsquo;t. It&amp;rsquo;s the key to being a good designer. It&amp;rsquo;s hard. It&amp;rsquo;s scary. But sharing your work will make it better. Particularly before you hit that &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m comfortable with this&amp;rdquo; stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to have a great chat over lunch as I had to jump onto another urgent call. Bit upset. But that&amp;rsquo;s what happens when you are launching a national service in a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a great day though. Always feel sad when the day is over. Never enough time to talk to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walk back to the train station had a good chat with a colleague or two. Issues shared. Truths told.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my train back I heard news about the hard requirement I emailed about on Wednesday was being reversed. Moment of great relief. Promised to investigate the concern that caused the requirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can stop losing sleep over it now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also had a good chat about cookies and GDPR and what stuff needs to happen to explore the impact of that too. Plans made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finished off the first prototype for the new &amp;ldquo;NHS Number&amp;rdquo; project. Pretty happy with it all things considered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crafted up some screens for the cookie project. Wrote up and modelled some proto-personas. Evaluated and ranked some needs. Balanced user needs, business requirements and potential clinical risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When your website visitors may be having a heart attack. Or their child is struggling to breathe you have a duty not to get things wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explored the screens against various websites and pages. Judging the solution against different styles of page. And in different scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shared preliminary stuff with the cookie cutters. Tweaked a few things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day then went a bit south. Ended up watching my wife connected to all sorts of machines and tests. Frustrating and very long day. All fine in the end. At times it didn&amp;rsquo;t sound like it would end well.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 05</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/05/11/weeknotes-05.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/05/11/weeknotes-05.html</id>
    <published>2018-05-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-05-15T21:43:25+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bank holiday. Spent it in Cheshire. Sadly felt really ill for most of the day :/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked from home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looked into an issue with our analytics during public beta. We need to be clearer on capturing consent. Right now we don’t capture it quite to the standard needed (Post May 25th). There is an organisation-wide solution but it may not actually be ready for our cutoff. Asked a question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tweaked a couple of things on a prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got back to a colleague who had some questions about how we had evolved our site&amp;rsquo;s navigation. Hypothesis driven design to the rescue again. Every change we’ve used a set way of recording changes and the reasons for them. You can find more info on &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2017/12/10/hypothesis-driven-design.html"&gt;how we do Hypothesis driven design in this blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sketched some potential solutions. Issue being how we handle important offline forms for very specialist groups. Mocked a few things up. Trying to find something that is sustainable. Something that can deal with shifting requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a meeting with the programme and NHSUK team about progress for go live. After that did a technical review of the pages. Caught a couple of small issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked a little on my part of the &amp;ldquo;Making UX Agile&amp;rdquo; talk. Emma Harvey (Head of Product) and I got asked if we could take the show on the road to Agile Manchester. Got told we had extremely positive reviews at UX in the City.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential audience was quite different.  So, although the narrative remained similar, I wanted to nail down the main takeaways. See Thursday for those!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Manchester for &amp;ldquo;Agile Manchester&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Couldn&amp;rsquo;t quite get into the swing of the event due to other work stuff. Was there with my delivery manager and she also had quite a few things to attend to as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had to duck out of the keynote to make an iteration on a prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught an interesting talk from John Clapham called &amp;ldquo;Kaizen to Karõshi - sustainable pace and performance in teams&amp;rdquo;. Effectively, how and why people burn out. How agile can actually be an excuse for some bad behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Made me pause for thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look after yourself, and each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Co-presented after lunch. Our talk was called &lt;a href="http://agilemanchester.net/2018/sessions/index.php?session=503"&gt;Making UX truly agile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talked about our journey. Starting from an agile-ish team but with some massive silos. To a well-connected, lean agile design into dev team. We&amp;rsquo;re facing new challenges everyday. But the team feels able to rise to the challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was the only designer in the room. We had a mixture of developers, delivery staff and agile coaches. I asked how many people had experience of working with designers they felt were &amp;ldquo;agile&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;lean&amp;rdquo;. I got one half hand-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Room to improve designers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main points in the talk were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;1. Focus on the quality of conversations you have, much more than the quantity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make it easy to say things of substance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go where the conversations are happening&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;don’t do things - like stand ups etc. - because “that’s how we do things here”. Make sure they’re adding value. If they’re not, change it up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;talk less, say more. Listen twice as much as you speak up and when you do, make sure it is productive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if it feels like it would be awkward or difficult to talk about an issue, talk about it twice as much. Get things in the open. Get things cleaned up and sorted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if you get a gut feeling like “really need to catch up with X”. Do it. Don’t delay&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do this and have less &amp;ldquo;WTF?&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Why wasn&amp;rsquo;t I told&amp;rdquo; moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;2. You&amp;rsquo;ll never make design agile on your own&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you are the sole designer or have one designer in the team, you&amp;rsquo;ll need help. Empower your team to think about the user. Everyone impacts on the design. In exploration or implementation. Get everyone involved. Make it everyone&amp;rsquo;s problem with yourself (or your designer) as the lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduce user outcomes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;talk about it a lot and use the same language all the time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;talk about users beyond the &amp;ldquo;UI&amp;rdquo; stuff. Non-functional things like security and performance are UX issues too!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;invite everyone to user research and design stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proactively engage and elaborate design things with the development team. Be it your BA, product owner, developer or whatever. Co-craft the implementation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do this and you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to not only &amp;ldquo;keep ahead&amp;rdquo; of the development, but see what&amp;rsquo;s coming up. See what hasn&amp;rsquo;t been thought about. And spend less time telling people &amp;ldquo;you didn&amp;rsquo;t implement that right&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saving you time and energy to reinvest in the service or product you are building. And your own mental wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;3. Treat your design process like a design problem. Create, iterate, test, iterate, test, iterate, test&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Master your design workflow. Be sure how to take a problem and turn it into an outcome for your user. Make your process repeatable so you can keep iterating your design and iterating your service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;work out a simple stepped flow on how you finish a piece of design work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;add phases you&amp;rsquo;d like or should have (document, design review etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use your process. Iterate. Test. Explore what works&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of building a process, &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2018/01/08/kanban_for_interaction_design.html"&gt;I wrote up more about how we used a Kanban board to do just that in this blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have a process ask yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What works?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What could you do better?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is too zoomed in? What am I obsessing over?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is too high level? What is important but isn&amp;rsquo;t being captured?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where am I holding things up?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Am I finishing things before starting the next lot of work?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where and when do I get design tasks from?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And don&amp;rsquo;t forget to share your process. Talk about it to everyone who will listen. Share it early and often. It&amp;rsquo;s the only way to get better at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;4. There will always be a tension between design and delivery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is okay. Design tries to get things right. And delivery is about making a thing real. There is always a need to balance making the right thing and making something real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll never know for sure if something works until it is used by real people. So get something out in front of a user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being agile as a designer, or doing agile design, is about finding that path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bit intense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our lead developer announced at standup he would be moving on. Really gutted to hear. He&amp;rsquo;s been great to work with and I will miss him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To prepare for go live we had loads of attention and requests flying in. Very hectic day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll leave it at that :)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 04</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/05/04/weeknotes-04.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/05/04/weeknotes-04.html</id>
    <published>2018-05-04T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-05-07T21:51:02+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the week with some urgent medical care. My own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After dealing with that, jumped on some frontend tickets for the Thunderbird team. Updated the interruption card in the live service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw some mixed results using the latest version of the &amp;ldquo;interruption card&amp;rdquo;. It was either not interrupting enough or people were clicking icons. We had hoped that icons would make the card more arresting. But it has not. If anything, it made it more like a graphical element that people skipped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started on updating the error messages for the live service too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finished the error messages for pubic beta. Making the service&amp;rsquo;s error messages more actionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asked in the gov slack for advice. Got &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1mbQPc_YATKR4h7inHMDvE8OLor7crEGP7f7Qd_QszqA/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;some great practical advice about writing error messages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked through screen recordings of the service. Digesting the feedback from the private beta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helped a colleague help a graduate prepare for an internal interview. Always enjoy helping others see how great they are. But also pushing them further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrote and presented at a show and tell. Great to see the researchers work through their findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I updated the wider project on the interruption card and upcoming design work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
  &lt;img src="/images/research_beta.png" alt="Two user researchers standing in front of a television screen"/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Emma and Katharine bossing it at the show and tell.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked on some more frontend cards for the Thunderbird team. This time SMS messages and emails. Took a chunk of the day. Had other personal stuff to deal with too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got some good news from some recruitment work I had helped lead on earlier in the year. Passed on that good news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sent an email to the programme setting out my understanding of what to do for Friday. Took a few phonecalls to uncover requirements and pragmatic approaches going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the day with another call. Explored final content requirements and pragmatic approaches going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Halfway through the day got asked my opinion on some ministerial feedback. Dug out some stats from the private beta period to back up my position. Things like scroll depth, user journeys etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a few phonecalls to sort a range of issues that sprung out of that. Helped define a few small prototypes that could be of use to explore certain issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked on those for first thing Friday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finished four prototypes. Three for the minister in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sent a final call on the content and offline forms. Got all the content and packaged it up for a baselined prototype for the NHSUK team. Ready for go live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Received some updated terms and conditions for the live service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helped a junior colleague go through the process to make changes to the live service. Folding in a small content correction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exhausting end to a very exhausting week.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 03</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/04/28/weeknotes-03.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/04/28/weeknotes-03.html</id>
    <published>2018-04-28T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-04-29T16:47:37+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yet another busy week. Something of a pattern for April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the week finishing off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Error messages. Form downloads for the offline service. Helping the Thunderbird team update the transactional service with some small tweaks. Bit of career management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helped get a grad I met at the GDS training in touch with Thunderbird&amp;rsquo;s talented delivery manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spent lunch with a friend from a different team. Ended up in a random Italian place. Talked about the tension of delivery and delivering the right thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Met with the service owner. Thrashed out how we are going to help all the teams on the same page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Folded in the new HTML email design into the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got told I had to use a real life photo on a slack instance. So, used the first one in my phone. Got trolled hard. Obviously just too saucy. Too Mills and Boon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class="noir right"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/mills_and_boon.png" alt="A joke mock-up of a Mills and Boon romance novel called 'Kanban at midnight' feating Andrew Duckworth's face"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Available in all good bookstores&amp;hellip; Thanks Dean ;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lost count of the amount of people who told me the photo made me look fatter. Thanks. I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spent some time with the user researchers. Ever since we had to move offices, the whole team hasn&amp;rsquo;t been able to sit together. Although Slack helps. For some people you need to get together face to face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked through the private beta findings. We used &lt;a href="https://www.usability.gov/how-to-and-tools/methods/system-usability-scale.html"&gt;&amp;ldquo;System Usability Scale&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; as well as a comprehension survey. Great usability scores. SUS scores place the service in the top 90%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comprehension is a worry. There was a recent phrase change that we can point to as causing a drop in comprehension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoyed going through the screen recordings. Will build the findings into a show and tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Met with communications teams from various parts of the organisation. Working out how to help coordinate any old content and how that gets updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked to a GDS designer about their prototyping kit. Some of the reasoning behind certain design decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prototyping kit is a tool that brings patterns into life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, less is often more. If you have too many patterns, or too low a bar for a pattern you increase the potential for teams to put in place things that are going to fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, too few, or too high a bar for a pattern, then people will do what they need to do to get the job done right now. Often at the expense of the bigger picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got asked to produce something for the minister. Asked for clarity on a few things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a meeting with the service owner and content designer. Went through the transactional service. Talked errors, issues to implementation, emails and planning for planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Met up with a new designer, Alexandra. Working on the buying catalogue. A market place tool for procurement for CCGs. Interesting stuff. Hard challenges. Loads of potential. Was great to meet her. Had many questions about styles, patterns and standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also talked about measuring usability and comprehension and how to get that in place for alpha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large planning meeting with programme, Head of Product and Thunderbird tribe. Pretty productive. No fuss. Bit worried about the level of work I am touching on in the next few weeks. Need to sketch a plan of action. Will pair up with another designer again to get some of the design work into the product for the deadline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside planning had to pull in some changes for a prototype for
the minister. Took a fair chunk of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got invited to talk at Agile Manchester. Taking &lt;a href="http://uxinthecity.net/2018/manchester/sessions/index.php?session=311"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Making UX Agile&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; on tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Owned a lot of flexitime. Took some. Alongside a little bit of work on the prototype and the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spent some time exploring the GDS prototype kit and the inner workings. With the aim to pull in some features into my personal kit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learnt lots from all the prototypes I&amp;rsquo;ve built since early October last year for NHS Digital. Important not to get hung up on all the hacks. Also important to learn from them and make life easier next time.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 02</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/04/20/weeknotes-02.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/04/20/weeknotes-02.html</id>
    <published>2018-04-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-04-22T14:59:08+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another busy week. Worked through some issues in implementing the service&amp;rsquo;s site on the NHSUK platform. Spent some time learning how GDS and gov.uk do design in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the week talking design principles. We have some draft NHS design principles up on the wall in the Digital Delivery Centre. Right now we have nine principles. To kickstart conversation I asked what two principles people would remove. We had a pretty healthy debate.  It was interesting to see slight differences between interaction and service designers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the principles may actually be better described as behaviours.  “What makes someone a good designer” rather than “what makes something a good design”. Something to think about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran into Stephen Corbett who was in his last week. Talked about service design with him and the world of “UX”. Going to miss Stephen. Always good fun and a smart mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a sprint retrospective with the Thunderbird tribe. Then walked through some storyboards for a side project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attended the Digital Delivery Centre experience design team meet up. Talked about the progress of the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked from home. Crafted a sitemap for the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcomed new member of the design community via Slack. Always make a point to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Travelled down to London later in the day. Had a 40 min delay due to a passenger medical emergency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got to my hotel fine. Right next to the tower of London and tower bridge. Missed out on being able to catch my brother before he left work and a friend. Worked out meeting my friend on Thursday though. Next time I have to stay over in London I will arrange something with a friend or a colleague beforehand. Felt bored. Had a wonder and took some photos to relieve the boredom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/london/tower_bridge.jpg" alt="Tower Bridge in black and white with heavy shadows"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a wonder up to Whitechapel after strolling around St Katharine’s. Beautiful place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First day of the GDS course. Talking principles, user stories, service design and journey mapping. Before getting into interaction flows with Tim Paul. Some of the day seemed out of sync. We did journey mapping before research. Seemed in the wrong order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a great lunch from a local street market. £5 for a massive chicken tikka roll, meat samosa and a drink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src="/images/london/team_with_tikka.jpg" alt="Four designers eating Chicken tikka wraps in a street market"/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="noir"&gt;Street food on a Yorkshire budget&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoyed spending the day with a group of people doing digital stuff for government. Paired with a graduate from NHS Digital, Sam as well. Enjoyed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a night out with the team from NHS Digital. Had a blast. Pizza. Beers and good company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next day at the training started with content design. Sam shone here. It’s always great to see people doing what they love. We also heard from Ed “from slack” Horsford about the journey to create the passport service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed doing an interaction design review with Tim Paul. Piped up a little too much. Particularly here. But interaction design is my jam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later on after work met a friend. Had some beers by the river. Funny how far we’d come from when we first met in a small publishing company in Birmingham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last day in London. Started it early by touring around the City of London and enjoying the sights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="half"&gt;
  &lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/london/noir_gerk.jpg" alt="The Gherkin building in London in black and white with heavy shadows"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Gherkin. Always swamped and surrounded by other buildings but standing out by its shape.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/london/lloyds.jpg" alt="The Lloyd's building in London in black and white with heavy shadows"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Lloyd&amp;rsquo;s building. Brutally showing its bowels.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training was about using the gov.uk prototyping kit. A couple of the NHS Digital grads didn&amp;rsquo;t get IT to put the kit on their machines. Tried to use a browser based option. But all the platforms had issues. Either with gulp.js (glitch) or with a need for a credit card (Cloud9, Koding) or some bizarre no access to a terminal on free accounts (codio).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bit frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I paired with one of the graduates and let her use my machine. It was great to see the GDS designers and frontenders there to help. Being able to cobble together an interactive prototype is a fun and powerful thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The room benefitted from there being plenty of examples in the kit as well. Lots of lessons for NHS Digital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had to catch up and jump into many conversations through the day about my normal work. Found it a touch stressful as the project is gearing up to go live and not being in Leeds.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
