<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Andrew Duckworth</title>
  <subtitle>Designer, artist</subtitle>
  <id>https://grillopress.github.io/</id>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2023-10-11T19:14:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Codesign and the carnivalesque</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/10/11/codesign-and-the-carnivalesque.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/10/11/codesign-and-the-carnivalesque.html</id>
    <published>2023-10-11T19:14:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2023-10-11T19:45:33+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Codesign is popular thing right now. I’ve heard it from lots of different corners of programme, project and delivery management. Nevermind research and design worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like codesign. It’s about involving the people who are impacted by your design in the design process. Of opening up and evening out power to create. But it’s something that gets said a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The promise of codesign is great. But the reality of how it’s done is often not so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of codesign reminds me of the “carnivalesque”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The carnivalesque&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The carnivalesque is a literary and cultural concept. It refers to a temporary mode of subversion and rebellion against social norms and conventions. It originated from the medieval carnival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/pieter-bruegel.jpeg" alt="Carnival and debauchery on show in a painting from Pieter Bruegel the Elder, painted during the 16th century."/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Some sort of carnivalesque prototype of a knight going on in a Pieter Bruegel the Elder painting&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The carnival was a time when people would gather and engage in fun. Including role reversals, plays, masks, and other forms of transgression. The carnivalesque was a moment in time where roles are reversed. Activities that allowed people to challenge and undermine established hierarchies and power structures. Often by inverting or parodying them. And I&amp;rsquo;m sure often with lots of food and drink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the carnivalesque, the boundaries between sacred and profane, and normal and abnormal are blurred or even reversed. This leads to a sense of liberation and freedom. People are encouraged to express themselves and act outside of their usual roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jokes are had. Fun things take place. You get away from your normal roles and position in things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What codesign and the carnivalesque share&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of codesign and cocreation can be like the carnivalesque in several ways. Both involve a sense of playfulness and experimentation. People are encouraged to explore different ideas and possibilities in a non-conventional way. Like the carnivalesque, codesign and cocreation allow for the breaking down of barriers. And the crossing of boundaries between different disciplines, perspectives, and ways of thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both codesign and cocreation are collaborative processes. They involve a collective effort to create something new and innovative. This collaboration often leads to a disruption of traditional power structures. Participants are given an equal voice and agency in the design process. This is like carnivalesque’s inversion of power hierarchies and its emphasis on collective participation and democratic decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True carnivalesque is about unmanaged, unrefined sense of upheaval and fun bubbling under the surface that at any moment can strike hard at false certainties. Getting rid of “that’s how it works”. The carnivalesque is about upending roles. The lords become the peasants and those without power become the lords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of design tools and techniques attempt to use this. None more so than codesign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is where codesign is the most powerful. Where it recreates this feeling. Where people who are typically excluded from decision making are in the room. The excluded are now making and producing with equal power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The shared flaws and limits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However. As with anything where there’s a transfer of power from those that have it to those that don&amp;rsquo;t. It’s scary. People will ask for “unrealistic things”. A strength. But also a threat. And with any threatening things, a risk to minimise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In organisations that are risk adverse. This happens all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, codesign doesn’t happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or if it does. It doesn’t actually influence or change anything beyond the moment of fun. Relegated to an hour of hope, exchanged in the long term for pessimism and sense that was a bloody waste of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if that feels dramatic. I’ve seen it plenty. With people faithfully wanting to create the conditions to use what comes out of the chaos of codesign. But those in power having no acceptance or readiness to share power. Or take the fruits of codesign forward. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teams, communities and organisations then learn (rightfully) to distrust those with power. To roll their eyes. To say “we’ve heard this before”. And then they shun the next chance. Turning down any tickets to the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And who’d blame them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also the main criticism of carnivaleseque. It isn’t something that creates lasting change. When the carnival closes everything goes back to the way it was. It’s not changing things in a lasting way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Codesign offers so much. But be careful that you can live up to the offer you make people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time you’re encouraging your users and communities to get involved. And take a codesign approach. Ask yourself: does your codesign project promise the carnival but leave your participants feeling like clowns?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>User stories arent the tale for discovery</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/09/29/user-stories-arent-the-tale-for-discovery.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/09/29/user-stories-arent-the-tale-for-discovery.html</id>
    <published>2023-09-29T18:59:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2023-09-29T19:40:02+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From the volume of blog posts. Show and tell decks and confluence pages you’d think that writing user needs in user story formats would be the road to success. And though it’s a method that some teams find useful it’s not something I ever advocate. And particularly not when a team is exploring what problems to solve (problem discovery).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;User needs in user story format, with their &amp;ldquo;As a [user], I want [action] so that [benefit]&amp;rdquo; structure, tend to cram needs into a narrow solutionised scope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is their point. But to do so they fudge complex things into bite-sized chunks. In discovery or as a vehicle to document the messy reality of a user&amp;rsquo;s needs, it means missing the broader picture. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A user story might encapsulate a single user&amp;rsquo;s immediate desire, but it often fails to reflect the collective needs and aspirations of the entire user base. Or the context and why behind the how.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;User needs aren’t really a single thing. &lt;a href="https://www.myddelton.co.uk/blog/research-heresies"&gt;They’re a complex patchwork&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;User needs in user story formats tend to emphasize &amp;ldquo;how&amp;rdquo; over &amp;ldquo;why.&amp;rdquo; They fixate on the solution before understanding the problem. This can lead to a rush toward building features without a deep comprehension of the underlying issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like building things. I like solving problems. So I need to make sure I&amp;rsquo;m solving the right problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To address user needs effectively, it’s best to spend some time to uncover the root causes of pain points. And give yourself and the team a pause before getting into solving a problem. This way you avoid just recreating whatever burning platform or missed opportunity you’re trying to patch up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Problem statements can offer a more thoughtful approach by succinctly articulating the core issues and context. Other techniques like journey maps or storyboards that provide a visual narrative of the user&amp;rsquo;s entire experience can also be useful. Helping the team and related teams or stakeholders to share in the uncovering of hidden pain points and opportunities for improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These tools help teams to shed light on the emotional, and contextual aspects of user interactions, which can be as critical as the functional ones when in discovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To truly understand and address your user’s actual needs, it is essential to deliver a comprehensive vision, acknowledge the intricate problems users face. A format of user needs in a story format funnels your thinking and articulation into solutions and simple actions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth isn’t like this. And when you’re exploring and prioritizing the problems to solve. This isn’t what you need. Teams that do this build the wrong thing. They build solutions that miss the why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A simple method to knowing whether you should write user needs like this is … can you and every member of your team explain in detail how your user thinks and how they act in a given circumstance? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If not. Leave the user story format behind. Leave that format for development of the solution. Not the storytelling of what your user needs and how they act. And get better at writing and sharing richer tales of your users and what they need from you and your product or service.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Overcrowding the pan</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2022/05/24/crowding-the-pan.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2022/05/24/crowding-the-pan.html</id>
    <published>2022-05-24T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2023-09-29T19:40:02+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been really getting into cooking dishes with a wok recently. Learning new recipes and the tool. It recently sprung about because a member of the family has been found to be allergic to latex heavy foods. Things like tomatoes. That meant all the curries and pasta dishes I had mastered were out the window.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through lots of trial and error I&amp;rsquo;ve learnt plenty. And got lots of tips through YouTube too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cooking for the family is often a refuge for me. Unlike work, it&amp;rsquo;s a small time bound thing I can easily share with others. Digital transformation projects take years. Egg fried rice takes 5 minutes*.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that I found important was keeping the wok hot. And I mean REALLY hot. Both when frying rice or vegetables. But also when deep frying things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over time I&amp;rsquo;ve felt I&amp;rsquo;ve got a better handle on how to keep things sizzling. Techniques to cool things down. But also, most importantly for me, how not to crowd the pan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It feels really counter-intuitive, but you can often cook faster by frying in 2 smaller batches than all at once.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you try to fry lots at once the lack of room makes things steam and take longer to crisp up. It also makes things stickier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What too much is&amp;hellip; is not a concrete thing. And as I learnt to use a wok correctly, often discovered too late. But over time I&amp;rsquo;ve worked out the balance by eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a long day at work on a project not quite hitting the right tempo, it dawned on me we had crowded things out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The subject was complex. But we had a large team. Multiples of each profession. Created from 2 projects merging. Instead of speeding things up. We had crowded things out so that taking the lead on things was harder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It got so bad at 1 point, it felt that only a few of us was doing anything at all. There were so many silent people. So many experienced people seemingly reporting back no progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were other factors. As an organisation we had made reaching our users difficult. That played a big part. Lots of stopping to fill each other in or to give context. Some clashing perspectives on the same ideas. But that would have been easier if there had been less of us to agree anything before we took an approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real momentum only really happened when we were our smallest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t new. Lots has been written about the &lt;a href="https://hbr.org/2019/02/research-when-small-teams-are-better-than-big-ones"&gt;benefits of small teams&lt;/a&gt;. But we had created the conditions to overcrowd ourselves as a team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It had become too hard to hear each voice. To be clear about who was doing what and what to do next. There were just too many of us for us to be agile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overcrowding is not just a numbers thing. Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s not just how many pizzas feeds a team. Problems vary too much for that to be true. I&amp;rsquo;ve been on teams of different sizes where the tipping point is different. Either on balance of roles or the type of work that needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many reasons something slows down and doesn&amp;rsquo;t get going. One cause could be that you&amp;rsquo;ve overcrowded your pan. Either with too many people trying to do the same thing. Or stopping each other because there&amp;rsquo;s too many people to take responsibility. Either way, it&amp;rsquo;s something I have a better sense of for the next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be careful to balance your teams so they have just the right amount of people in them. Don&amp;rsquo;t overcrowd the pan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*assuming we&amp;rsquo;re talking about just frying the egg and rice that is!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Choosing what discovery to go forward with</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2022/05/13/choosing-what-discovery.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2022/05/13/choosing-what-discovery.html</id>
    <published>2022-05-13T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2023-09-29T19:40:02+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A researcher in another gov department recently messaged about tips for choosing what discovery to go with next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought this was an interesting question. There&amp;rsquo;s many ways to go forward. And context can change this a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I find myself in a similar situation I like to create frameworks within the team. Myself, product, programme whoever on what factors we&amp;rsquo;d use to decide as a team that something&amp;rsquo;s worth looking into more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not just what we could do. But what will help make a decision. And the organisation a better decision about what to do next. Even if that&amp;rsquo;s just ourselves about the direction of the service we&amp;rsquo;re providing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some factors I use in a that framework are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;User impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much is this area gonna improve things? And how likely is the change going to be welcomed and embraced?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Business impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much is this gonna chime with a benefit or impact to the organisation? [grasp an opportunity, save money, reduce cost, improved specific outcomes]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Strategic alignment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does this thing have strategic buy-in or alignment? If not, doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean don&amp;rsquo;t do it. Just that&amp;rsquo;s a factor in how much effort it&amp;rsquo;ll be to get people to buy into this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Ease to do&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is this something we can do? And find out about? Or does it include working across teams and organisations. Again. Doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean don&amp;rsquo;t do it. Just be brutally honest that the more of a system you have to understand the harder it&amp;rsquo;ll be&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Can we name the decision it&amp;rsquo;ll help make?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we know what decision we need to make. Then a discovery is really focused, well scoped and easy to shape. If it isn&amp;rsquo;t we may need to think about it again. Or try explaining it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Feasibility&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How likely is it the things we&amp;rsquo;re looking into are things we can solve? The NHS has wasted millions on discoveries and alphas into things that&amp;rsquo;ll take billions to solve etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are we trying to boil the ocean when it might make sense to start somewhere smaller?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Conditions for tackling problems</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2022/03/31/conditions-for-problems.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2022/03/31/conditions-for-problems.html</id>
    <published>2022-03-31T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2023-09-29T19:40:02+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Been thinking a lot about team dynamics and process. Because there are a few things that aren&amp;rsquo;t quite working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve always been a believer that you empower your teams by asking them to find opportunities and go do something about them. As opposed to telling people the solution, or the problem to work on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve done this in my career. Sometimes wrestling this freedom after being handed a solution. Sometimes after buying some credit through delivering something. And a few times with that brief itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the freedom to go find opportunities or problems to solve can be really difficult sometimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently an agile consultant, who had been reviewing different team&amp;rsquo;s maturity in agile, explained why her recommendations weren&amp;rsquo;t about adopting the pinnacle of agile best practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her recommendation was that because there was little existing culture. And rapidly shifting policy. That it wasn&amp;rsquo;t sensible to get to best practice quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Her recommendation was to do small things. They were to start very small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there, what worked could be shared and grow. And bit by bit a culture could emerge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conditions, context or capabilities weren&amp;rsquo;t there to go do the pinnacle of agile best practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talking the recommendations through got me thinking about conditions and context. Not just for agile. But also what is needed to handle the freedom to go find opportunities and problems to solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re working in a space where problems have so many causes and interconnected systems, the freedom can be suffocating. Especially without deep domain knowledge. And you often find it&amp;rsquo;s better to start the journey with a small but well-shaped opportunity. Or a vision of what you want the solution to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, if you have a team that&amp;rsquo;s not quite experienced in navigating uncertainty the freedom can stifle any progress. And often results in endless and fruitless discoveries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to take smaller steps if:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;policy or strategy is always shifting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;context changes all the time (think COVID-19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;teams or organisations are beginning their journey in certain ways of working&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;there’s a lack of delivery or history to call on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the team hasn&amp;rsquo;t had the time to build the domain knowledge&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empowering teams is a process. Sometimes full freedom to go find opportunities or problems is not the first step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And allowing a team to prove a hunch is wrong can be an effective way to build the conditions and context for finding what would work. (Though this only works if you&amp;rsquo;re willing to listen and it&amp;rsquo;s safe for them to say not that, but this)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Shaping design work (with STAR)</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2021/05/12/shaping-work-with-star.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2021/05/12/shaping-work-with-star.html</id>
    <published>2021-05-12T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2023-09-29T19:40:02+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Shaping design work for others, rather than tackling it yourself is a hard balancing act. Shape the work too much and people are too constrained. Too little and people get lost. Or scope is so large it’s difficult to show progress and value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not something a formula can solve. But there are things you can use to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve started to use a format when writing up and shaping design work. This was in response to at times feeling like some work was better shaped than others. And what an ideal statement of design work would be for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format I’ve started to use is STAR. This isn’t a new thing. Though it wasn’t designed for shaping work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The STAR format helps write up case studies as well as structure interview responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It stands for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="list-unstyled"&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Situation&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Task&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Activity/Action&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Result&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a sort of narrative helper. Useful to structure retrospective stories of how someone tackled something. And what results they got. STAR isn’t the only format, there’s a quite few around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with any narrative structure, it’s not only useful for when you’ve done something. It can help shape what you, or other people, can do to tackle work. Before you’ve done it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s something I’ve started to use. But I’m finding it helpful. To get my thoughts in order. To direct teams and individual teams to kick start work. Big and small.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How I use the format to shape design work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use the format to break down work into each section. Which together helps create the size and shape of the work. This can then help someone to tackle work. Or act as material for kick off workshops and other meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also doesn’t have to be completely formed and can be created together as a group. And there’s no reason it needs to 1 person’s work. Or 1 role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Situation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like many stories. Start at the beginning. Writing down all known facts about a problem or opportunity. This might be something like a preliminary problem statement. Or. It could be a raw set of constraints and hunches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve found it works better to throw in a few lines of what’s going wrong. And the issue that is being caused over a formal problem statement. But that might be a personal thing. I try too hard to get problem statements perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the situation section I also like to be clear where a request has come from. If it’s a policy, something observed in user research or a request from a product manager. Then say it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If an opportunity needs some selling then that needs to be clear. Either internal buy in or validation. It helps teams know what they’ve got to do next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a request has a rigid scope that is also worth calling out. Again, it helps teams know what the situation is. And if it’s a “go do it” sort of situation and the reason is less than clear. That should be clear. It helps the team understand what to do. And how other people will understand the work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Task&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial scope of the work. This helps make it clear what I’m expecting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I’m open to challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the section I leave the lightest. I like to use a phrase with a verb that defines the scope of the task. So something like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Understand why 25% of users are dropping off at the file upload page”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Design how we add second factor authentication to the sign up flow”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The verb acts to say what the scope is. Understand/design/review etc. This shapes the work of the team. Where the limits are. If it’s about understanding, that means we review as a team with next steps. If it is design, there’s a sense that we need to work on showing what the future should look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Activity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the part where you shape the sort of things you or the team should do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re shaping work for others, this is the most sensitive section. And where you want to be most aware of how much direction your team needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For teams with some experience you can call out the key milestones. Things like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create range of options for how to tackle [problem]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Agree with product team which option to take forward&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Take design through assurance workshop &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For very experienced teams you could give even less. This section allows you and them to talk about process and must-dos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For people or more junior teams you can be even more specific and shape how to tackle a problem. And the order. For example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Map existing entry points&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review user research into entry points&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Compile analytics for bounce rates and journeys&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review how other sites provide entry points&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create presentation summarising findings and next steps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Review work with [team] at team huddle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key of course isn’t to dictate exactly what to do. It’s to create a strategy for how to solve a problem or make the most of an opportunity. For those with less experience, you give them their tactics. For those with more, you let them devise the tactics, but make sure key things are still covered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this section, whether for yourself, an experienced team or not, you’ve made the tactics clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the situation tells you where you are. And the task how far you want to travel. Then activity is a description of what to bring when you travel. And what route to take. What’s left is the ultimate destination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This section makes clear the outcomes or results you think the work should create. What we should achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the traditional STAR method, it’s about measuring success. In this model, it’s about the outcomes you want to create.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s about asking “How do you want to judge success?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can range from metrics like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Reduced drop offs at checkout page by x%”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To task based things like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Got buy-in to redesign triage flow”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find sketching the results out also helps shape the activities too. And it can be useful to write this before the activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with the others, this section is another conversation starter with a team to get a shared sense of success. Of what done looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Creating a size and shape of work&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After working through this format. You should have a good sense of the size and shape of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have a documented sense of what you know, how far you want to go, what you need to do and what outcomes you want to create from a bit of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format can be a workshop. A team effort or solo enterprise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve found it helpful to shape work for others. To make things clear. And make context obvious. Particularly compared to projects that I’ve not used this format.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find yourself needing to shape your own work or work for others. Use a format to structure your shaping. Try a format like STAR.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
