<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Andrew Duckworth</title>
  <subtitle>Designer, artist</subtitle>
  <id>https://grillopress.github.io/</id>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2023-12-04T12:47:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Get beyond the 'so what?'</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/12/04/get-beyond-the-so-what.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/12/04/get-beyond-the-so-what.html</id>
    <published>2023-12-04T12:47:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-12-05T10:42:58+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In a rush to get headlines and report back I often see research and design teams reporting things that don’t add any insight. Or develop any understanding of a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At best you’ll get a shrug. At worst people will mark it down mentally that user research will only find out stuff they already know or could have guessed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir left fig-left fig-left-gutter" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/splash.jpeg" alt="A figure in matisse style dancing - By Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;ldquo;You also need to ask yourself a question. Is it clear what the team needs to do next?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems to be worse when there isn’t a product or concrete service to understand. When what we want to find out is broader. Or when there’s a strong sense of service. When teams have been running things for a while. (Regardless whether they REALLY do know their users)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t have to find out something novel every time you do research. But you do have to get past “so what?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is that shrug. Either it’s an unemotional response because you’ve not made the research feel real or believable. Or it’s because you’re telling people things too late. Or maybe it’s because it’s not clear how that solves an issue for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many causes of so what:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Not going deeper. Not going beyond surface answers or the first cause. Not finding out the why behind things.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teams not being confident in what’s currently known or running assumptions. So that when a thing is confirmed to be true that confirmation cannot be celebrated or the team doesn’t use the confirmation to tackle the next thing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teams getting used to being powerless. So solving suffering is out of scope. This can happen to really high performing teams too. Ones that are very good at knowing what they can’t do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research teams being kept out of the loop and at a distance so they don’t build on what’s known. Getting stale or out of date commissions that’ll always deliver yesterday’s news or last week’s decision. And when no one is able to do anything about it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teams with poorly defined scope. So what they need to know is hard to define so they just find out whatever happens to turn up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teams who leave synthesis and reflection to one person rather than a conversation. So there’s actually no team reflection at all&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A lack of clarity in what research or insights should tell people. Often because not enough research is done or the analysis is only half-complete or completed without policy/tech teams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teams trying to dress up insights to being deeper than they are. Rather than having honest conversations about what will need to be in place to go deeper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do you can tackle “so what”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tackling the so what problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;1. Get a better scope for research&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good research starts with timing and relationships with those that need the insights. Build those. Though often you have to show the benefit before you really win people round.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But work hard on shaping what it is the research is going to do. What decision are you supporting? And will the decision be made in time? Or when you can influence it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You should also understand what is important for the organisation so you can align insights that will really motivate and get change to happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not underestimate the value of getting close to product (or whoever is setting vision) so you learn what you need to reflect back. Even in advance of an ask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;2. Build understanding of the process&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure you build understanding of your process by sharing it and involving people along the way. Don’t just preach. Show the way. Take people with you. Do the hard work to make what and why you do things clear and obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve lost count of the amount of times I’ve had to explain and guide development teams why researchers are doing what they are doing. At times this is because they’re not entirely paying attention. Bu also people haven’t explained in terms they got either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you build understanding of the process you can also talk through how much time is needed for certain things. And impress upon people when to get you involved. Lose the mystery, ensure people can work with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;3. Make it a partnership&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The researchers I’ve worked with who do the best don’t make it feel like they’re different or outside the team. They feel part of the team and do things with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t easy. And some teams make it hard. But you need to create the trust and culture where team members share insights and learnings to you. So you know what they know. And you know what they need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do this through regular team reflections to discuss research findings and their implications. Encourage diverse perspectives and input during reflection sessions. Get people who do customer support involved. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get a deep understanding of the product or problem space. Get close to people who decide and learn what influences them. And be part of the general feel and presence of the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Build the relationships you need to reach the users who’ll challenge you. Or will be a challenge to reach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do not underestimate being active in things like stand ups to help build that presence and awareness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And make sure to involve the team who will be impacted by the research to take part. To collect notes, insights and do the analysis together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;4. Go deeper&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What insights will help and help much research to do will be much easier when you’ve defined the scope with the team. And they’re involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be sure to give research the time it needs to work. But also be clear about the impact of this and have different tools for different speeds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Often the time to stop is when you’ve started to hear the same things from people. But ensure you reflect upon whether you’re hearing similar things because you’ve found a truth. Or because you’re not asking the right things or the right people something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also worth working with your designers and tech team to change things if it’s obvious a thing doesn’t. Build in some agility to switch and pivot your plan to get deeper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just because teams have heard something before doesn’t mean they might know why or when. Or how important it is. Work to get deeper insight into those things. Even for things teams know. That can be the depth that stands research apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;5. Make your insights clearer and more impactful&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way you do this is by doing a lot of the other steps well. But also working out how to summarise and make your insights actionable. A way to do this is to focus on your storytelling skills and techniques. So as you reveal your research you bring people along. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You also need to ask yourself a question. Is it clear what the team needs to do next? But don’t mistake actionable insights into having to design the solution or being directive over exactly what to do. That’s the space for your designers and team to shine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making insights more impactful also involves being able to visualise and illustrate your ideas in different ways. From simpler words to diagrams and images to explain complex concepts. To help teams digest and see things differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also means going beyond words and presentations. You can run exercises and workshops to make insights real. And next steps clear and understandable because the team’s cocreated them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also reflect on who you need in the room. Who needs to hear this message? And whether there are different stories for different teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But whatever you do. Get beyond the so what. And better yet, do it as a team.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The role user-centred design (UCD) should play in AI development</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/28/the-role-ucd-should-play-in-ai-development.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/28/the-role-ucd-should-play-in-ai-development.html</id>
    <published>2023-11-28T19:31:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-12-05T10:24:25+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been interesting watching and playing with AI tools as they emerge. Some feel really impactful. Others less so. And watching and experiencing the balancing act that teams are navigating. Between things potentially dangerous but generative and or transformational. And those that are more restrictive but less impactful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Misleading content. Purposeful or not has a massive potential impact on the world. We&amp;rsquo;ve all seen the speed a lie gets around the world. What better than a lie that looks and feels like the truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir left fig-left fig-left-gutter" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/typewritter green.jpeg" alt="A robot at a typewrter sweating a deadline with sticky notes everywhere - By Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;ldquo;We’ve already seen the rapid reaction of people to changes in models and how things are less popular as they become safer&amp;rdquo;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently a conference organiser has faked some profiles of conference speakers using AI.  To avoid criticism about gender disparity in their speaker lineup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although one day the threats and potential harm posed by AI might be new. The reality is most of them are here today. But we&amp;rsquo;re just not ready for the scale and speed that people can spread them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also see how people have caught on to the hype of AI recently and it&amp;rsquo;s jammed everywhere. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every feature is an AI powered thing. Chatbots have come back with a vengeance. AI has made little to no impact to the sheer number of terrible products and journeys being churned out. Though I suspect AI will soon be responsible for scaling up the number of terrible products out there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it has immense potential to make things great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These 2 things. The potential risks and harms opened up by AI to us, users, customers and communities. And the ability to meet a need for users through AI. The solution to these 2 things aren&amp;rsquo;t new processes either. In fact, they&amp;rsquo;re ripe for high quality, agile user-centred design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I am talking both about the design of the underlying models and platforms. As well as the tools built on top of AI and those models and platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Designing the underlying model, tools and platforms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Great models start with a clear vision and clarity over what you want it to do. Or make possible. UCD helps prototype and create these things with product and data teams. Exploring quickly whether a vision is worth bothering with. And before spending too much time trying to make it real. Researchers also help teams know their users and customers. And what opportunities there are to meet unmet needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir right fig-right fig-right-gutter" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/At the model.jpeg" alt="A figure amongst colourful lines that looks a little like computer chipboards and websites - By Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;ldquo;AI has made little to no impact to the sheer number of terrible products and journeys being churned out in the world&amp;rdquo;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, on a project I worked on last year. There was a data scientist who was jumping deep into an idea and how it could work in a different way. The clinical product owner wasn’t able to answer a question about process directly. The data scientist had a vision how it could work. But I was able to bring in some research and visualise how our users managed clinical cases. The vision from the engineer was smart. But it wouldn’t have worked for the way people managed cases. And it wasn’t a behaviour change that would have been easy to embed. The engineer had a good vision but didn’t work for there. Rather than waste some time finding out things after building a model we did something else. We used AI to get better data into our systems and reduce the time it took people to manage cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The quality, accuracy of data and facts in AI models is also critical. Teams building models and underlying tools will need to ensure they collect better data. That in part will include incentivising and making it easier to do that. Which are all better with user researchers and designers playing a part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teams developing the underlying models will also need richer and more in-depth data. And insights about people, how they work and act. This comes from data sure. But lots of it will need to come from observations of people. If you’ve ever done a study with lots of data you’ll also know that it often fails to tell you why. You might have a clear signal that no one is doing a thing. But why they’re not is often a case of contextual understanding that data doesn’t give you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As new models emerge teams will need to understand their biases and implications. This means models will need to be coproduced and designed with communities. This will only be believable if it’s done with users and communities in an open and honest way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The teams using these AI tools will also have their needs. We’ve already seen the rapid reaction of people to changes in models. And how things are less popular as they become safer. Or when certain counter measures create new unintended consequences that ruin the model. Teams and platforms that’ll succeed over the long term will ensure they design their tools with their users. And they’ll do so in quick, iterative loops. Avoiding making changes that don’t meet the model’s original vision or intent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key then is to bring together people who understand users with those who understand the tech. And using both skillsets to complement and bounce off each other in unique and novel ways. To make the models and tools useful. But also safe. And where things can’t be completely safe, a level of clarity and understanding of the biases and harms it could create.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Designing the products and features that sit on top of AI&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will be more comfortable clothes for many researchers and designers. The building of products and services to meet user needs. As with more traditional apps and websites, the best ones meet user needs. And do so supporting business goals and sustainability. The products that don’t make things better. That don’t meet the raised expectations of users who now know what AI could do, will be left long behind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir left fig-left fig-left-gutter" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/zombie.jpeg" alt="A green face staring. looking through the code - By Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;ldquo;Great models start with a clear vision and clarity over what you want it to do&amp;rdquo;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But as teams explore how AI will work to make services better, they’ll need to understand their users and customers more. Not less. It’ll be only thing that stands 1 apart from another. All powered by AIs of the same or similar flavours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People with user centered design skills are uniquely placed to help teams do this. This is their skillset. Understanding people and how to shape and mould products to meet their needs. And as AI generates more tools to build the software and products themselves, everyone will need to cultivate these skills to succeed. The barrier to build will be lower. But the expectations will be higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good research and design will also have a part to play to keep communities safe. The size and scale of impact that AI has. It gives us all super powers. But those super powers provide opportunities to those with good and bad intentions.  So we’ll need nuanced designs and services that balance safety with usefulness. Designs that incentivise doing the right thing. And put barriers in the way of doing the wrong thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Things we as designers and researchers can do to be helpful&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So UCD can make a massive impact on AI design and development. From model design and development, to building products on top of those models and platforms. To enable less bias and ensure communities are involved in the creation of AI models. But also to create safer products that really solve user needs and meet business goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this we need to be confident in the role we can play. And the value we can add. But we also need to use, understand and learn about AI more. Both as users and makers with it. Else we’re going to leave so much value behind because we won’t be able to help in practical and pragmatic ways.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Get more out of design reviews</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/26/get-more-out-of-design-reviews.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/26/get-more-out-of-design-reviews.html</id>
    <published>2023-11-26T15:28:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-11-26T19:20:10+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve reviewed a lot of designs. It’s a sign of healthy team that they share work to be reviewed. When I ran NHS Digital’s weekly design meet-ups I made sure to encourage this as much as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir right fig-right fig-right-gutter" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/sticky board.jpeg" alt="Green black and yellow sticky notes arranged with different patterns - By Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;ldquo;If a designer can’t explain the problem they’re solving it’s a sign they need to think it through some more&amp;rdquo;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes it can be hard to know where to start with some feedback. Particularly beyond some gut feels or likes or dislikes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But once you get rolling it gets easier. And you find you start really helping. Particularly if the feedback is constructive or open to allow the designer to talk through their ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also experienced a lot of designers who were very reluctant to change designs or scared of feedback. And you find that they’ll put your feedback into the “backpocket” to never be thought about again. Which is frustrating if you’ve made a mistake before and are watching someone else make the same one. But you do find that making the change or improvement their idea can work. And the way to do that is to use questions to guide them, you and everyone in the review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The structure I use&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s what I do. Let me know if you do anything differently. If the designer has made a few of these clear already. Skip a section. These are the more generic chunks I use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What feedback is useful right now?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of designers getting used to having their work reviewed share their work too late. So sometimes you find there’s not much that can be changed before research or build. But ask about what sort of feedback they’re after. It might not be what you give them. But expectations are good at the very least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;The context of the design?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good storyteller very quickly sets the context of where a design sits within a product or journey. If that wasn’t clear confirm the scenario and context something will be used. There’s a massive context difference between most sales sign up forms and something you use because you’re sick. Is this something pays for? Or has to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What problem are they trying to solve?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What thing are they trying to make clearer? What issue needs solving? Is there data to prove that. Is that something they can control or improve here? Is this the best place to do it? Or the only place we can control for now? At the heart of a good review is being honest about whether we’re going to make the impact we expect. And the cost or effort to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the problem doesn’t feel very important. And it’s great to talk about. And if a designer can’t explain the problem they’re solving it’s a sign they need to think it through some more with whoever set the issue or opportunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What else have they tried or explored?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good design is iterative and goes through loops of change and creation. Sometimes in a review we can also suggest ideas people have discarded. Ask them what else they considered and why they didn’t go with them. It’s often a very revealing part of discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s also worth considering who they’ve worked with to explore a design. Have they talked to any engineers? If not, they might need to explore some other things if technical constraints exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What do they think is the weakness?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of telling them what you think works and doesn’t. Get the designer to talk through where they think things are weak. I know personally when I have a worry about a thing being weak it often is. And talking it through can help me design something better. Or be at peace with that issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;How and with who are they going to prove their thoughts are right?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good process works out if something works. How will they do that? Who will be included in that. Who isn’t involved? And will that cause issues. If they’re going to build it without testing it first, how will they mitigate any issues or rapidly change?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What could go wrong, and how people could recover?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things are always going wrong. What happens if someone inputs something unexpected? How recoverable are things? Will the user be guided to success or is it a painful process? Get the designer to walk through what thought they’ve put into this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s quite common for teams to spend a lot of time on the happy path. But we all know from daily use of services and products that’s not always true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Does it align to style guides, product journey and typical use of the component?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you know these rules this is easier. But ask how it reuses existing styles and whether anything changes or uses things differently. A good designer is cautious about changing or reinventing patterns that work. And knows when to use them and when something new is needed. If it is different they should be able to justify it. And be believable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What thoughts have they put into accessibility and inclusion?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have they thought about how people on different devices and using assistive tech will experience the thing? What about people with disabilities? How have they thought about the impact of the service will be on people? Will it make it easier for people to use the service or product? Who have they not included and will they be able to take the steps to do resolve that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What happens next?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to end a session finding out what they’re doing next with the feedback and the design. It’s a good chance to open up the choice of coming back with some changes or the feedback from going live. A good design process keeps evolving. When something is &amp;ldquo;design and done&amp;rdquo; it’s a bad sign and carries a lot of risks if things don’t work.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Test often to keep your designs simple</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/19/reduce-the-time-it-takes-to-test.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/19/reduce-the-time-it-takes-to-test.html</id>
    <published>2023-11-19T15:05:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-11-21T17:17:49+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was talking to an ex-colleague and friend about some work. Talking through some issues we’d both seen in different places and times. One that stood out was how the length of time a designer has before they can test something works makes their work more complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of any good design process is making sure things work with users. Not to confirm but to prove things work. And if they don’t get the evidence to do more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than use the most complicated design first. The key is to try the simplest thing to build and get going. That way if you don’t need to build on more things, you don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key of course is actually doing this with users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you don’t always get the luxury of regular access to users. Or usability sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir left fig-left fig-left-gutter" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/next research is too late.jpeg" alt="Artwork. 3 people looking at calendars looking bored or confused - By Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;ldquo;If your next research session isn’t for months. You’re carrying a lot of risk.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the situation my colleague found themselves in. They saw that teams members were overthinking their designs because they had so much time between usability sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s sort of no surprise. The more time you have, and the fewer opportunities to find things out with users, the more you need your design to win first time. To hit all the right notes. But what this does is mean you overcomplicate a design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You add all the bells and whistles. You make everything flash red. To get your design past the usability session. But even in the best case scenario things work. You’ll not know if something simpler worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve gone through with something complex. It’s hard to scale back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the issues of not testing with users regularly as a design team. You give yourself too much time to overthink things. To worry through each issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you’ve ever done any extensive user research. You’ll know that often the thing you worry about is not the thing that makes people stumble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you’ll jam in things that were never needed. And you might even design the usability session is such a way that the real question is never asked. And you don’t learn about the thing that means the whole service will fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="stretch-container"&gt;
    &lt;figure class="noir" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
            &lt;img src="/images/click the button.jpg" alt="Picture of a mobile with lots of arrows on a screen pointint to a button with a speech bubble next to it of the researcher saying 'Where would you click?'"/&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &amp;ldquo;But it worked in testing!&amp;rdquo;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is to do usability more often. Particularly if you’re a product team. If you’re updating things and you have hundreds of thousands of users you have no excuse for several months between usability sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put this in place. Do whatever it takes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst putting that regular cycle of user research in place, run “critiques” and sessions with people who know little to nothing about your product. Be they other designers, staff, friends and family. Just to get some signals. Just to get fresh eyes seeing things. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do this to keep your design simple. Keep it crude. And learn as fast as possible if simple works. Simple often works. And only needs some small tweaks to work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course there’s probably a “Goldilocks zone”. Where you’re testing too often to reflect and think things through. But it’s better to be in that situation and calm things down than being months and months apart from reality. Never mind factoring in that a prototype isn’t the real thing. And there’s always more to learn from making things live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your next research session isn’t for months. You’re carrying a lot of risk. And making it worse for your designers and product teams as they’ll overthink. Overthinking leads to more complex designs that might work but at a higher cost to build, maintain and change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s always easier to add than take away.  Test often to keep your designs simple.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why you made a bigger impact as a smaller design team</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/18/why-you-made-a-bigger-impact-as-a-smaller-design-team.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/18/why-you-made-a-bigger-impact-as-a-smaller-design-team.html</id>
    <published>2023-11-18T13:22:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-11-22T09:25:50+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently read a blog post by Katherine Wastell about &lt;a href="https://www.katherinewastell.com/blog/2023/11/17/the-phases-of-establishing-design"&gt;the phases of establishing design&lt;/a&gt;. I like giving names to things. As it makes it possible to think and discuss about what to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In it there was a funnel visualisation of the impact teams have and it grew as you moved through the phases of design. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It got me thinking however, that as we scale up the size of design teams in organisations, the actual impact of design doesn’t always follow that idealistic path. That is, many times once we start to scale up design we actually become too inwardly focused and make less impact per person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small design team or community is often more impactful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re less focused on internally and self-serving/healing patterns and processes and more about looking out and doing things and getting mucked in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s less people to manage. Grow and check on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s more lines of communication in big teams. And places to hide, disappear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may to join parts of an organisation less willing to work with your team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there&amp;rsquo;s more people who may want to pull in different directions. From design components and patterns to whole ways of working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as you grow you’ve got new pains and problems to deal with. Job descriptions. Specialisms. Communications challenges. You have to shift people around to where the money is and maybe not to where the impact is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir right fig-right fig-right-gutter" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/through the looking glass glassing through the look.jpeg" alt="Artwork. Man looking at glass which distorts himself - By Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;ldquo;Be conscious of it. That cycle of inward and outward focus.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens over time is the team also embodies this. It becomes inwardly facing and focused and stops looking out and partnering with the rest of the teams to get things done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been in countless leadership and lead design meetings where the only thing happening is some navel gazing and frustration. Where the question of “how do we make a positive impact?” has ceased to be asked in one shape or form. And it&amp;rsquo;s mostly about recruitment or retention but not action on either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing is. It’s quite clear why you fall into this trap. As you deliver you optimise for impact and don’t put the things in place to keep the community or team healthy. Things start to break. People will leave or get frustrated at a lack of promotion or clarity or the weight of bureaucracy or similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a switch is made to focus inwardly. But you start losing the focus to really make an impact beyond design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be quite damaging to design as a function within a company. You hear “there’s more of you but you make less of an impact”. And however much you hate to agree we’ve probably all seen that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be conscious of it. That cycle of inward and outward focus. Making sure we hold ourselves and our teams to account to making an impact. Of looking out there and to making an impact and improving things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have solid “business partnering” process. That is, have a process where you have people support other people meet their goals. This can be through small things like &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/13/design-critiques-and-feedback-as-a-service.html"&gt;letting teams experience design&lt;/a&gt;. Or it can be specific people who ensure your designers and teams are adding value to the most impactful areas of the business. Typically this is the product or engineering department or an impactful programme of work. So have designers who collaborate with the leaders of those teams to see how and where design can help. With the ability to quickly help solve some of the other departments major problems or issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treat internal issues and &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2018/09/29/treat-your-design-process-like-a-design-process.html"&gt;processes like design problems&lt;/a&gt;. Keep them small, iterate and use small prototypes to find the right thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure you’re focused and clear that adding value to your users and other teams is what’s important. And that your most talented and skilled people continue to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="stretch-container"&gt;
    &lt;figure class="noir" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
        &lt;a href="/images/Impact framework.jpg" target="_blank"&gt;
            &lt;img src="/images/Impact framework.jpg" alt="Change framework for making an impact. Asks several questions to navigate a user to understanding how they might make an impact. Starts with who are the key partners. Who within those teams you can reach. How you'll reach them. What benefits short and long term we and they can get by working together. And then what we could do. Underneath the last 3 section is space for assumptions and who will do the work - By Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;
        &lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;
            Use things like this &lt;a href="/images/Impact framework.jpg" target="_blank"&gt;change framework&lt;/a&gt; to show how you could work with others
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure you claim your part and your team’s part in successes. Do not be shy to build the story of your impact. Even if it is shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t just burden your most experienced doers to run the community. Or to create the internal processes. Spread that out and even hire people to do those things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But whatever you choose to do. Think about the strengths of those smaller teams making an impact. They:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hunt for opportunities to add value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get on with designing things&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look to collaborate and grow influence beyond their own profession or skillset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And ensure your teams and functions keep doing those things and those things are still cherished and rewarded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve lost count of the number of places that promote their best designers and then burden them with internal facing problems. Regardless of whether they’re suited to them. Or if the organisation cares about that stuff. And then lose momentum in showing the impact design can make.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Being clear about the shifts you need to make to get people to buy or use your service</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/16/clear-about-the-shifts.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/16/clear-about-the-shifts.html</id>
    <published>2023-11-16T12:39:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T14:51:45+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When trying to get users for your service it&amp;rsquo;s helpful to outline the stages of interest people go through. And what strategies you might want to use to meet their needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This applies whether you’re selling a thing. Creating a health service. Or building a service the user must legally complete under certain conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use a quick framework to help guide me. To help myself and my team be clear about the shifts we need to make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking about how users start your service, or buy your product, you’ll find the following stages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="table-container"&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
    &lt;caption&gt;User stages of interest&lt;/caption&gt;
    &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;th scope="col"&gt;Type&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th scope="col"&gt;Interest level&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th scope="col"&gt;Example&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/thead&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Actively looking for a/the service to meet a need&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Proactive interest&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Someone looking for new shoes, person looking for a doctors phone number etc.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Open to a/the service to meet a need&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Inactive interest&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Someone who knows they need new shoes but feeling busy or not looking right now, Someone who knows they need to do something about a health issue but not sure what or if something exists so do nothing&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Not thinking about a/the service to meet a need&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Inactive disinterest&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Someone who think their shoes are fine and not thinking about them, Someone who thinks the health problem is just age or something that’ll be fine in time&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Don’t think a/the service would meet their need &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Proactive disinterest &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Someone who is thinking / conscious of new shoes or alternatives but doesn’t want them, Someone who knows a new model of car exists but doesn’t want it, Someone who thinks a health service would be a waste of time for them&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Successfully selling things is about making it as easy as possible for those actively looking. Or to stand out as the best option for those people. And then trying to shift the inactive people into some activity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those with inactive interest, it&amp;rsquo;s about showing the possibility of your product to improve things. To answer their need. That it is possible to do THAT thing. Or solve THAT issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those with inactive disinterest, it&amp;rsquo;s about getting them to pay attention and answer a question. Are you sure this isn’t for you? Don’t you need this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For proactive disinterest. That can sound like a terrible place. But you’ve got people’s notice. Maybe your service isn’t for them. But it’s a chance to do something. It’s harder to shift their perceptions because they come with some. But understanding those people means you can tailor your service to respond to what they currently think your service lacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir right fig-right fig-right-gutter" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/all the people all the places.jpeg" alt="Artwork. Many people in blue. Searching looking for things. Looking for all the people and places amongst mountains of sticky notes - By Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ask yourself. Do we need to reach people or convert those we&amp;rsquo;ve reached?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s nothing harder for services than the unengaged. The people we find hard to reach. To influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many urgent and emergency health services you find a lot of proactive disinterest. That is. People who very consciously don’t think a service will meet their needs. Many examples in health are because they don’t want to go to hospital. So they’ll look for other services to meet their need if possible. Or try and do nothing at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In South East London, a team I worked with found that to be true of a lot of their patients for their “virtual ward” offer. They had a lot of patients who were in a thin line between seriously ill enough for hospital care, but safe enough and insistent enough that they didn’t want hospital. Traditionally the patient would be cajoled into hospital. Or worse left at risk in the community or with family. But with a “virtual ward” approach they could be given the care they’d expect in hospital. With the access to drugs, diagnostics and consultant care, but in the comfort of their own home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This service now had something they could offer. To nudge those with proactive disinterest in going to getting the care from hospital. Something in the middle. And once care started. If things were really unsafe at homes a relationship had started. And patients were much more willing to talk their options through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not everything has to be as involved as reinventing your service. Sometimes it’s the slow drip work of making obvious that &amp;ldquo;people like you become their best self with THIS&amp;rdquo;. Getting your main proposition out there. And if that doesn’t work, working out from the actively disinterested what it is that your service is lacking. Be it clarity or specific things you can offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who are actively looking or considering things also have different modes or ways they search for information too. There&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://boxesandarrows.com/four-modes-of-seeking-information-and-how-to-design-for-them/" target="_blank"&gt;an interesting model here by Donna Spencer about those seeking modes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re mapping out how your service or product works. Make sure to visualise the routes to using your service from these states. How are you helping shift people to meet their needs using your service? What are your tactics?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a 2by2 grid can be useful. Use it to write in the tactics or solutions you have for shifting people. Do this as a team. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="stretch-container"&gt;
    &lt;img style="border: 1px solid black;" src="/images/interest activity 2by2 grid.jpg" alt="2 by 2 grid with one side having interest, the other activity with arrows between to highlight where the shifts to be made are"/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A format like this will make it easier to talk about but also show you where you might be lacking. It can be easy to over optimise for people to buy. But your problem might be that you’re not getting people interested first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You find this in government a lot. Where most of the work is making the service easy to use. With little work on how we get people to know about the thing in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself. Do we need to reach people or convert those we&amp;rsquo;ve reached?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s also worth noting that the time people spend in these phases isn&amp;rsquo;t equal. The length of time someone will stomach actively looking but finding nothing is not long. And differs on the level of importance to them. People will rarely stay active for long. So you have to be quick there to get the sale or convert a disbeliever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People also get things wrong. And a potential user whose tried something and failed will very quickly think your service can&amp;rsquo;t exist. Or is a load of rubbish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you may have very different users or types of people either starting or referring people to your service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But whether you’re trying to sell something, offering a health or government service, make sure to understand the phases your potential users go through. And map out how well your service meets those phases. And the things you could change to shift people to meet their needs using your product or service.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
