<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Andrew Duckworth</title>
  <subtitle>Designer, artist</subtitle>
  <id>https://grillopress.github.io/</id>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2025-03-01T18:07:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Between shifted and removed costs</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2025/03/01/between-shifted-and-removed-costs.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2025/03/01/between-shifted-and-removed-costs.html</id>
    <published>2025-03-01T18:07:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-03-05T09:39:46+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many organisations invest in service transformation with the goal to reduce costs or improve efficiency. Be it automating manual tasks, streamlining processes, or cutting out steps that seem unnecessary. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However these changes can end up just moving costs or effort to another part of the organisation or onto users. Leading to new challenges instead of true efficiencies. And ultimately much worse outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to see a task that takes time and assume removing it will create value. Sometimes, that’s true. Like automating how we test whether a change in code has broken a journey. But in other cases, the cost is not removed—it’s just moved elsewhere. Often, this burden falls on users or other teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t always the big stuff. An example I&amp;rsquo;ve suffered recently is a change in packaging. Over Christmas I was in my local shop to look for some nice beer. I found something interesting. But instead of the usual plastic rings or cardboard packaging, the cans were held together with glue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir right fig-right fig-right-gutter" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/dripping.jpeg" alt="An artwork of a family made out of fluff and sticky notes, dripping"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;A well-designed service should aim to genuinely remove costs rather than just shift them&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This likely reduced packaging costs, may have had environmental benefits, and let the product have a clean look. But it also made it more prone to falling apart, and shifted the risk to me as the customer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m sure the team is celebrating cost savings and sustainability improvements. But they achieved this by pushing inconvenience and risk onto me. Recycled cardboard would have worked just fine. Glue, not so much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not a happy customer when it means your savings cost me more when things go wrong. This will inform every purchase I make going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond beer, nowhere is cost-shifting more apparent than in healthcare. While there are some tasks that are better done with active patients, many health services now place an excessive burden on patients and their families.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patients are expected to remember their prescriptions, manage drug interactions, and carry information between appointments and teams. Partial digitisation and service cuts mean that clinicians often don’t have the time or access to the right information, shifting that responsibility to patients instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big efficiency, better systems that record and talk to each other, is left undone. So teams are left with smaller ones. Ones where time is cut down to the bare minimum. People are a bag of symptoms rather than a person in the rush to increase throughput.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means that the most unwell often burden the highest cost of gluing together a good health service. And anyone with a chronic illness facing doing that for the rest of their life. Ultimately at the cost of jobs, money and health of those very patients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A health service might have saved a bit in efficiency or number of appointments offered. But at the cost of the ultimate outcome: the patient&amp;rsquo;s health and ability to live a good life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we design and build products, if we care about our users and the impact of the &amp;ldquo;improvements&amp;rdquo; we make, we need to counteract this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;How might we do that&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To avoid simply shifting costs rather than removing them, we need to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand and amplify the voices of those affected and talk with users and teams to identify where burdens are being created&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the problem properly. Doing root cause analysis can reveal alternative ways to remove, rather than shift, burden&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Model the true end-cost. If removing a task leads to more customer service calls or increased churn, factor that into the cost-benefit analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set clear red lines. Principles like “no new burden on the user” or “no added complexity” ensure efficiencies don’t come at the cost of user experience&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work and prototype the bigger solutions. Stop accepting that it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to share data and start prototyping ways it can be even in smaller sets of services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Successful product, projects and programmes make informed decisions about what they will and won’t do. A well-designed service should aim to genuinely remove costs rather than just shift them. Without this, efficiency gains come at the cost of worse experiences for users and higher costs elsewhere in the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t just shift a cost. Remove it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Service design is not mostly convincing other people to do service design</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2024/11/29/service-design-is-not-mostly-convincing-other-people-to-do-service-design.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2024/11/29/service-design-is-not-mostly-convincing-other-people-to-do-service-design.html</id>
    <published>2024-11-29T14:05:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-03-02T19:33:56+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s catchy. And many people feel that’s what they do. And you’ll be doing it a bit I don’t doubt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’ve talked to a service designer over the last few years (or been one) you’ve probably heard some variation on that theme. That the job is mostly convincing other people to let them do their job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a good ear worm but it’s a bad brain worm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Telling people that’s what the thing is is setting them up to fail. No one wants a methodological pedant who mostly preaches and rarely practices on a team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No one wants to hear how they’re doing it all wrong by someone who appears to only say that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir right fig-right fig-right-gutter" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/pink-mess.jpeg" alt="An artwork of pink sticky notes and fluff"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Service design starts in the stony rubbish. That’s where things take root. Not in a perfect world where things are cultivated and manicured&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there’s something I’ve seen a lot of the last few years in the service design world, then it&amp;rsquo;s a lot of pedantry about what is or is not service design. Or how &amp;ldquo;these aren&amp;rsquo;t the true conditions&amp;rdquo; or this or that. And a lot of people trying to do good work spending too much time arguing about what it is rather than getting on with it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of people following a &amp;ldquo;preaching and throwing rocks process&amp;rdquo; rather than getting their hands dirty. Spending time “evangelising” rather than just getting on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If showing is powerful and telling less so, then it’s about showing how it works. Through doing it rather than talking about doing it. By helping combine various views and helping make better decisions based on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s done by helping teams visualise and talk about complex things. And be able to add their skill set and viewpoints into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s done by ensuring teams are held to account by the users actual expectations and experiences. And weaving those viewpoints into business and technical discussions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes it&amp;rsquo;s hard. But it&amp;rsquo;s done by doing not telling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now people might say, yeah that’s what they meant. But is it what’s happening? If 90% of the work is advocating for service design it must be done by doing. And not preaching and explaining the theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it really is just convincing other people of the approach then it’s a pyramid scheme not a path to better products and services. So it’s got to be mostly about facilitating and designing how services are offered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Better products and services are made by getting stuck in. Not by disappearing and working on futures that’ll never happen. Or by preaching a set of conditions to do work that’ll never materialise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Service design starts in the stony rubbish. That’s where things take root. Not in a perfect world where things are cultivated and manicured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No service design is not mostly convincing other people to do service design. It’s by using tools and techniques to make services and products better. Designing services together. Not preaching about the conditions or what jobs are called.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Justifying design's impact</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2024/09/25/justifying-ucd-s-impact.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2024/09/25/justifying-ucd-s-impact.html</id>
    <published>2024-09-25T19:41:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2024-09-25T20:16:11+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been in a few places where there’s been talk about justifying the cost of UCD and similar roles. At first glance it’s a fair point. What impact do we have? How are we helping? How do we ensure we’re doing the best we can?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the question rarely gets asked in &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s one of the ways I note the health of an organisation or profession. If the organisation is complex or complicated, but the measures and patience for a profession to make an impact don’t reflect that, it’s a bad sign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it takes years to build anything. And years more to know if you’ve made things better. It’s unlikely you’ll see the impact you expect due to other bigger cultural problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recall working at an organisation and hearing a director ask teams to capture examples and case studies to illustrate the impact teams have made. But making an impact on things like child poverty, whether people can get a GP appointment or the rate of reoffending isn’t something 1 person is going to easily impact in a team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir right fig-right fig-right-gutter" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/having a chat at the workshop.jpeg" alt="A rough pastel drawing of figures with one pressing a phone on a persons ear"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;You’re not claiming that you’ve solved child poverty. But you can say you’ve make it clearer to get help. That satisfaction has increased or that people are more likely to find the information they need first time.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hell, a whole service will struggle to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When that particular ask was put out, everyone was on the backfoot. It was not about building a culture of caring about impact, showing and telling how people’s work helps. It was to justify, backfill and escape a cull immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if we’re honest most designers and UCD staff are rarely powerful or influential enough to own the outcomes that get measured. Nor do they have the freedom to accelerate when their designs get made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may be less so in some problem spaces and in individual products or smaller teams. Where there is a closer relationship to doing some work and seeing it out there in the world making changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But in complex and complicated organisations it’s impossible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the issue lies in that complexity. But it’s also because we can never directly claim updating a website or a flow is really going to be the single thing that changed some numbers for a complex problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Child poverty is just too big. And drawing an honest line between 1 strand of work to that is going to be impossible or a lie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately when the question is being asked about impact it’s often a budget thing. Justify the cost. And actual evidence for those big outcomes are going to be problematic at best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;1. Don’t&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a big believer that you’re wasted in proving your impact in these situations. Don’t tell, show. Do it by doing the work to make things better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get drawn into trying to claim a slice of a complex outcome and then the mental gymnastics required to pretend you really did all that yourself and it wasn’t a system wide thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if you can’t not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;2. Try and reverse the ask&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re getting someone asking to justify how a profession makes an impact there’s a chance a decision has already been made. Maybe someone needs to sleep well with it and are throwing a fake bone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But maybe it’s a legit ask. If so, ask them what they think. What’s their expectations? Sometimes money was given with expectations and that hasn’t aligned to what happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been in and seen enough teams try and make an impact but getting chance to bed in is so tough because so many other things have to change to allow it. And maybe those things aren’t well understood higher up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It might also be because people inherit decisions and teams. And may not know what they’re meant to get back. Or it could be that they don’t know what impact looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A mechanic will know what sounds and things happen when an engine runs smooth. And when it doesn’t. Sometimes people don’t know if they’re getting the right signals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;3. Do the groundwork and know how your outputs contribute to the outcomes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To help show impact do the work to show how a role or roles contributes to outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote about why &lt;a href="/2023/10/27/why-we-design-forms.html"&gt;designers design forms&lt;/a&gt;. Have a model like this for your business and what elements you contribute to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be it quality, innovation, experience, efficiency, risk, profit etc&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Help yourself and your teams out by creating a basic model of those big, broad outcomes at the top and the common outputs and things you do and visualise how the small things you do impact the big things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="1" cellpadding="10" cellspacing="0" style="margin-bottom:1rem;overflow-x:auto;"&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Broad Outcome&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Smaller Outcome&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Design Output/Action&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td rowspan="4"&gt;Reduce number of calls to support team&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reduce onboarding-related support queries by 15%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Improve in-app onboarding flow with clearer step-by-step guidance&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Increase usage of self-help resources by 30%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Design a more prominent and useful help section&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reduce form drop-offs by 20%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Redesign long forms reducing duplication, redundancy and improving usability&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Reduce error-related support calls by 25%&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Provide more user-friendly, actionable error messages and recovery steps&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This way you can tell the story of smaller impacts and wins but create the thread between that and the bigger outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;4. Get good at finding smoke signals&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a model being crafted ensure you and your teams get good at identifying smaller, quicker signals that something’s making an impact or potentially contributing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only focus on smaller impacts than those massive outcomes. But also quicker signals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something I’ve worked on recently is working with the an organisation to define what it means by increasing quality. By doing this I could give a name to several different components. It’ll take a longer time to measure and understand if the product we’re going to release has done this. But we can cheaply check elements of it as a quick smoke signal that things look like they’re getting better. That we’ve made an impact in a much smaller way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If quality has 12 ingredients, can we see we’ve made 2-3 happen? Or made it stronger?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;5. Talk about it all the time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Know how you do stuff and what outcomes they support you need to  talk about it all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ensure all activity has clear threads to why we’re doing work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This round of research? It’s about derisking a policy landing wrong. Or maybe it’s about ensuring we reduce calls to contact centres. Or maybe it’s about exploring new ways of working that will lead to xyz.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe it’s even smaller scale. It’s about derisking a policy by just getting everyone aware and on the same page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key is to talk. And to sow the seeds of contribution all the time. Even when it’s collaborative. To own your fair share.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because you can bet your ass other professions and teams are taking credit. As they should. But so should you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’re not claiming that you’ve solved child poverty. But you can say you’ve make it clearer to get help. That satisfaction has increased or that people are more likely to find the information they need first time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few summers ago when MPOX (previously called monkeypox) broke out I did this in very cheap way. It was an emergency ask and I helped a bunch of clinicians, call centre teams and tech people come together and make the heath protection teams response more sustainable and effective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I did the work I reported up and out at all times. Starting with daily notes and then weeknotes to directors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ensured that directors and teams knew it was the work I was doing that contributed to other things they heard about. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was my work to get people together, map out the existing service and insights and help plot 3 or 4 changes we could make. Another team put the solution in place. But without the design and facilitation that didn’t happen. So I could (justifiably) claim that credit and my part to play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We got early estimates of the time saved and I shared those too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This built up the links between other work and my work. Between what I do and better outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few weeks later a very UCD sceptical director calls myself and my director in for a chat. They had more they want to do together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was easier to then build a relationship and “justify” the sorts of roles and how they work as they’d seen it work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;6. Make sure everyone in the profession knows the impact we have and how to explain it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When a design team is small it’s easier to do this. To tell stories and keep the story going. As a team grows or you’re in a big organisation where ways of working can be so different everywhere do the work to make sure people are mapping how they contribute through small contributions to bigger outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teach, train and hold people accountable. Talk about it a lot. Give people the tools to talk about it. And do so before you need to justify your impact as a profession.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;7. Find friends and the right places to make an impact&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find the sweet spot between what your organisation really cares about and where your skills and those of your teams can really contribute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find friends and allies. Be okay with less ideal situations that let you demonstrate value. And exploit those to build the relationships and trust you in need to make an impact. And it be easier to demonstrate that value next time&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>When and how to move from an assumption to a hypothesis</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2024/03/12/moving-from-an-assumption-to-a-hypothesis.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2024/03/12/moving-from-an-assumption-to-a-hypothesis.html</id>
    <published>2024-03-12T19:11:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2024-03-17T09:54:36+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Working at pace often means you need to work on assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The current team I’m leading. I’ve had to make some assumptions clear that we would have to work to. Some about our users. Most though, about the organisation. We had to believe certain things will be true to unblock our focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you define what feature, service or product you need to build. A team will have assumptions about how their users work. Or what their stakeholders want.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power of an assumption is it gets you somewhere fast. You act on belief, on faith that something is true. The problem is, they&amp;rsquo;re not based on fact. And can be very optimistic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the business assumptions I asked my team to work under, I set out to make them true. Gaining support or buy in for certain approaches. Or confirming shared priorities and expectations. Where things needed adjusting or there was nuance, we worked that though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the assumptions about our users and how a new thing would work. It’s a little trickier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t normally hold a workshop or two or have a side chat and clear the approach. There isn’t a steering group or senior leader to clear things with. What 1 user tells you might be contradicted by the next 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than working on assumptions, which can be useful to get some momentum, it’s worth turning things into hypotheses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An assumption is a guess or thing that you work on with the belief that it’s true. A (good) hypothesis doesn’t come with any belief. It’s an idea or statement you use as a starting point to prove or disprove a position.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir right fig-right fig-right-gutter" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/Another note to note.jpeg" alt="A seemingly endless row of sticky notes in tight grids with people slowly melting into them"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;By translating your assumptions into hypothesis you reduce risk. And build a pattern of learning into your process&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This way you’re framing things to remove the risk of working on a belief that can be false. And the work that you do gets more agile and clear about what decision you’re trying to make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember working in a team who often assumed a certain feature of a rival company worked. Rather than set out to prove or disprove the idea. They just acted as it was true and designed and built accordingly. What the team found out often was all the reasons things didn’t work, far too late. And often a few versions behind the rival company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The company was always playing catch up working on the assumption that the bigger rival knew what they were doing. And what was public was the most optimal version of an idea. But if you’ve ever built anything you know the path to live is full of compromise and promises to fix things later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if it sounds dumb to work on the assumption other companies know what they’re doing. Well, that’s most organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of this is again, that assumptions are so powerful. A bit of faith and it unlocks the ability to act. But when it comes to your users or customers. It gets risky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an assumption turns out to be wrong. You’ve built and acted on something that’s false and potentially going to be bad. If a hypothesis is wrong, you’ve got an opportunity to act differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To turn something into a hypothesis is pretty easy. It’s basically a statement that can be proven true or false. &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2018/12/19/trying-a-new-format-for-hypotheses.html"&gt;I like to use certain formats&lt;/a&gt; but there are plenty of options. The key for me is to state how you expect to judge a statement is right or wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can do this on your own or as a team. And many &lt;a href="https://duckworth.design/our-playbook/assumption-mapping.html"&gt;formats exist to map your assumptions as a team&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The beauty of assumptions are that they can come from lots of different people. Which means they can be &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2024/01/24/it-s-okay-to-start-with-a-stakeholder-s-solution-just-don-t-stop-there.html"&gt;useful to start with to help define an early visions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You could also use something like ChatGPT to help you if you’re struggling. Do that by stating your assumptions and ask it to turn it into a hypothesis. Give it a format. And ensuring to tweak the output to ensure it’s not a sack of rubbish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking my mind back to the team that copied their competitors, if we had just stated some of the assumptions as hypotheses. We’d have realised we didn’t rate the idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Should everything be a hypothesis? I don’t think so. Time is short. You need to spend your time experimenting and learning on things that make an impact. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;something is outside your direct control&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;relies on users or customers (including internal users)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;there is a real risk of something goes wrong or doesn’t work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and the cost of finding out by building it is higher than faking it, then treat it like a hypothesis. Else, take a view on whether an assumption is safe to make and proceed from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To state it another way, what’s the cost if what we believe isn’t true? Start there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it’s an internal set of teams you need to work with. It’s an assumption and whether you act on it depends on when you’re able to make a decision with others fast enough (and the risk of doing so).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it’s a user, customer or wider community facing thing, work out the risk. And if it’s at all worrying or impactful, treat it like a hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By translating your assumptions into hypothesis you reduce risk. And build a pattern of learning into your process. And being clear when you create hypotheses or act on assumptions you will balance risk and speed.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>It's okay to start with a stakeholder's solution. Just don't stop there</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2024/01/24/it-s-okay-to-start-with-a-stakeholder-s-solution-just-don-t-stop-there.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2024/01/24/it-s-okay-to-start-with-a-stakeholder-s-solution-just-don-t-stop-there.html</id>
    <published>2024-01-24T19:52:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2024-01-24T22:01:33+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter if you&amp;rsquo;re working in a complex organisation or not. It&amp;rsquo;s pretty common to work on projects where you have opinionated colleagues who have a &amp;ldquo;stake&amp;rdquo; in the product or feature working. Either to their part of an organisation or their reputation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be the starting point for a lot of terrible features and ideas. Or things that sound very believable but aren&amp;rsquo;t quite right. Particularly if teams just get their heads down and do the thing they&amp;rsquo;re asked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean they don&amp;rsquo;t understand things or their vision is invalid. Or not a starting point to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s okay to start with a stakeholder&amp;rsquo;s vision or solution. And use it as the first hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not dirty or bad practice to listen to your partners and help them work through how they see things working now and what might make that better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just don&amp;rsquo;t stop there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve seen so many teams waste weeks and months in turmoil because they have stakeholders with strong opinions and visions but try to define their own separate &amp;ldquo;pure&amp;rdquo; visions and plans in isolation when there&amp;rsquo;s one sitting there to try with or understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a waste of time. And emotional energy. Because you&amp;rsquo;ll end up needing to explain why your vision will work and not the one they have in their head. And that&amp;rsquo;ll turn into a straight shootout. If you&amp;rsquo;re lucky they&amp;rsquo;ll see how to combine things. If you&amp;rsquo;re not you&amp;rsquo;ll have to throw yours out and any good ideas with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In GOV design in the UK I see this a lot. People will share their work or talk things through. There is often a sense of exhaustion and despair if a service or product seems to be building off a stakeholder vision or idea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or if they&amp;rsquo;re collecting some stakeholder&amp;rsquo;s idea as if that invalidates their user-centred credentials. It does if that&amp;rsquo;s the only thing you do. Or. If you don&amp;rsquo;t challenge, combine and explore things with your users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than avoid stakeholder ideas. Lean into it and make it part of a process. Help your partners map out their vision of how things work now and could work. And use that process to challenge, highlight risks and approaches to test those ideas. Or what possible other ideas there are to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll be surprised how much easier it is to talk about things when you make them clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use the process to show how to take a vision and understand it and your users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/simple map.png" alt="A zoomed out example of some pictures and boxes explaining a service journey. Used to generate comments and thoughts"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Use simple models and visualisations to capture feedback and make processes and visions clearer&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do that alongside and with these teams and show them a process that helps them detect and understand user needs in robust ways. They&amp;rsquo;ll be responding to signals too and a desire to make something better or different for a reason. And understanding that motivation will help you to collect the right insights to prove or disprove their ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do it by using frameworks like problem statements to capture the intent behind asks. Do it by helping them visualise how things work today in user journey maps and pin where and what they&amp;rsquo;re trying to change. Do it by treating them as partners in delivering on user needs and coherent and effective services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do it by creating small, constant loops of progress. By creating a shared vision of how things work now and what the future could look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re worried that this means that big ideas and new futures can’t happen. You’ll be surprised how open people can get if you’ve brought them into the process. Plus it’s a lot easier to be radical and challenging when you know what people’s current ideas and thoughts are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir right fig-right fig-right-gutter" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/stakeholder sticky notes.jpeg" alt="A styleish print of people overlayed with stickynotes - By Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s not dirty or bad practice to listen to your partners and help them work through how they see things working now and what might make that better&amp;rdquo;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;User centred services start with the user and put them at the heart of your designs. But if your operational, policy, strategic or other colleagues can&amp;rsquo;t have their visions and ideas taken through that process then we&amp;rsquo;ll not make better services. We&amp;rsquo;ll just have unhelpful conflicts between teams and not create the services we&amp;rsquo;ll need to provide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll get more space and autonomy to explore the right solution the faster and quicker you gain the confidence and trust of your stakeholders and partners. You&amp;rsquo;ll also gain the space to critique and spot the risks that motivate them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lean into working with stakeholder ideas, solutions and visions. This is where most of the work is in complex organisations and systems. Where many people have their own visions and goals. And only by treating each other as equal partners will we be able to define the right vision and goals. And design user centred services and products.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Start with the forms</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/12/11/start-with-the-forms.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/12/11/start-with-the-forms.html</id>
    <published>2023-12-11T19:28:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-12-12T10:18:18+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently finished a couple of discoveries. Based down in London and within the NHS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things I was looking into is the pain points between primary and secondary care. That is, between GPs (doctors) and services that GPs refer you to like hospital clinics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One part of the project was to collect, map and assess the size and shape of the problems. Which if you’re interested in I’m happy to chat through. And point to the strategic and tactical approaches to making this better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir left fig-left fig-left-gutter" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/torus torus.jpeg" alt="Layers and layers of people running and running through sticky notes and forms - By Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;ldquo;You’ll have the credit to be able to work on other things that no doubt need to change too.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We mapped many painpoints, projects and attempts to resolve issues. But a real incubator for continued innovation and improvement was forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is. Starting with the forms. And using that as the first step in collaboration. In making daily issues better. And building trust between different teams or people not used to working together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be it making them easier to find, enter the right details or using them to route a person to the right care. Improving forms was a first step in challenging how things work. And how to work better in challenging times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking through some choice quotes when pulling together some research I came across this one:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Pathway design has been positively impacted through collaboration around form design”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve found this myself. Countless times I’ve come in to help design a form flow but what’s been needed. And happened. Is real transformation. But transformation that starts with a few clearer questions. Or smarter use of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I was to tell anyone where to start. Particularly in a complex system like the NHS, it would be to start with the forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make it easier to pass across data. To ask for help. To give help. To get the information people need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re a great place to kickstart real conscious design of service. With the added benefit of showing rapid improvements. And all the blockers you might encounter making things better. Be they cultural, organisational or technological.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hosting a workshop between doctors in the community and in hospitals we started with a form process. And ended by removing blockers that had taken a year to sort. Just by getting in room together to make a form better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you start with a form you’ll have evidence of making people’s lives easier. Data more complete or accurate. And processes more efficient that you’ll have the credit to be able to work on other things that no doubt need to change too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Start with a form. Start with something tangible and well used. &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/10/27/why-we-design-forms.html"&gt;Good form design improves so much&lt;/a&gt;. And start your transformation there. And &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2021/03/19/win-space-to-design.html"&gt;win the space to design whole services&lt;/a&gt; and transform the system.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
