<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Andrew Duckworth</title>
  <subtitle>Designer, artist</subtitle>
  <id>https://grillopress.github.io/</id>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2020-01-02T07:30:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Share before you solve it</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2020/01/02/share-before-you-solve-it.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2020/01/02/share-before-you-solve-it.html</id>
    <published>2020-01-02T07:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2020-01-03T09:20:07+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s nothing I love more than bouncing ideas and questions around with a designer. Be it in a team, a weekly thing, a slack channel or with a colleague. It&amp;rsquo;s partly why I arrange the weekly design meetups at NHS Digital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However you do it. It&amp;rsquo;s vital to share. And share what you&amp;rsquo;re working on before you &amp;ldquo;solve it&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The earlier you share an issue or idea the more room you have to ask the right questions and get answers you can handle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It gives you time and space to speak through your thinking. And to have that thinking challenged whilst you have space to change things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve spent time iterating and fine-tuning an idea. You&amp;rsquo;re invested. And it can be hard not to defend. It can be hard to look wide again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your design may also be &amp;ldquo;publicised&amp;rdquo;. With other teams may already have started shaping their work based on your solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your work doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be well polished to talk it through either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I’ve talked through a range of design options to letting users upload a file to their GP. I had a few rough screens designed but all I talked through was a scrappy page and some arrows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This helped a colleague challenge my thinking. And get to a better design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Share your work before you solve it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Yearnote: 2019</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/12/28/in-review.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/12/28/in-review.html</id>
    <published>2019-12-28T07:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2020-01-03T00:13:22+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s been a year. Lots of things I hope I’ll not have to deal with again. And some I know I will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s tempting to put 2019 straight in the bin. From a work point of view I’ve had plenty of downs this past year. And recently I had been feeling out of sorts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But taking some advice I’ve given others plenty of times. I made a list of some stuff that was pretty cool that I did in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the stuff I did:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finished an alpha into how health records are used, successfully not building a service that would have increased burden on the NHS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Passed live service assessment for the opt-out service. First NHS service to do so!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Led a discovery into the uses of patient data for research. Helped the NHS pivot from building a costly service and find other ways to satisfy uncovered needs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Steered a discovery looking into how patients get contacted/communicated with. Ended by having my recommendations taken seriously by those at the very top of the NHS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Helped Sam and Rhiannon develop as people, professionals and pass their end of graduate scheme assessments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Designed an MVP notifications and messaging service&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Helped reshape the short/medium term future of appointments in the NHS App&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Presented at 2 NHS Digital code clubs. Helping loads of people get to grips with coding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ran the weekly NHS Digital design meet-ups in Leeds&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Helped lots of colleagues design better shit and create some cool prototypes to test their thinking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2019 I led 4 discoveries, 3 alphas, 1 beta and taking 1 service into live management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe 2019 doesn’t belong &lt;em&gt;completely&lt;/em&gt; in the bin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2019 was full of opportunities and I&amp;rsquo;m grateful for those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though it wasn&amp;rsquo;t calm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something I&amp;rsquo;m going to try be smarter with the opportunities that come my way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than saying no though. I&amp;rsquo;m going to try to pass on and share opportunities that don&amp;rsquo;t quite fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did that last summer and it turned out to be a great decision. For me. And the team too because I was able to give the opportunity to one of the best designers I know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More of that in 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Stuff I wrote in 2019&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Articles&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote 16 articles. Most based on advice I gave someone in person. Or to remind myself to do better next time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/12/05/stretch-your-design.html"&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t forget to stretch your design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/12/05/design-for-real-data.html"&gt;Design for real data&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/10/22/use-the-right-words.html"&gt;Find the right words to get the job done&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/10/10/start-it-right.html"&gt;Start it right&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/10/08/make-it-about-a-decision.html"&gt;Make it about a decision&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/08/05/let-your-design-breathe.html"&gt;Let your design breathe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/07/25/make-it-easier-to-work-in-the-open.html"&gt;Make it easier for yourself and others to work in the open&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/06/10/make-things-open.html"&gt;Making your work open isn&amp;rsquo;t just the final icing on the cake&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/05/04/writing-shorthand.html"&gt;Prototyping in shorthand&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/04/06/minus-interference.html"&gt;Minus interference&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/03/26/you-never-know-you-know.html"&gt;You never know, you know&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/03/18/do-the-hard-work-to-make-it-inclusive.html"&gt;Do the hard work to make it inclusive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/01/31/one-thing.html"&gt;One thing per page&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/01/31/asking-questions.html"&gt;Ask a question&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/01/20/asking-the-right-question.html"&gt;Asking the right question&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/01/10/doing-paper-forms.html"&gt;Offline services and paper forms&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also wrote a pattern about asking patients for their NHS number. Which is much better now. Through feedback from the wider NHS design community. And the service manual team at NHS Digital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://beta.nhs.uk/service-manual/styles-components-patterns/nhs-number"&gt;Ask users for their NHS number&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Discovery notes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In April I also wrote weeknotes for each week of a discovery into the uses of data in the NHS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/05/31/discovery-notes-08.html"&gt;Week 08&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/05/24/discovery-notes-07.html"&gt;Week 07&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/05/17/discovery-notes-06.html"&gt;Week 06&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/05/10/discovery-notes-04.html"&gt;Week 05&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/05/03/discovery-notes-03.html"&gt;Week 04&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/04/26/discovery-notes-03.html"&gt;Week 03&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/04/19/discovery-notes-02.html"&gt;Week 02&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="/2019/04/12/discovery-notes-01.html"&gt;Week 01&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Don't forget to stretch your design</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/12/05/stretch-your-design.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/12/05/stretch-your-design.html</id>
    <published>2019-12-05T07:30:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-12-06T15:25:50+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When reviewing a design, I like to ask how it will stretch to cover different scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When things are empty. When things go wrong. On different devices. But also for variable data or poor quality data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A designer should ensure they have a solid design for a common path. But it’s easy to design for unrealistically good examples or data. Or &lt;a href="https://samanthasaw.github.io/samantha-saw-blogs/check-how-your-design-works-on-different-devices.html"&gt;not consider all devices&lt;/a&gt; and when things go wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A long time ago I redesigned a few websites for a communications team. Part of the work was a clearer, more accessible web design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I designed some of the system and reviewed it against the live website, it dawned on me the how different some of the article headings were.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the H1s were full paragraphs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working with the team I knew this wasn’t going to change anytime soon. And even if it did, the years of news articles would still be there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My large clear font worked great for most of the website, but it didn’t stretch to this part of the website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To remedy this I first set up a web crawler to download every article into a spreadsheet. I could then analyse the size and shape of the data my design had to stretch to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My design was much better for it. My design was now more flexible and able to cope with real data. It was no longer so brittle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be sure to &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/12/05/design-for-real-data.html"&gt;design for real data&lt;/a&gt; and real user journeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can either design for data so good it’ll never exist. Or accommodate what a user will experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your design will have to stretch to getting data back from APIs in FULL SCREAMING UPPERCASE. And some users seeing 1 category, and others seeing 32. Or comms teams who like to write full paragraphs as a heading.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t forget to stretch your design.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Design for real data</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/12/05/design-for-real-data.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/12/05/design-for-real-data.html</id>
    <published>2019-12-05T07:29:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2019-12-06T15:39:03+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It’s vital to design for real data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t, your service or product design is artwork. And your design will not be made. Even if it tests well. Because it can’t be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When designing a service that includes data from a database you will have to design around the quality of data. And any business process rules for that data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designing for real data is vital when you have to accommodate data from other sources or APIs. Especially ones not designed for being shown to your users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When tackling a database or APIs you need to ask:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what&amp;rsquo;s the source of data?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what&amp;rsquo;s the original purpose of that data?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;who looks after the database?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how is it kept up to date?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how consistent is that data?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what&amp;rsquo;s the exact format of data?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what&amp;rsquo;s the most (length, number of items etc.) something can be? What&amp;rsquo;s the least?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what are some real examples you could use?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding the real shape of data will let you ask why. &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/12/05/stretch-your-design.html"&gt;Stretch your design&lt;/a&gt;. And potentially create moments to really transform services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A colleague &lt;a href="https://samanthasaw.github.io/samantha-saw-blogs/"&gt;Sam&lt;/a&gt; recently finished a project rethinking data collection. Part of her process she looked at previous submissions. As she did, she could point to failings and data quality issues. Which provided real evidence for change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can either design for data so good it’ll never exist. Or accommodate what a user will really experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s hard work. But it’s where the work really is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do the hard work. Design for real data.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Find the right words to get the job done</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/10/22/use-the-right-words.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/10/22/use-the-right-words.html</id>
    <published>2019-10-22T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-10-22T23:33:49+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;About a year ago a designer helped fill in for a couple of weeks when I was on leave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They mentioned that one of the development teams I worked with didn&amp;rsquo;t know some design thinking terminology, and it surprised them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially as I worked with them for over a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from inspiring some mild imposter syndrome, it got me thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things I like to do is make teams know the outcomes we&amp;rsquo;re trying to create. And the problems we&amp;rsquo;re trying to solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s why I do &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2017/12/10/hypothesis-driven-design.html"&gt;hypothesis driven design&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there&amp;rsquo;s a difference between working in the right way and dictating the exact words and ways we explain things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s about finding the right words to help each other understand how to get to a solution. Or what&amp;rsquo;s blocking one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From colleagues to stakeholders to users. You have to lean on commonly understood things. As well as what the people you&amp;rsquo;re working with say and label things as.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to use &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2018/12/19/trying-a-new-format-for-hypotheses.html"&gt;a set format for hypotheses&lt;/a&gt; and I use this to document my work. And when I get my work reviewed by colleagues I tend to talk through them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;rsquo;m not going to talk about hypothesis driven design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than talking about double diamonds, design thinking and hypotheses. It&amp;rsquo;s important to start by using the words and concepts of the team or individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a time and a place to introduce new things. But no one wants to be lectured at. Find the right words to get the job done.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Start it right</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/10/10/start-it-right.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/10/10/start-it-right.html</id>
    <published>2019-10-10T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-10-10T23:10:43+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve spent a fair amount of time doing discoveries in the last year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some better than others. And I&amp;rsquo;ve learnt loads.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that helps frame discoveries better is &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/10/08/make-it-about-a-decision.html"&gt;shaping them around a decision&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this well it’s best to kick off your discoveries with an “inception” meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An inception is a project kickoff session.  Everyone who is part of the discovery team should be there. As well as any decision maker or stakeholder too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This meeting helps you define the right scope and what you need to go find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A format for an inception that has worked for me and other teams I&amp;rsquo;ve helped is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is a discovery?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What problem or task have we been given?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our discovery is to decide [x]?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To make that decision, we need to know what?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What should we do to find out what we need to know?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This format helps get your team focused on the right things. And gives you the space to define what decision you&amp;rsquo;re going to tackle. As well as the steps you&amp;rsquo;re going to take to make that decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you don’t have a shared understanding of what decision you’re helping make. Or of what you need to do to support that decision, it’s nearly impossible to do any project justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No discovery should start without understanding what issue you&amp;rsquo;re exploring. Nor should they continue without you understanding what decision you are helping make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After defining the policy intent or issue to a decision you should discuss as a team what you need to know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding what a team needs to know is the most important part. This can range from &amp;ldquo;who are our users&amp;rdquo; to more specific technical issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you only have an hour together, you should spend half your time talking through what you know. And what you need to find out. As well as prioritising what to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you&amp;rsquo;ve defined as a group what you want to find out, you can define some activities you&amp;rsquo;ll likely do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This part might be flexible. But it helps push forward your team from things to find out, to what we can do about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Continuous inception&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s no reason to only do this sort of activity at the start of project either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the last summer I joined a discovery project several weeks in and struggled a little with the scope. By resetting it with the whole team I caught up but the team could also pivot on what they’d already found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That meeting shaped the next few weeks and helped us come to a different, better decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get your discovery going by setting the direction. By starting, or restarting, it right.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
