<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2018-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Explaining a thing over saying a thing</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/12/29/explaining-a-thing-over-saying-the-thing.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/12/29/explaining-a-thing-over-saying-the-thing.html</id>
    <published>2018-12-29T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2018-12-30T17:17:46+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Explaining what something is is almost always better than using a technical term for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t use complicated, specialist language in a service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even audiences you think will know what a word means will benefit from explaining a thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Avoid complex phrases unless you have clear and unambiguous proof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designing in the world of data, privacy and medical records you often have complicated concepts. And equally complicated terms:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anonymisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pseudonymisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data minimisation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In user research we see the negative reaction to these terms. Users find them confusing. Or evasive. And they are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of saying anonymisation, talk about information that has personal details removed. And give examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we share your information with another organisation, we remove all personal details such as your name and address&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being open and clear isn’t without problems. Exposing how you use someone else’s data can be problematic. But it’s the truth. And you shouldn’t be processing data without good reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technical terms or metaphors are always the worst choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explain the thing. Your service or product will benefit from it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Trying a new format for hypotheses</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/12/19/trying-a-new-format-for-hypotheses.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/12/19/trying-a-new-format-for-hypotheses.html</id>
    <published>2018-12-19T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2018-12-20T07:38:33+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a big fan of &lt;a href="http://grillopress.github.io/2017/12/10/hypothesis-driven-design.html"&gt;hypothesis driven design&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have advocated using it in my own team. In other NHS teams and across other organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was sitting in Bridgewater Place the other day and I overheard a team use it. A junior designer I worked with on a previous service has started doing it with his new team. A team that hasn&amp;rsquo;t always been great at doing design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing design hypotheses isn&amp;rsquo;t always pleasurable. It can be tough to get them exactly right. But they make you a better designer. And design better things as a team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The act of articulating your design choice further refines your design. And your skills as a designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By using a hypothesis driven design process you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Articulate your thinking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provide others with understanding of your thinking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a framework to test your designs against&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Develop a standard way of documenting your work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make better stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working on a new range of services with a new team we&amp;rsquo;re still finding our feet. And working out how we work together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing we are doing is looking at our format of hypotheses. We started with:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="list-unstyled list-margin--indent"&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[Context]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If [some action]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Then [outcome for users]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Because [reason for outcome]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re trying to make how we test things clearer. This is something a few people feedback when they talk about how they&amp;rsquo;ve adopted the format above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Find whatever works for you and your team is my answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, taking my advice, we&amp;rsquo;ve moved to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="list-unstyled list-margin--indent"&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[Context]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If [some action]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Then [outcome for users]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll know this works/is true when:&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;[Measurement]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The measurements are the key results. Some based on numbers. Some not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems to work right now. And it&amp;rsquo;s making them easier to write and easier to talk about how to prove an idea or not.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Make things obvious</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/12/18/simple.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/12/18/simple.html</id>
    <published>2018-12-18T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2018-12-18T21:56:29+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Good interaction design is about keeping things obvious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be it restraining complexity. Simplifying the complex. Or making a way forward clearer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the cross-gov slack a question was raised about the best way to show users something was being processed. And that the user would have to wait for a while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The request was long enough that the designer was worried about a user either trying to refresh the page. Or quit the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many things you can do to give the user reassurance or understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Disabled buttons, spinners, skeleton pages, spinners in buttons, animations, progress bars etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But creativity in this situation is your worst enemy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that seeing your users use your designs shows you is that anything smart doesn&amp;rsquo;t work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In isolation things like spinners in buttons can seem like smart solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surely the thing the user clicked is a great place to give feedback?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it violates a few things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;doesn&amp;rsquo;t act like a normal button or link&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;user clicks a button and expects a full page refresh so their focus moves away&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;visually a tiny place to explain a complex thing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;vague whether it is checking the form or submitting the form or the internet is being terrible&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this scenario the best approach is to be obvious. If the user has submitted data. Act as if that is the case and change the page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it may take a while while their data is processed. Make that obvious. Tell them. Particularly so if the transaction is serious.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you need to give them a sense the page isn&amp;rsquo;t dead. Give them that sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be obvious. Don&amp;rsquo;t let a user guess. If you&amp;rsquo;re too smart, you&amp;rsquo;ll be solving the wrong problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here the effort should be to reassure the user their data has been received and processed. Even if that takes longer than ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your greatest efforts though should be spent on making your service quicker.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Show at your show and tell</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/12/14/showing.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/12/14/showing.html</id>
    <published>2018-12-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2018-12-14T23:08:36+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve recently been reviewing some of the language we use in our service. What the terms mean and the implications they have for understanding the service. And how the NHS works in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been quite a contentious issue within the team because we want to balance between being:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;easy to understand&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;comprehensive and transparent&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;words people use themselves&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve run some pop-ups and a lab to focus on the words we use. In particular our service name and how we define the data people have a choice over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re getting closer to the point where we have a strong sense of direction. Nothing is easy here. But a sense of direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The work we had been doing recently culminated in a show and tell after a lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a great show and tell. What was the greatest part was letting the users talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had video after video on the same issue. What &amp;ldquo;confidential patient information&amp;rdquo; meant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It struck me as being one of the better show and tells I&amp;rsquo;ve been to for a while because:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;everything was on a topic we cared about&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;we let users do the talking&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;we discussed the issue as a team&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and came together to the solution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you have to pitch a vision, but when you can, let your users talk. It&amp;rsquo;s a lot more powerful than summarising their words.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Questions for your questions</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/12/05/questions-for-your-questions.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/12/05/questions-for-your-questions.html</id>
    <published>2018-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2018-12-05T17:14:03+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, to no fanfare, I put live a significant iteration to the non-digital service. The service helps users make a choice on how their children&amp;rsquo;s data can be used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the new process was an iteration on a previous form. The work brought together:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new visual system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduced list of identity documents required&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;simplified process to prove parental responsibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;user focused words and ways of asking questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Redesigning the forms with the team meant questioning everything. Things we held self-evident. Rules that were stuck-in-stone. Policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happily the whole team leapt into this work. Sam (grad content designer) and I had no need to canvas for support to charge ahead with this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It made me realise that you could better explore the tough parts of any service with the non-digital version first. That is, inputting information, reading it and processes. But not just pretend stuff (paper prototypes). But actual real life submissions. Paper is cheap. Easy to iterate. But live. If your service is a policy-driven thing. What better way to test drive whether that policy delivers what it needs to?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also felt that there are many questions you need to ask when designing a service that gets information from a user. That is, questions that all services, digital or not, should answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote some of these questions down and shared them. And in the spirit of making things open. Here is my first go at questions to ask yourself when designing services and forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Questions for your questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is your user trying to do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What information do you need to get them to their goal?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why are you asking for this information?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If any of it isn&amp;rsquo;t necessary, why are you asking for it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is what you&amp;rsquo;re asking for, the least you can get away with asking?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could you get the information you need from them without directly asking?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How would you ask the user in person for this information?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How would a user describe what they&amp;rsquo;re being asked for?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is there any format restrictions? (Age by number or specific date etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will the things you are asking for be expected or natural?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will the context of the service, or where the user is, change how appropriate the question is? (Sexual health, prison, on behalf of another etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will the location of the user change how easy to answer the question is? (Mobile, home, abroad, in an emergency)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What happens if the user can&amp;rsquo;t or won&amp;rsquo;t answer the question?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If there is a restriction, what happens if the user doesn&amp;rsquo;t meet it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Questions to help your questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do other services ask for this currently?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How effective is this? What do they say works or doesn&amp;rsquo;t work? If  they could click their fingers and it happen, would they change anything?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What help does other systems provide to help people answer it? (Before they fill it in)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What help does it provide if the answer isn&amp;rsquo;t filled in?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What help does it provide if the format is wrong?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What happens when a user doesn&amp;rsquo;t meet the requirements? (For example, they are too young)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 16</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/11/02/weeknotes-16.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/11/02/weeknotes-16.html</id>
    <published>2018-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2018-11-06T07:10:43+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back on the Weeknotes wagon. See how long this&amp;rsquo;ll last&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fair chunk of Monday spent reviewing the work done on the paper forms. Sam (graduate designer) took a day last week to get heads down on the forms. We worked through some issues and translated her content into the new design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The forms have come a long way. Even from September. Much of that credit to the team jumping into this issue. And Sam&amp;rsquo;s hard work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon the national data opt-out team met up to talk about the research roadmap. We reviewed what we had planned. Including the paper forms and the accessibility audit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some extra work planned in for December. Had a good discussion with the programme manager about what we needed to do next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also looked at how we are evaluating comprehension. There were a few questions that when we wrote them they worked well enough but now we could see how to improve them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sent over the finished paper forms to the user researchers to help them do a live test of their lab plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Backlog review for the national data opt out service. Talked through a few cards and bugs I created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spent much of the day with the senior members of the design community talking about design culture. Both in the community and wider organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We celebrated the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-future-of-healthcare-our-vision-for-digital-data-and-technology-in-health-and-care/the-future-of-healthcare-our-vision-for-digital-data-and-technology-in-health-and-care"&gt;new vision for health tech&lt;/a&gt; released by the department of health and social care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few of us in the room had written the NHS design principles. But we also pondered how we can get our organisation to talk more about design and its value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a productive chat with the developers about the future product. Not my role, but talked though technical architecture. We talked through how we could make the most developer friendly set up. Whilst maintaining the most device/platform agnostic frontend possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ended the day talking to the audit and transparency team about user research. Design questions and content questions. Always enjoy talking to Lucy, Will and Sam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the day talking to Will (researcher on audit and transparency) about problem statements. The problem statement had gone through many changes. But there wasn&amp;rsquo;t a confirmed one. I felt we had one pretty much there. With enough scope not to allow for a pivot. We agreed to go for it in the steering group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had my first steering group show and tell for audit and transparency. Everything was very positively received. Make sure Sam&amp;rsquo;s good work on the content discovery was front and centre too. One of the clinicians raised a great point. When giving users a look at their medical record you have to be aware there are risks that they are being treated for things they may not think they are. Or how it is recorded in their medical record may make it look more serious than it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the call switched back to the opt-out service&amp;rsquo;s paper forms. Went through the initial feedback and lab plan with the user researchers. A few small things to change and some to watch in the lab next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the issues was having nothing but a PO address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought the lack of a service name or title for the postal address would make that seem creepy. Rather than secure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon we had a long user stories review and writing session. Cleared out some older ones. Wrote some cornerstones. More work to do. Good session though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finished the day chatting about information architecture to Sam. The picture of the NHS website platform and our user&amp;rsquo;s needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the day with a chat with the NHS website team with how to get access to edit the website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got the audit and transparency team together to talk through content. We talked:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As is picture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search terms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Referrers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organisational strategy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &amp;ldquo;to be&amp;rdquo; picture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best thing we got out of the day was a better understanding of the whole galaxy that our users navigate. When it comes to finding out about their health records, users often start with their GP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over lunch heard about what Well Digital have been up to. The format was pretty well organised. It was nice to hear they cared about the human processes behind the digital and not the computers bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing overran but would have asked about clinical risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked about the new audit service we are building at the design huddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked through our design principles and design constraints. Pitched a short sketching challenge too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could tell from a few faces that the designers thought the challenge was obvious. But when we talked things through it wasn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of us in that room have apps and use services that let us audit our activity. In the app or service (energy usage, milage, spend) and some that let us audit how the data about us is generated or shared. Like Uber, Google etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not as productive as I&amp;rsquo;d like. Lots of small things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gave a colleague a review of some of the stuff I sent another team. A situation where I tried to help nudge and review some work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Created some materials for the upcoming lab. Wasn&amp;rsquo;t as straight forward as I had hoped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed the paper forms once last time with Sam. Took a decision on a few items that were left outstanding. Everything ready for the lab next Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
