<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Andrew Duckworth</title>
  <subtitle>Designer, artist</subtitle>
  <id>https://grillopress.github.io/</id>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2019-05-10T08:30:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Week 05</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/10/discovery-notes-04.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/10/discovery-notes-04.html</id>
    <published>2019-05-10T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-05-13T23:41:03+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Failed to make any notes for the last week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some stuff happening that made it emotionally quite exhausting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Better API&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovery wise I finally cracked the API I was exploring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turned out I was seeing a spreadsheet that was only a summary. What someone thought was what I would be interested in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fields were right but some of the details I wanted were missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Went from “your data was part of the A&amp;amp;E dataset” to tracking exact bits of data shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a user this means we could be clearer about what identifiable stuff is shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of “we shared details that personally identify you” we can give more context. Postcodes were shared because the study was about a specific area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looked like the API available would need lots of love. Processes might still do. But less to overhaul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Getting stuff out of my head&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest sins you see in meetings is overeager solution designing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Is this a problem?” is often lost the second you have a solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean, if you have a solution, course there’s a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than criticising people it’s helpful to ask questions to get back to the problem. Or take a solution as a set of assumptions or research questions to tackle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond meetings solutions can hang around in the mind. Particularly when trying to explore if a problem is significant or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was causing some issues for me when exploring the API. It was quite easy to think of solutions to things that aren’t needed. And take what’s possible and engineer experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of this rattled around my mind all week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Took Friday to purge some of it. Get it out on paper. Sketch some components and flows so they didn’t rattle around and get in the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the ideas and solutions are down I&amp;rsquo;m not worrying about them. They&amp;rsquo;re a bunch of assumptions and I&amp;rsquo;m taking them as material to form research questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put things to bed by getting them out of your head.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Prototyping in shorthand</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/04/writing-shorthand.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/04/writing-shorthand.html</id>
    <published>2019-05-04T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-05-09T08:34:40+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in my last &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/03/discovery-notes-03.html"&gt;discovery notes&lt;/a&gt; I like to write up pages in a shorthand method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t something that only I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was helping out in services week for &amp;ldquo;formapalooza&amp;rdquo; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Ralph_Hawkins"&gt;Ralph Hawkins&lt;/a&gt; spoke about the format he used in Google docs to write pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format follows the shapes of interface elements using:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;div class="dl_element"&gt;
    &lt;dt&gt;Radio buttons&lt;/dt&gt;
    &lt;dd&gt;(&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;)&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="dl_element"&gt;
    &lt;dt&gt;Checkboxes&lt;/dt&gt;
    &lt;dd&gt;[&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;]&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="dl_element"&gt;
    &lt;dt&gt;Input fields&lt;/dt&gt;
    &lt;dd&gt;[&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;]&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="dl_element"&gt;
    &lt;dt&gt;Buttons&lt;/dt&gt;
    &lt;dd&gt;[ Continue ]&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do this too. But I like to add a few markdown elements as well, so &lt;code&gt;#&lt;/code&gt;&amp;lsquo;s for headings. So:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="list-unstyled"&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;# Heading one&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;## Heading two&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;### Heading three&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means I like to write pages like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
# Make your choice

You need to choose what you're going to have for tea.

It's really important.

## What do you want for tea?

( ) Curry
( ) Chips and sausages
( ) Pizza

[ Continue ]

&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Write in this format or similar in a sharable doc and you’ve got a way for a whole team to work together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can even use document editor styles like links.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using shorthand makes it easy for two designers to collaborate on screens. Or for other members of the team or other teams to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use Google docs, word or a notes app. It’s a quick way of prototyping screens and flows. It’ll help you focus on the important bits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the words and questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the structure and flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and ultimately, if your service meets a need&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Week 04</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/03/discovery-notes-03.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/03/discovery-notes-03.html</id>
    <published>2019-05-03T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-05-04T22:19:07+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Met with Phil Cooke from the Data request service and data access environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked about background to some of the internal data pipeline for NHS digital. Constraints. Things to improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saw the benefits of a cross programme workshop we held before. Getting out of your part of the business is the type of thing that rewards you long after the initial reason you held a workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a couple of practical questions answered. And a name to help with digging into the API/database which logs where your data has been shared for research and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed the opt out service development backlog. We have four tickets left (!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed the prototype from Friday. Few things to glue together. On reflection a few things to clean up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s always some rework moving from a sketch on a sticky note to another level of fidelity. And that&amp;rsquo;s fine. Things sound better in the head and worse when said. Giving things shape will always be a challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam asked for &lt;a href="https://github.com/alphagov/govuk-design-system-backlog/issues/29"&gt;examples of declarations from around government and got linked to this&lt;/a&gt;. A reminder that GitHub isn&amp;rsquo;t always obvious to search, but is a treasure trove of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed some information architecture issues with Rhiannon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrote up some notes into a presentation. Tussled with it for most of the day. Didn&amp;rsquo;t quite get the narrative right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retro and planning with Will, Lucy and Emma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talked about what we&amp;rsquo;ve got in the next few weeks. I talked a little about getting to the heart of what makes a research study an attractive for someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d gotten my hands on an API spec so will jump into what we log about research studies at NHS digital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More work on a presentation. Still didn&amp;rsquo;t like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chat with Jordan (grad researcher). Catch up on how he&amp;rsquo;s getting on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talked about being able to talk about why you use a method and tools. Job interviews and assessment criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More tweaks on a presentation. Still didn&amp;rsquo;t like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popped onto a call with the leadership team of the NHS website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gave the presentation. Went fine. Gave a service eye&amp;rsquo;s view of a few issues with the website. Nothing insurmountable. Everyone was very nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked through the job descriptions with Sam. What type of things a designer needs to show. Matching it against the spec etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dialled in to the content huddle. Really glad to see the content community chatting through some issues. Was about the &lt;a href="#"&gt;care cards component&lt;/a&gt; and some questions about implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strict scenario the component should only be used in means it&amp;rsquo;s something you should set apart from the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not a general building block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s more of a very specific solution in response to a very specific scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A solution that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re unsure works in the specific situation it handles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unsure whether every type of &amp;ldquo;get help&amp;rdquo; should be solved by the care card&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unclear how it&amp;rsquo;ll work alongside other cards or long pages of content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The type of thing that should be shared and discussed as a solution to a particular problem. But rolled out cautiously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pop up day in Bradford uni for the research team. 98% of those talked to would be happy to proactively share data with the NHS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of interesting things shared (Will being heckled one foot into Bradford).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One person who didn&amp;rsquo;t want to share their data but it was nothing to do with the NHS. They just didn&amp;rsquo;t trust data being shared on computers. Once it&amp;rsquo;s online or in a database it could be leaked, hacked and shared beyond purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also heard about someone who is happy to share but where they used to live they would have said no. With concerns about the weaponisation of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People told us &amp;ldquo;for training&amp;rdquo; was a good reason to share data too. Hadn&amp;rsquo;t heard that before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed the pages on the NHS digital website we want a survey. And what we wanted to ask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam did some great work on search terms in Google analytics and Google search console.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam made a list of pages that would be good to ask questions on. We went through reviewing each page if we had specific thing to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shared the questions round the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We based our questions on something that really worked for us on the health records pages before. With a tweak or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emma had a couple of questions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked through some changes to the data donor screens with Sam&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then had a debrief with Ruth and Sam about the pop-up the day before which lasted most of the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunch then reviewing our work. More prototyping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mainly in shared docs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re using a shared doc to write the screens in shorthand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
( ) For radio buttons

[ ] For checkboxes

[           ] Input fields

[ Buttons ]

Etc.
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t new. I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing notes to myself in a mixture of shorthand and markdown on my mobile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we agreed it works for us working together. In that space between sketch and full screen or prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Went over earlier to BWP so Sam could get the NHS app environments set up on her laptop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good huddle reviewing some work on eRS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing will make your work better faster than sharing your work in the open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;ll hurt at times. But do it early and often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if someone asks for your help listen to the constraints. Context. And give them the fruit of all the hard work you&amp;rsquo;ve done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing and critiquing other people&amp;rsquo;s work will make you better. You&amp;rsquo;ll see things that&amp;rsquo;ll work for you. And spot issues you have too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always try and make Friday a chatty day. Answer emails. Respond to questions. Post questions. Raise issues or fixes on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today was no exception. Wrote up some documentation too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answered some development issues and dug into why some CSS was working on the prototype but not a build environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrote a few sketches up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed Sam&amp;rsquo;s work on the prototype. Helped her stitch a few things together and taught her about JavaScript objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rhiannon noticed a couple of things so fixed them in the opt out prototype. Chatted about a question from Ruth. She&amp;rsquo;s going to dig into the data and see what&amp;rsquo;s what.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Week 03</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/04/26/discovery-notes-03.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/04/26/discovery-notes-03.html</id>
    <published>2019-04-26T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-04-29T19:49:55+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slow day. Other things to sort beyond work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed the new end of service feedback questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrote up some thoughts on a few issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agreed to do a talk about GDS assessment to the graduate BA community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the morning was a resetting exercise following the workshop the week before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be tough to get talking about data with people. It&amp;rsquo;s abstract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we&amp;rsquo;re prototyping to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovery so far has been slower than hoped. Some of that&amp;rsquo;s due to changes based on feedback from a lab and workshop. Some of it other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught up with a graduate researcher to see how he was going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spent the time before and after lunch mapping out an exploratory service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re going to explore attitudes to data with a data donor service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the provocative questions  underlining the prototype was:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;d be happy if you or your loved one benefited from medical research, so would you be happy to donate your data to help this?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re exploring:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how happy people are to share data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what changes if they data is donated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what happens when people look at matching data with projects that would like it to be shared with. And those they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what people need to know to understand research studies and make a decision about them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what we&amp;rsquo;d need to show to give people a sense of positive feeling about donating&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what people would want in a way or a happy ending&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrote a presentation about 5 lessons from doing GDS assessments. For the huddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Couple of issues here or there. Mostly spent time sketching a flow with Sam in response to the service we mapped out the day before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed some work of Rhiannon&amp;rsquo;s. Asked for her decision on what of the three options was her preferred thing to take forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did some annual review meetings. Always important for people to know what they&amp;rsquo;re responsible for. What good looks like and what&amp;rsquo;s important to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back on sketching out the basic flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then to the huddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Didn&amp;rsquo;t end up giving my GDS presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked about how we document designs and design decisions. Then an interesting issue from Ben Cullimore about highlighting that the NHS website medicines A to Z may not include every medicine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prototyping prototyping prototyping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Divided up the work with Sam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked to Ben about benefit realisation and OKRs (objectives and key results).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joined in a discussion on slack about documenting design decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poked Mat Johnson to share his tweet in slack as well as the twitters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-dnt="true"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Utterly &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/lazyweb?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#lazyweb&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;swiftly and simply&lt;/em&gt; documenting and recording design decisions to create a usable record. What do you do? Any good posts I should look at?&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mat Johnson (@demotive) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/demotive/status/1121335669958246400?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;April 25, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;70 comments later I think it was a good thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s key to split up what it is you&amp;rsquo;re trying to document:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How things act and look (now, should)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Changes to designs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reasons for decisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are overlapping things but to me do have differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A reason for a change doesn&amp;rsquo;t need the whole service to be mapped out and every potential change shown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for a team meeting or planning session it might.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to find a consistent, efficient way to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My design team, &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2017/12/10/hypothesis-driven-design.html"&gt;we do hypothesis driven design&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal being to log why we&amp;rsquo;re making certain changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to put all hypotheses in the prototype. And some colleagues said it was useful. But watching them read it it was the major one or two before entry into a prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also got quite laborious to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the opt-out service I&amp;rsquo;ve created hundreds of prototypes. Documenting all things on our Jira board and the prototype become tedious and inefficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re writing lots of text in a prototype, you&amp;rsquo;re better off with a CMS or word document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within corporate environments there comes the question of shareability. If that document goes to confluence or SharePoint it might as well be buried in the garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, a prototype with a password and one designer to update it doesn&amp;rsquo;t sound like a great sharing mechanism either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, you have to find your way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the way forward isn&amp;rsquo;t doing nothing. Complicated systems need documenting. Teams need help being kept on the same page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2018/01/08/kanban_for_interaction_design.html"&gt;Document your work as you go&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2017/12/10/hypothesis-driven-design.html"&gt;Write hypotheses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make it easy to understand your work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make it easy to have a discussion about your work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Week 02</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/04/19/discovery-notes-02.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/04/19/discovery-notes-02.html</id>
    <published>2019-04-19T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-04-24T21:01:05+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed Rhiannon&amp;rsquo;s work on the live service&amp;rsquo;s start page. Good work. Massive simplification. Asked her to look at the page we let people download the paper forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a call with a colleague from NHS improvement about an information architecture issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a planning meeting with the team for the cross team inception workshop. Grabbed some time to confirm what we wanted to cover and the outcomes we wanted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Made a point of making sure everyone had a role. Be it presentation or facilitation or leading an activity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After lunch had a quick meeting about the &amp;ldquo;Detained and secure estates&amp;rdquo; service. Reset the plan for user research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let Sam lead on reviewing the forms and emails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ended the day writing the presentation for the workshop. Just enough presentation to allow us to ask provocative questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the day running through the slides with Sam for her activity. And the presentation with Will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And talking with Lucy and Emma about what they would cover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Held the workshop. We went into it with a clear feeling we didn&amp;rsquo;t want to spend 8 weeks discovering what we knew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About as perfect a workshop as possible. Hard questions were asked. We reset our scope to be much more ambitious. Good videos of users confirming that approach too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
  &lt;img src="/images/sam_at_workshop.jpg"/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Sam running a &amp;ldquo;min specs&amp;rdquo; exercise&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the workshop there was some slight reorganising of the team due to a new discovery piece.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practicalities of this took the wind out of the discovery workshop a little.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After lunch organised the design huddle about accessibility statements. Emma from NHS login has written one and wanted to update on that. I asked for access to the GDS one so we could cross reference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed Rhiannon&amp;rsquo;s work with Sam on the page for the paper form downloads. Added it to the prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then reviewed with Sam the NHS app content and the prison forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Live service release. Goodbye beta!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The release also included some accessibility improvements. And small but important CSS changes that improved how the service looked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early morning start at Bridgewater. Chat with Susie about the work she&amp;rsquo;s jumping onto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then an end of service survey review with Caroline Jarrett.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was a great meeting (as ever). Talked through what we are asking and what we wanted to know.  As ever the key is being purposeful about what you ask. And not hiding questions within questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walked back to the office then chatted through the one-time password improvements with Sam. We&amp;rsquo;d done quite a lot of work on this but it was time for a decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked about probability. &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/03/26/you-never-know-you-know.html"&gt;You never know&lt;/a&gt; so you have to weigh up how confident you are a change will solve an issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We both agreed it would solve a couple of issues. Though that the ultimate issue is improving data in another system. One this change can&amp;rsquo;t impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed Sam and Rhiannon&amp;rsquo;s work on the app and the live service landing pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Backlog review with product owner, lead developer and scrum master for the live service. We have a few things we will continue to work on but very happy with where the product is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After lunch took part in a workshop with &amp;ldquo;Empower the person&amp;rdquo; programme about consent and preferences. So completely up my street.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Found common ground and definitions. Then moved onto contact preferences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the audit and transparency alpha we explored showing people what information we had about people and in particular contact details. So we had lots of research here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the day talking about the workshop from the day before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walked over to Bridgewater with Sam to talk to the app team. Talking about issues and talking ways of working together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quick catch up with Tero then over to the office again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started a (delayed) design activity into exploring one of our big questions in discovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re looking to mock up a service to dig into some things we&amp;rsquo;ve seen over the last year or so.
Many people are really happy for their data to be used to help the NHS. In the workshop last week we heard:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If my data helps just one person it&amp;rsquo;s worth it&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We want to explore this. The limits and extent of this. The potential to help people see the impact their data is having. And if people want to do more. And if so, what that could look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We lost a couple of hours due to other meetings but got quite a lot mapped out. We&amp;rsquo;ll pick this up next week and take something to test with people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walked over to Bridgewater for the design huddle. Emma took us through the accessibility statement shed written for NHS login. I shared what GDS had given us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
  &lt;img src="/images/emma_at_the_huddle.jpg"/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Emma talking to the group about accessibility statements&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some questions left over on policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Matt Edgar also made a point about accessibility statements being the cost of not building things right. The shame of not doing it right and having to state everything you&amp;rsquo;ve done that isn&amp;rsquo;t up to standard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My concern was that as with cookie policies and privacy notices organisations soon get over that embarrassment. And they can become a dumping ground of &amp;ldquo;won&amp;rsquo;t fix&amp;rdquo; rather than the spirit behind the policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that every NHS team makes the right choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bank holiday. Walking. Beer. BBQ&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Week 01</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/04/12/discovery-notes-01.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/04/12/discovery-notes-01.html</id>
    <published>2019-04-12T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-04-15T06:52:20+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’m going to &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; and write up weeknotes during discovery. We&amp;rsquo;re deciding whether to a build a service to show the use of data for research and planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not everything will be about the discovery. But lots will.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the week by finishing off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewing error messages and end pages with Sam. She&amp;rsquo;s put in a lot of hard work and documented everything we do and want to do for users when things don&amp;rsquo;t work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed the feedback banner we&amp;rsquo;re going to use on the service. We&amp;rsquo;re removing the hotjar one. Avoiding an accessibility issue and letting us capture email addresses if users are happy to talk more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Went to the first opt-out service meeting since we passed our live service assessment. Looked at a few issues we want to tackle. Some stuff not quite right in the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last two weeks before we started our discovery we ran some exercises to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;state what we wanted to find out during discovery and scope of the discovery&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the decision we want to make and what questions we&amp;rsquo;ll need to answer to make the right one&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;our definition of done&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the things we thought we knew already&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the things we&amp;rsquo;re going to do&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today was a quick look back at all of our planning and how we are working as a team. And what we&amp;rsquo;re going to do over the next week or so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran the exercise in two parts. Things we should stop/start. A classic retro style meeting. And a quick calendar based chat about what we&amp;rsquo;ve got coming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plain to me that we could learn quicker with some props. Services or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later on reviewed the new service forms for making a choice for &amp;ldquo;the detained and secure estate&amp;rdquo; (screams forever). Meeting with that part of the programme was cancelled but work done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed some changes for the NHS website with Rhiannon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started with a call about SEO. Let Rhiannon take the lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ran through some accessibility tickets for the live service. Crossing turtles and dotting i&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then to the first workshop of discovery. 10 people in two sessions in Roundhay. New venue. Interesting. Not ideally placed for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
  &lt;img src="/images/roundhay.jpg" alt="Several people sitting at a desk writing up notes"/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Some of the Roundhay gang&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a drive over with Lucy. And a drive back with Ruth (product owner).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a good session. But we heard nothing radically new. Different stories with the same answers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;people make tradeoffs with data and privacy all the time (privacy loses)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;people think data sharing is consent based&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;people don&amp;rsquo;t think that data is processed beyond appointments or on request (blood tests)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;most people see why the NHS would share data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid using the word &amp;ldquo;confidential&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;anonymised&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;people are generally speaking cool with the NHS sharing data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;people like having a choice but rarely want to use it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;people prefer not to think about this stuff (&amp;ldquo;more worried about brexit&amp;rdquo;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helped out with analysis on the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Four days in and none of us want to hear the same answers. We agreed that we needed to be more ambitious. Provocative. And try a different approach if we were going to get anything out of this discovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
  &lt;img src="/images/analysis.jpg" alt="Lucy, Emma and Will looking at sticky notes"/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Is Will confused, suspicious or thinking too hard?&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed an issue on the live service. Came to an agreement with John (developer) on the right approach. I really enjoy working with John. Went you like working with people you should tell them. I make a point of that. John is a good egg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrote up a naming report for the programme with Sam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over to BWP for the design huddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had Lucy and Rhiannon from my team talk about their work on Electronic Prescription Service (often referred to as EPS). Bonnie talk about inclusive design. And Ben talk about the NHSX website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was great having Lucy and Rhiannon at the huddle. There are some tough challenges when rolling out new features nationally. It&amp;rsquo;s important we understand our users pain points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
  &lt;img src="/images/huddle-april.jpg" alt="Lucy and Rhiannon bossing it at the huddle"/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Lucy and Rhiannon bossing it at the huddle.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In light of the findings on Thursday, rewrote a session plan for a workshop with the programme next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spent most of the day enjoying a migraine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;If technology or policy was no barrier what would data sharing for research look like?&amp;rdquo; was the question I considered.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
