<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Andrew Duckworth</title>
  <subtitle>Designer, artist</subtitle>
  <id>https://grillopress.github.io/</id>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2019-05-24T08:30:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Week 07</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/24/discovery-notes-07.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/24/discovery-notes-07.html</id>
    <published>2019-05-24T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-05-28T07:46:21+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s difficult now would have been impossible before&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Week started in crunch mode trying to get the prototype ready for the lab on Tuesday. Most of the bits were there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sadly I was all across Leeds for a lot of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed the prototype with Sam. She took lead on the part of the prototype for the last lab activity. We sketched out the flow together. Two questions but if they answered yes to any one of them the system would get a little more complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She did an amazing job. There was some tricky logic to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s always worth reminding yourself that what&amp;rsquo;s difficult now would have been impossible before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Lots of likes but no needs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the lab users were very complimentary about the prototype service. But none of them had thought, never mind tried, to solve the issue it was attempting to meet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Their politeness about the service was nice. But it was all &lt;em&gt;nice&lt;/em&gt; to have and nothing they&amp;rsquo;d drop things to do. Or need to do before they could drop things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be very easy to be persuaded by people saying they&amp;rsquo;d use a service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or that something they&amp;rsquo;re interacting with is interesting and means something to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But people say things but behave very differently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The user is in a strange room with strange people interacting with a strange system asking strange things. It&amp;rsquo;s natural behaviour to be nice and say pleasant things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Key of course is to really watch people&amp;rsquo;s behaviour. Before and after interacting with a thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The service wasn&amp;rsquo;t going to meet any need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
  &lt;img src="/images/real-needs.png"/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Some sort of visual metaphor for users solving problems because they have a need &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The strategy is delivery (but not this thing)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right now, there&amp;rsquo;s no strong need for the service. It makes our system more coherent. But it wouldn&amp;rsquo;t do much better than:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improved signposting&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;better content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fixing some plumbing and internal processes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An &amp;ldquo;online&amp;rdquo; service wouldn&amp;rsquo;t deliver the benefits in a sustainable way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course trust, accountability and openness with health data isn&amp;rsquo;t a thing you decide not to do. But there are more effective steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Giving people control and sight of their health records is, from what we&amp;rsquo;ve seen from people, the better first step.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Week 06</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/17/discovery-notes-06.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/17/discovery-notes-06.html</id>
    <published>2019-05-17T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-05-21T07:41:20+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Very busy week. Wake up at 4 in the morning thinking about work type of busy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some good news (eventually) on Monday. Now a &lt;em&gt;senior&lt;/em&gt; designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend asked what that means. Doing the same things I think. And helping out on a new project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We did a lot of user research as a team this week. Two pop-ups and two workshops. With a lab and a patient panel planned the week after.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Busy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s hard work making this simple&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of time spent discussing, exploring and trying to make the log of where NHS digital shares data simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Found it hard to make it simple to grasp what data has been shared, to who and why. Without adding unimportant noise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In isolation the things aren&amp;rsquo;t difficult. But the ordering and interconnected bits are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one data sharing agreement you may have your data shared as part of 40 different datasets. All to help a local area evaluate and plan services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size, shape and structure of every data sharing agreement is unique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I just don&amp;rsquo;t want people to have to know how the system works to see how the system is working for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;d also help if the content wasn&amp;rsquo;t so academic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Your job is to help the organisation make better decisions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About a year ago a team from GDS came to the digital delivery centre and I walked round with them for a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talked a little about adopting more agile ways of working within programmes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the guests asked a good question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;How are you helping the programme make better decisions?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t a question I didn&amp;rsquo;t have an answer to. But it was one of those that stuck with me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The depth to which you can answer this question is a sign of your impact as a designer or researcher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working in agile ways means you make decisions more often. You respond to change. You test things. You make change possible and at a lower cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a designer you ask questions and force decisions. But you need to be purposeful about your work and ask yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What decision is my work helping to make?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I help make that decision?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do I help make the best decision for the user and the organisation?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;re likely to get pushback when you start working like this. More so if you&amp;rsquo;re working beyond how something &amp;ldquo;looks&amp;rdquo; or how the interface works. People will challenge why a designer is caring about certain decisions or business process. But your job is to challenge thought processes and deliver value. If you&amp;rsquo;re not challenging you&amp;rsquo;re probably not designing for a better outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday we had a show and tell that I felt forced a decision and delivered the evidence to make a better choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the end we&amp;rsquo;d agreed what evidence was left to capture and what we needed to do to finalise a decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But also how to communicate that finding beyond our organisation so the whole system stops repeating the same research and finding the same thing.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Week 05</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/10/discovery-notes-04.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/10/discovery-notes-04.html</id>
    <published>2019-05-10T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-05-13T23:41:03+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Failed to make any notes for the last week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some stuff happening that made it emotionally quite exhausting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Better API&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovery wise I finally cracked the API I was exploring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Turned out I was seeing a spreadsheet that was only a summary. What someone thought was what I would be interested in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fields were right but some of the details I wanted were missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Went from “your data was part of the A&amp;amp;E dataset” to tracking exact bits of data shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a user this means we could be clearer about what identifiable stuff is shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead of “we shared details that personally identify you” we can give more context. Postcodes were shared because the study was about a specific area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looked like the API available would need lots of love. Processes might still do. But less to overhaul.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Getting stuff out of my head&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest sins you see in meetings is overeager solution designing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Is this a problem?” is often lost the second you have a solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mean, if you have a solution, course there’s a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than criticising people it’s helpful to ask questions to get back to the problem. Or take a solution as a set of assumptions or research questions to tackle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beyond meetings solutions can hang around in the mind. Particularly when trying to explore if a problem is significant or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was causing some issues for me when exploring the API. It was quite easy to think of solutions to things that aren’t needed. And take what’s possible and engineer experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of this rattled around my mind all week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Took Friday to purge some of it. Get it out on paper. Sketch some components and flows so they didn’t rattle around and get in the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the ideas and solutions are down I&amp;rsquo;m not worrying about them. They&amp;rsquo;re a bunch of assumptions and I&amp;rsquo;m taking them as material to form research questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put things to bed by getting them out of your head.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Prototyping in shorthand</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/04/writing-shorthand.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/04/writing-shorthand.html</id>
    <published>2019-05-04T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-05-09T08:34:40+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As mentioned in my last &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/03/discovery-notes-03.html"&gt;discovery notes&lt;/a&gt; I like to write up pages in a shorthand method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t something that only I do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I was helping out in services week for &amp;ldquo;formapalooza&amp;rdquo; &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Ralph_Hawkins"&gt;Ralph Hawkins&lt;/a&gt; spoke about the format he used in Google docs to write pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The format follows the shapes of interface elements using:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;dl&gt;
  &lt;div class="dl_element"&gt;
    &lt;dt&gt;Radio buttons&lt;/dt&gt;
    &lt;dd&gt;(&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;)&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="dl_element"&gt;
    &lt;dt&gt;Checkboxes&lt;/dt&gt;
    &lt;dd&gt;[&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;]&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="dl_element"&gt;
    &lt;dt&gt;Input fields&lt;/dt&gt;
    &lt;dd&gt;[&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;]&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="dl_element"&gt;
    &lt;dt&gt;Buttons&lt;/dt&gt;
    &lt;dd&gt;[ Continue ]&lt;/dd&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do this too. But I like to add a few markdown elements as well, so &lt;code&gt;#&lt;/code&gt;&amp;lsquo;s for headings. So:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="list-unstyled"&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;# Heading one&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;## Heading two&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;### Heading three&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means I like to write pages like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
# Make your choice

You need to choose what you're going to have for tea.

It's really important.

## What do you want for tea?

( ) Curry
( ) Chips and sausages
( ) Pizza

[ Continue ]

&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Write in this format or similar in a sharable doc and you’ve got a way for a whole team to work together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can even use document editor styles like links.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using shorthand makes it easy for two designers to collaborate on screens. Or for other members of the team or other teams to get involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use Google docs, word or a notes app. It’s a quick way of prototyping screens and flows. It’ll help you focus on the important bits:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the words and questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the structure and flow&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;and ultimately, if your service meets a need&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Week 04</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/03/discovery-notes-03.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/05/03/discovery-notes-03.html</id>
    <published>2019-05-03T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-05-04T22:19:07+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Met with Phil Cooke from the Data request service and data access environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked about background to some of the internal data pipeline for NHS digital. Constraints. Things to improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saw the benefits of a cross programme workshop we held before. Getting out of your part of the business is the type of thing that rewards you long after the initial reason you held a workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a couple of practical questions answered. And a name to help with digging into the API/database which logs where your data has been shared for research and why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed the opt out service development backlog. We have four tickets left (!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed the prototype from Friday. Few things to glue together. On reflection a few things to clean up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s always some rework moving from a sketch on a sticky note to another level of fidelity. And that&amp;rsquo;s fine. Things sound better in the head and worse when said. Giving things shape will always be a challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam asked for &lt;a href="https://github.com/alphagov/govuk-design-system-backlog/issues/29"&gt;examples of declarations from around government and got linked to this&lt;/a&gt;. A reminder that GitHub isn&amp;rsquo;t always obvious to search, but is a treasure trove of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed some information architecture issues with Rhiannon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrote up some notes into a presentation. Tussled with it for most of the day. Didn&amp;rsquo;t quite get the narrative right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Retro and planning with Will, Lucy and Emma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talked about what we&amp;rsquo;ve got in the next few weeks. I talked a little about getting to the heart of what makes a research study an attractive for someone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d gotten my hands on an API spec so will jump into what we log about research studies at NHS digital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More work on a presentation. Still didn&amp;rsquo;t like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chat with Jordan (grad researcher). Catch up on how he&amp;rsquo;s getting on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talked about being able to talk about why you use a method and tools. Job interviews and assessment criteria.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More tweaks on a presentation. Still didn&amp;rsquo;t like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Popped onto a call with the leadership team of the NHS website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gave the presentation. Went fine. Gave a service eye&amp;rsquo;s view of a few issues with the website. Nothing insurmountable. Everyone was very nice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked through the job descriptions with Sam. What type of things a designer needs to show. Matching it against the spec etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dialled in to the content huddle. Really glad to see the content community chatting through some issues. Was about the &lt;a href="#"&gt;care cards component&lt;/a&gt; and some questions about implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strict scenario the component should only be used in means it&amp;rsquo;s something you should set apart from the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s not a general building block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s more of a very specific solution in response to a very specific scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A solution that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re unsure works in the specific situation it handles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unsure whether every type of &amp;ldquo;get help&amp;rdquo; should be solved by the care card&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Unclear how it&amp;rsquo;ll work alongside other cards or long pages of content&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The type of thing that should be shared and discussed as a solution to a particular problem. But rolled out cautiously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pop up day in Bradford uni for the research team. 98% of those talked to would be happy to proactively share data with the NHS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of interesting things shared (Will being heckled one foot into Bradford).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One person who didn&amp;rsquo;t want to share their data but it was nothing to do with the NHS. They just didn&amp;rsquo;t trust data being shared on computers. Once it&amp;rsquo;s online or in a database it could be leaked, hacked and shared beyond purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also heard about someone who is happy to share but where they used to live they would have said no. With concerns about the weaponisation of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People told us &amp;ldquo;for training&amp;rdquo; was a good reason to share data too. Hadn&amp;rsquo;t heard that before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed the pages on the NHS digital website we want a survey. And what we wanted to ask.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam did some great work on search terms in Google analytics and Google search console.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam made a list of pages that would be good to ask questions on. We went through reviewing each page if we had specific thing to find out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shared the questions round the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We based our questions on something that really worked for us on the health records pages before. With a tweak or two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emma had a couple of questions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked through some changes to the data donor screens with Sam&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then had a debrief with Ruth and Sam about the pop-up the day before which lasted most of the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunch then reviewing our work. More prototyping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mainly in shared docs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re using a shared doc to write the screens in shorthand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;
( ) For radio buttons

[ ] For checkboxes

[           ] Input fields

[ Buttons ]

Etc.
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t new. I&amp;rsquo;ve been writing notes to myself in a mixture of shorthand and markdown on my mobile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we agreed it works for us working together. In that space between sketch and full screen or prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Went over earlier to BWP so Sam could get the NHS app environments set up on her laptop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good huddle reviewing some work on eRS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nothing will make your work better faster than sharing your work in the open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;ll hurt at times. But do it early and often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if someone asks for your help listen to the constraints. Context. And give them the fruit of all the hard work you&amp;rsquo;ve done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seeing and critiquing other people&amp;rsquo;s work will make you better. You&amp;rsquo;ll see things that&amp;rsquo;ll work for you. And spot issues you have too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always try and make Friday a chatty day. Answer emails. Respond to questions. Post questions. Raise issues or fixes on GitHub.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today was no exception. Wrote up some documentation too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Answered some development issues and dug into why some CSS was working on the prototype but not a build environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrote a few sketches up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed Sam&amp;rsquo;s work on the prototype. Helped her stitch a few things together and taught her about JavaScript objects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rhiannon noticed a couple of things so fixed them in the opt out prototype. Chatted about a question from Ruth. She&amp;rsquo;s going to dig into the data and see what&amp;rsquo;s what.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Week 03</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/04/26/discovery-notes-03.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2019/04/26/discovery-notes-03.html</id>
    <published>2019-04-26T08:30:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2019-04-29T19:49:55+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slow day. Other things to sort beyond work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed the new end of service feedback questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrote up some thoughts on a few issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Agreed to do a talk about GDS assessment to the graduate BA community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the morning was a resetting exercise following the workshop the week before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be tough to get talking about data with people. It&amp;rsquo;s abstract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So we&amp;rsquo;re prototyping to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discovery so far has been slower than hoped. Some of that&amp;rsquo;s due to changes based on feedback from a lab and workshop. Some of it other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught up with a graduate researcher to see how he was going on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spent the time before and after lunch mapping out an exploratory service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re going to explore attitudes to data with a data donor service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the provocative questions  underlining the prototype was:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;d be happy if you or your loved one benefited from medical research, so would you be happy to donate your data to help this?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re exploring:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;how happy people are to share data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what changes if they data is donated&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what happens when people look at matching data with projects that would like it to be shared with. And those they wouldn&amp;rsquo;t&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what people need to know to understand research studies and make a decision about them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what we&amp;rsquo;d need to show to give people a sense of positive feeling about donating&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;what people would want in a way or a happy ending&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrote a presentation about 5 lessons from doing GDS assessments. For the huddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Couple of issues here or there. Mostly spent time sketching a flow with Sam in response to the service we mapped out the day before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed some work of Rhiannon&amp;rsquo;s. Asked for her decision on what of the three options was her preferred thing to take forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did some annual review meetings. Always important for people to know what they&amp;rsquo;re responsible for. What good looks like and what&amp;rsquo;s important to achieve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back on sketching out the basic flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then to the huddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Didn&amp;rsquo;t end up giving my GDS presentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked about how we document designs and design decisions. Then an interesting issue from Ben Cullimore about highlighting that the NHS website medicines A to Z may not include every medicine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prototyping prototyping prototyping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Divided up the work with Sam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked to Ben about benefit realisation and OKRs (objectives and key results).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Joined in a discussion on slack about documenting design decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poked Mat Johnson to share his tweet in slack as well as the twitters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-dnt="true"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Utterly &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/lazyweb?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#lazyweb&lt;/a&gt; - &lt;em&gt;swiftly and simply&lt;/em&gt; documenting and recording design decisions to create a usable record. What do you do? Any good posts I should look at?&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Mat Johnson (@demotive) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/demotive/status/1121335669958246400?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;April 25, 2019&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt; &lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;70 comments later I think it was a good thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s key to split up what it is you&amp;rsquo;re trying to document:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How things act and look (now, should)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Changes to designs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reasons for decisions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are overlapping things but to me do have differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A reason for a change doesn&amp;rsquo;t need the whole service to be mapped out and every potential change shown.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But for a team meeting or planning session it might.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have to find a consistent, efficient way to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My design team, &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2017/12/10/hypothesis-driven-design.html"&gt;we do hypothesis driven design&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal being to log why we&amp;rsquo;re making certain changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to put all hypotheses in the prototype. And some colleagues said it was useful. But watching them read it it was the major one or two before entry into a prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It also got quite laborious to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the opt-out service I&amp;rsquo;ve created hundreds of prototypes. Documenting all things on our Jira board and the prototype become tedious and inefficient.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re writing lots of text in a prototype, you&amp;rsquo;re better off with a CMS or word document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within corporate environments there comes the question of shareability. If that document goes to confluence or SharePoint it might as well be buried in the garden.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, a prototype with a password and one designer to update it doesn&amp;rsquo;t sound like a great sharing mechanism either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, you have to find your way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the way forward isn&amp;rsquo;t doing nothing. Complicated systems need documenting. Teams need help being kept on the same page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2018/01/08/kanban_for_interaction_design.html"&gt;Document your work as you go&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2017/12/10/hypothesis-driven-design.html"&gt;Write hypotheses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make it easy to understand your work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make it easy to have a discussion about your work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
