<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Andrew Duckworth</title>
  <subtitle>Designer, artist</subtitle>
  <id>https://grillopress.github.io/</id>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2023-11-19T15:05:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Reduce the time it takes to test to keep your designs simple</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/19/reduce-the-time-it-takes-to-test.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/19/reduce-the-time-it-takes-to-test.html</id>
    <published>2023-11-19T15:05:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-11-21T15:28:02+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was talking to an ex-colleague and friend about some work. Talking through some issues we’d both seen in different places and times. One that stood out was how the length of time a designer has before they can test something works makes their work more complicated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the heart of any good design process is making sure things work with users. Not to confirm but to prove things work. And if they don’t get the evidence to do more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather than use the most complicated  thing first. The key is to try the simplest thing to build and get going. That way if you don’t need to build on more things, you don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key of course is actually doing this with users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But you don’t always get the luxury of regular access to users. Or usability sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir left fig-left fig-left-gutter" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/next research is too late.jpeg" alt="Artwork. 3 people looking at calendars looking bored or confused - By Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;ldquo;If your next research session isn’t for months. You’re carrying a lot of risk.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the situation my colleague found themselves in. They saw that teams members were overthinking their designs because they had so much time between usability sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And it’s sort of no surprise. The more time you have, and the fewer opportunities to find things out with users, the more you need your design to win first time. To hit all the right notes. But what this does is mean you overcomplicate a design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You add all the bells and whistles. You make everything flash red. To get your design past the usability session. But even in the best case scenario things work. You’ll not know if something simpler worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve gone through with something complex. It’s hard to scale back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the issues of not testing with users regularly as a design team. You give yourself too much time to overthink things. To worry through each issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you’ve ever done any extensive user research. You’ll know that often the thing you worry about is not the thing that makes people stumble.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So you’ll jam in things that were never needed. And you might even design the usability session is such a way that the real question is never asked. And you don’t learn about the thing that means the whole service will fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="stretch-container"&gt;
    &lt;figure class="noir" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
            &lt;img src="/images/click the button.jpg" alt="Picture of a mobile with lots of arrows on a screen pointint to a button with a speech bubble next to it of the researcher saying 'Where would you click?'"/&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;
            &amp;ldquo;But it worked in testing!&amp;rdquo;
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is to do usability more often. Particularly if you’re a product team. If you’re updating things and you have hundreds of thousands of users you have no excuse for several months between usability sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Put this in place. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst putting that regular cycle of user research in place, run “critiques” and sessions with people who know little to nothing about your product. Be they other designers, staff, friends and family. Just to get some signals. Just to get fresh eyes seeing things. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do this to keep your design simple. Keep it crude. And learn as fast as possible if simple works. Simple often works. And only needs some small tweaks to work. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course there’s probably a “Goldilocks zone”. Where you’re testing too often to reflect and think things through. But it’s better to be in that situation and calm things down than being months and months apart from reality. Never mind factoring in that a prototype isn’t the real thing. And there’s always more to learn from making things live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your next research session isn’t for months. You’re carrying a lot of risk. And making it worse for your designers and product teams as they’ll overthink. Overthinking leads to more complex designs that might work but at a higher cost to build, maintain and change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s always easier to add than take away.  Reduce the time you test your designs to keep your designs simple.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why you made a bigger impact as a smaller design team</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/18/why-you-made-a-bigger-impact-as-a-smaller-design-team.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/18/why-you-made-a-bigger-impact-as-a-smaller-design-team.html</id>
    <published>2023-11-18T13:22:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T18:45:31+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently read a blog post by Katherine Wastell about &lt;a href="https://www.katherinewastell.com/blog/2023/11/17/the-phases-of-establishing-design"&gt;the phases of establishing design&lt;/a&gt;. I like giving names to things. As it makes it possible to think and discuss about what to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In it there was a funnel visualisation of the impact teams have and it grew as you moved through the phases of design. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It got me thinking however, that as we scale up the size of design teams in organisations, the actual impact of design doesn’t always follow that idealistic path. That is, many times once we start to scale up design we actually become too inwardly focused and make less impact per person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A small design team or community is often more impactful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re less focused on internally and self-serving/healing patterns and processes and more about looking out and doing things and getting mucked in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s less people to manage. Grow and check on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s more lines of communication in big teams. And places to hide, disappear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And there&amp;rsquo;s more people who may want to pull in different directions. From design components and patterns to whole ways of working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, as you grow you’ve got new pains and problems to deal with. Job descriptions. Specialisms. Communications challenges. You have to shift people around to where the money is and maybe not to where the impact is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir right fig-right fig-right-gutter" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/through the looking glass glassing through the look.jpeg" alt="Artwork. Man looking at glass which distorts himself - By Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;ldquo;Be conscious of it. That cycle of inward and outward focus.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens over time is the team also embodies this. It becomes inwardly facing and focused and stops looking out and partnering with the rest of the teams to get things done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been in countless leadership and lead design meetings where the only thing happening is some navel gazing and frustration. Where the question of “how do we make a positive impact?” has ceased to be asked in one shape or form. And it&amp;rsquo;s mostly about recruitment or retention but not action on either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing is. It’s quite clear why you fall into this trap. As you deliver you optimise for impact and don’t put the things in place to keep the community or team healthy. Things start to break. People will leave or get frustrated at a lack of promotion or clarity or the weight of bureaucracy or similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a switch is made to focus inwardly. But you start losing the focus to really make an impact beyond design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be quite damaging to design as a function within a company. You hear “there’s more of you but you make less of an impact”. And however much you hate to agree we’ve probably all seen that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be conscious of it. That cycle of inward and outward focus. Making sure we hold ourselves and our teams to account to making an impact. Of looking out there and to making an impact and improving things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have solid “business partnering” process. That is, have a process where you have people support other people meet their goals. This can be through small things like &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/13/design-critiques-and-feedback-as-a-service.html"&gt;letting teams experience design&lt;/a&gt;. Or it can be specific people who ensure your designers and teams are adding value to the most impactful areas of the business. Typically this is the product or engineering department or an impactful programme of work. So have designers who collaborate with the leaders of those teams to see how and where design can help. With the ability to quickly help solve some of the other departments major problems or issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Treat internal issues and &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2018/09/29/treat-your-design-process-like-a-design-process.html"&gt;processes like design problems&lt;/a&gt;. Keep them small, iterate and use small prototypes to find the right thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure you’re focused and clear that adding value to your users and other teams is what’s important. And that your most talented and skilled people continue to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="stretch-container"&gt;
    &lt;figure class="noir" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
        &lt;a href="/images/Impact framework.jpg" target="_blank"&gt;
            &lt;img src="/images/Impact framework.jpg" alt="Change framework for making an impact. Asks several questions to navigate a user to understanding how they might make an impact. Starts with who are the key partners. Who within those teams you can reach. How you'll reach them. What benefits short and long term we and they can get by working together. And then what we could do. Underneath the last 3 section is space for assumptions and who will do the work - By Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;
        &lt;/a&gt;
        &lt;figcaption&gt;
            Use things like this &lt;a href="/images/Impact framework.jpg" target="_blank"&gt;change framework&lt;/a&gt; to show how you could work with others
        &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure you claim your part and your team’s part in successes. Do not be shy to build the story of your impact. Even if it is shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t just burden your most experienced doers to run the community. Or to create the internal processes. Spread that out and even hire people to do those things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But whatever you choose to do. Think about the strengths of those smaller teams making an impact. They:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hunt for opportunities to add value&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get on with designing things&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look to collaborate and grow influence beyond their own profession or skillset&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And ensure your teams and functions keep doing those things and those things are still cherished and rewarded. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve lost count of the number of places that promote their best designers and then burden them with internal facing problems. Regardless of whether they’re suited to them. Or if the organisation cares about that stuff. And then lose momentum in showing the impact design can make.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Being clear about the shifts you need to make to get people to buy or use your service</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/16/clear-about-the-shifts.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/16/clear-about-the-shifts.html</id>
    <published>2023-11-16T12:39:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T14:51:45+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;When trying to get users for your service it&amp;rsquo;s helpful to outline the stages of interest people go through. And what strategies you might want to use to meet their needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This applies whether you’re selling a thing. Creating a health service. Or building a service the user must legally complete under certain conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I use a quick framework to help guide me. To help myself and my team be clear about the shifts we need to make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking about how users start your service, or buy your product, you’ll find the following stages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="table-container"&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
    &lt;caption&gt;User stages of interest&lt;/caption&gt;
    &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;th scope="col"&gt;Type&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th scope="col"&gt;Interest level&lt;/th&gt;
        &lt;th scope="col"&gt;Example&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/thead&gt;
    &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Actively looking for a/the service to meet a need&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Proactive interest&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Someone looking for new shoes, person looking for a doctors phone number etc.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Open to a/the service to meet a need&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Inactive interest&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Someone who knows they need new shoes but feeling busy or not looking right now, Someone who knows they need to do something about a health issue but not sure what or if something exists so do nothing&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Not thinking about a/the service to meet a need&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Inactive disinterest&lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Someone who think their shoes are fine and not thinking about them, Someone who thinks the health problem is just age or something that’ll be fine in time&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Don’t think a/the service would meet their need &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Proactive disinterest &lt;/td&gt;
        &lt;td&gt;Someone who is thinking / conscious of new shoes or alternatives but doesn’t want them, Someone who knows a new model of car exists but doesn’t want it, Someone who thinks a health service would be a waste of time for them&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Successfully selling things is about making it as easy as possible for those actively looking. Or to stand out as the best option for those people. And then trying to shift the inactive people into some activity. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those with inactive interest, it&amp;rsquo;s about showing the possibility of your product to improve things. To answer their need. That it is possible to do THAT thing. Or solve THAT issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those with inactive disinterest, it&amp;rsquo;s about getting them to pay attention and answer a question. Are you sure this isn’t for you? Don’t you need this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For proactive disinterest. That can sound like a terrible place. But you’ve got people’s notice. Maybe your service isn’t for them. But it’s a chance to do something. It’s harder to shift their perceptions because they come with some. But understanding those people means you can tailor your service to respond to what they currently think your service lacks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir right fig-right fig-right-gutter" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/all the people all the places.jpeg" alt="Artwork. Many people in blue. Searching looking for things. Looking for all the people and places amongst mountains of sticky notes - By Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;ldquo;Ask yourself. Do we need to reach people or convert those we&amp;rsquo;ve reached?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s nothing harder for services than the unengaged. The people we find hard to reach. To influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many urgent and emergency health services you find a lot of proactive disinterest. That is. People who very consciously don’t think a service will meet their needs. Many examples in health are because they don’t want to go to hospital. So they’ll look for other services to meet their need if possible. Or try and do nothing at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In South East London, a team I worked with found that to be true of a lot of their patients for their “virtual ward” offer. They had a lot of patients who were in a thin line between seriously ill enough for hospital care, but safe enough and insistent enough that they didn’t want hospital. Traditionally the patient would be cajoled into hospital. Or worse left at risk in the community or with family. But with a “virtual ward” approach they could be given the care they’d expect in hospital. With the access to drugs, diagnostics and consultant care, but in the comfort of their own home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This service now had something they could offer. To nudge those with proactive disinterest in going to getting the care from hospital. Something in the middle. And once care started. If things were really unsafe at homes a relationship had started. And patients were much more willing to talk their options through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But not everything has to be as involved as reinventing your service. Sometimes it’s the slow drip work of making obvious that &amp;ldquo;people like you become their best self with THIS&amp;rdquo;. Getting your main proposition out there. And if that doesn’t work, working out from the actively disinterested what it is that your service is lacking. Be it clarity or specific things you can offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who are actively looking or considering things also have different modes or ways they search for information too. There&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://boxesandarrows.com/four-modes-of-seeking-information-and-how-to-design-for-them/" target="_blank"&gt;an interesting model here by Donna Spencer about those seeking modes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re mapping out how your service or product works. Make sure to visualise the routes to using your service from these states. How are you helping shift people to meet their needs using your service? What are your tactics?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a 2by2 grid can be useful. Use it to write in the tactics or solutions you have for shifting people. Do this as a team. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="stretch-container"&gt;
    &lt;img style="border: 1px solid black;" src="/images/interest activity 2by2 grid.jpg" alt="2 by 2 grid with one side having interest, the other activity with arrows between to highlight where the shifts to be made are"/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A format like this will make it easier to talk about but also show you where you might be lacking. It can be easy to over optimise for people to buy. But your problem might be that you’re not getting people interested first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You find this in government a lot. Where most of the work is making the service easy to use. With little work on how we get people to know about the thing in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself. Do we need to reach people or convert those we&amp;rsquo;ve reached?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s also worth noting that the time people spend in these phases isn&amp;rsquo;t equal. The length of time someone will stomach actively looking but finding nothing is not long. And differs on the level of importance to them. People will rarely stay active for long. So you have to be quick there to get the sale or convert a disbeliever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People also get things wrong. And a potential user whose tried something and failed will very quickly think your service can&amp;rsquo;t exist. Or is a load of rubbish.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you may have very different users or types of people either starting or referring people to your service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But whether you’re trying to sell something, offering a health or government service, make sure to understand the phases your potential users go through. And map out how well your service meets those phases. And the things you could change to shift people to meet their needs using your product or service.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Growing design by letting teams experience it</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/13/design-critiques-and-feedback-as-a-service.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/13/design-critiques-and-feedback-as-a-service.html</id>
    <published>2023-11-13T08:47:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-11-18T14:26:27+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Whilst I was writing up &lt;a href="/2023/10/27/why-we-design-forms.html"&gt;why designers design forms&lt;/a&gt; I started thinking about the times I&amp;rsquo;ve worked in large organisations to convince people about design. The time I&amp;rsquo;ve spent making it easier for teams to learn about design. And the process of it and how to use designers to make things better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re in any sort of government or enterprise organisation there&amp;rsquo;s a good chance there are some designers. Some &amp;ldquo;UX&amp;rdquo; types somewhere. And some enthusiasts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most convincing and impactful things I found was showing (and not telling) the value of design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, not going around and doing a presentation about a particular design practice and telling people to respect it. But making it and the value it brings to life for people by doing it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/sharing the good word.jpg" alt="Cartoon. A duck standing in front of a presentation saying 'hire more of us'. The presentation slide says 'everything you do is stupid and what I do is smart' - by Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t do this. Don&amp;rsquo;t be that person when trying to convince people that they need your profession&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saving the face of a director in a pinch. Making something better. Making things more efficient in a crisis. I&amp;rsquo;ve used lots of those moments to &lt;a href="/2021/03/19/win-space-to-design.html"&gt;win the space to do design&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about teams and services that don’t have much budget? Or still don’t believe a thing you’re selling?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t always get to put designers and people in the spots that most need design. But you get to create powerful communities of practice and sharing. Often because it’s damn hard to make change happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I worked in a local hospital. There was no UX team. Only people who cared about doing things right. Or making interfaces. A blend of UX, UI and frontend people. As well as patient advocates and quality improvement people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We built a semi-structured community. A group of people who helped each other. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I worked at NHS Digital I helped look after our design community. Growing and sustaining it so it could support any team with advice and guidance. And when I led design in UKHSA, I helped support the UCD team rethink it’s content design community meetups. Particularly in the light of much smaller numbers of designers post-covid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As well as help grow and nuture the designers. These communities are also great places to show and share the value of design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you can do it by running design reviews almost as a service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this I mean opening up regular time as a profession or group of designers and researchers where you allow teams to share their work and you give them your feedback. On things to improve now to what to do next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But instead of just doing it between designers. Letting teams come with their products and ideas and supporting them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be in the same community space or activities. For example, ensuring the community events have some regular space for other people to rock up. Or it could be in dedicated times to open things up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At NHS Digital the data team did this with people working on data visualisation and it was a way of support teams beyond those the team could directly work with day to day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of this to design within an organisation is it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;helps grow experience and understanding of design&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;makes some things better than they would have been&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;gets teams to understand what to do next&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;makes the case for more permanent support&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value for your designers or design community space is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;more content / volunteers to talk and speak&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;keeps things fresh with new projects or teams arriving&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;helps people learn how to be pragmatic and less dogmatic&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lets people share the value of their experience and craft with those who need it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In UKHSA we helped a team designing things for data from labs to improve. To see the value of interaction and content design. And we helped them align their product more closely with GOV.UK standards. We did this through 2 or 3 sessions where the product and delivery team talked us through their product and needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir right fig-right fig-right-gutter" style="border: 1px solid black;"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/kandinsky-notes.jpg" alt="People walking around and sharing their ideas artwork by Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;ldquo;But doing it as a conscious way of adding value really does help grow design within your organisation. Just by letting teams experience it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if some of those people don&amp;rsquo;t directly lead to an ask for a designer. That&amp;rsquo;s a whole team of people who saw the value of it. And not in a theoretical way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s always a risk of course that though you show value you&amp;rsquo;ve made the value free. So why carve out some budget for a full-time designer?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But people who aren&amp;rsquo;t going to give you money aren&amp;rsquo;t gonna do it anyway. You&amp;rsquo;ve made something better. And you get to tell that story to everyone. And you can be clear on how often a team can ask for support if capacity is a worry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve lost count of the times I&amp;rsquo;ve jumped onto a project. Shown the value of design. And won the space for myself or others to do more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Design community support is a great way to move people through their journey to trusting and learning how to use design. It&amp;rsquo;ll help you get people past awareness. And in places that design doesn&amp;rsquo;t always get to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it won&amp;rsquo;t just happen. You&amp;rsquo;ll have to get out there and offer the opportunity. And create the space to it. But doing it as a conscious way of adding value really does help grow design within your organisation. Just by letting teams experience it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Do the design digging</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/08/do-the-design-digging.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/08/do-the-design-digging.html</id>
    <published>2023-11-08T14:53:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-11-08T17:33:10+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently been chatting with a former colleague and friend who is now working on a product I used to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They shared some of the challenges the team was working through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was interesting was that some of challenges were things we’d worked through way back in 2019. Classic sort of “know your API and data” type issues every good interaction or UX designer learns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things that meant you have to make sure your designs are &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/12/05/design-for-real-data.html"&gt;based on real data&lt;/a&gt;. The screaming capitals style of real data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What was interesting was that there wasn’t an active part of the team telling and teaching what we’d found out in 2019.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those lessons were no longer being carried across. And where we’d documented things, those lessons have been archived and no longer being used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are times when an outside perspective is useful. To ask questions like “why does this api work like that?”. But a good team should be carrying forward that information and stories. Even between and after suppliers or other teams come and go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because something didn’t work before, or there were limitations, doesn’t mean things can’t change. When looking at data and past decisions, you get to rethink or challenge things for the future. To tell the next chapter of how things work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But when the stories are no longer told, we waste money and time learning what we could have already known. Our research and design doesn’t get past the “so what?”. Or it does a lot later than it could have done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s no replacement for learning by doing. But it&amp;rsquo;s much more fun and valuable to learn new things. Rather than repeating the battles and lessons of the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A research and design team that forgets or fails to dig around what’s been learnt before is doomed to repeat the learnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we avoid this? A good design process starts by digging around and learning what’s been learnt before. And what’s been done. In the enthusiasm for change or design it can be easily forgotten. Every designer has done this. And will do it again no doubt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But reach out to those before. Or those who’ve done similar. Particularly on a product or service with many dependencies and history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make it easy to record and share your thinking. Make it easy to find your thinking. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make those that decide things aware that when they archive or remove the lessons and learning of the past they’ll be paying to repeat many of them in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you can influence how teams are put together. Make sure your team blends those that stick around and those that leave. Be they contractors, suppliers etc. Make sure you keep a thread.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But most of all. Do the design digging before you repeat the broken designs of the past.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/in the hot sun.jpeg" alt="People digging in the ruins and under the hot sun to find out what has happened artwork by Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Experience-threat modelling</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/10/29/experience-threat-modelling.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/10/29/experience-threat-modelling.html</id>
    <published>2023-10-29T13:36:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-11-02T18:24:24+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few years ago I was deep in the midst of working on covid-19 services. Of the major changing waves and pressures on the team I remember a period with an extreme focus on security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pace of delivery had dropped. It was still very high but there was a sudden change in atmosphere and shift from some new security people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the tasks the new security people wanted to do was a &amp;ldquo;threat modelling exercise&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seemed interesting. Threat modelling is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A structured approach of identifying and prioritizing potential threats to a system, and determining the value that potential mitigations would have in reducing or neutralizing those threats&amp;rdquo;
- &lt;a href="https://cheatsheetseries.owasp.org/cheatsheets/Threat_Modeling_Cheat_Sheet.html"&gt;OWASP Threat modelling Cheat Sheet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A team looks at the system/service they’re creating and thinks about all the ways it could be exploited or abused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s part “heuristic review”. Which is sort of an expert review by common rules or experience of the reviewers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="right noir fig-right"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/lots of people.jpeg" alt="Lots of small sticky notes and people in boxes artwork by Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;ldquo;Done right, it’s also a way of creating a narrative about highlighting the potential risks in poor experience. And the areas where mitigation and change is needed.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a user experience view, this interested me. There are lots of potential abuses of a service. As well as threats to a service. Security is one of those. But poor experience can do as much damage. Especially in clinical systems. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if that seems a stretch, I know of a hospital where the way date of birth was shown was directly responsible for a chain of events that led to a death of a mother in birth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of potential threats to your service. From malicious actors to accidents and mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scenario based workshop got me thinking of all the things that could impact a user’s experience. And importantly, how sustainable and useful the service would be to run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Done right, it’s also a way of creating a narrative about highlighting the potential risks in poor experience. And the areas where mitigation and change is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can also help pinpoint things to get further user research and insight into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Running an experience modelling exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m still playing with the right process. But here is what I’ve done so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Prep&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get/Create a journey map or service map [journey + actors and systems underneath the journey to the user]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the people providing the service&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the people using the service&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the people who impact/influence those using the service [partners, kids, colleagues etc.]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a list of people to involve in the review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/service blueprint.png" alt="A service blueprint with lots of comments and notes on it"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Any size or shape of a service blueprint or similar can do. Make it something people can follow along&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Workshop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get members of the team together to run through steps and scenarios in a workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“subject matter experts”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;people involved in running the service&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;people who have designed similar services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;people with tech skills. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;people without them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;people from policy or governance teams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For health services you will want clinicians too. You can also get people who use your services. In the NHS there are many ways of reaching patient representatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decide the scope of the service you want to include. If it&amp;rsquo;s a change, you may want to focus on that journey more. But be careful to make sure it sits within a realistic context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your service is live. Do some groundwork to get data. Insights and visualise them alongside your journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the workshop:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brief them about the goal. Unearthing the potential or known issues and outcomes of things going bad at each step.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walk them through a section of the service. If a large team, split into smaller groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get individuals to create notes on the potential ways a user could misunderstand, misuse or get each step wrong. If split into small groups, get the smaller groups to discuss and create more risks as a group.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Return to the room and walk through the steps articulating the risks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rank the risks by likelihood and potential impact as a group. Voting if needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Move to the next section of the service. Rinse repeat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you’ve done either the part you want to cover, or the full service. You’ll now have a list of potential issues per step and the guessed likelihood and impact of those risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have time you can then work out what to do next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Deciding what to do next&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you and the team struggled to represent your users. Do more research. Or involve them in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you got lots of risks. And you feel the process was realistic. The next thing to do is to choose what to do with the risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, whether to resolve, reduce, mitigate or accept a risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this I mean:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resolve risk&lt;/strong&gt; - Resolve a risk by removing the possibility entirely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reduce risk&lt;/strong&gt; - Take steps to reduce the likelihood of something bad happening&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mitigate damage&lt;/strong&gt; - Take steps to reduce the potential damage in a step&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accept risk&lt;/strong&gt; - Accept it’s unlikely or impossible to stop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example could be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resolve risk:&lt;/strong&gt;  don’t ask or save sensitive data so it can be leaked&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reduce risk:&lt;/strong&gt;  ask for two factor verification, or check against a database so it’s less likely that someone can access information they shouldn’t &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mitigate damage:&lt;/strong&gt;  only display partial information. Like half a postcode. This way if it leaks the damage is limited &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accept risk:&lt;/strong&gt;  Data is already public knowledge so don’t protect it. Or maybe a product replicates what’s happening in another product so accept this service would act in the same way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing this step helps make clear what you can do. And ranking the likelihood and impact helps frame whether to invest in solutions that resolve risks. Or when to accept or reduce risk too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you do it with teams like security or clinical you can save yourself weeks and week of back and forth. And lots of misconceptions of each other&amp;rsquo;s perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re able to get teams like security involved in wider experience issues, you also get a good balance. Because risks are in context of journeys and likelihood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did this process with some clinicians and data folk for an elective care service. They wanted specific data items that would have been impossible for the users to know. Using the scenario approach, we could show them the burden it would create. And that they would stop any hospital staff from wanting to use the service. Which would be a bigger risk than the nice to have data items.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
