<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2018-07-06T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 11</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/07/06/weeknotes-11.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/07/06/weeknotes-11.html</id>
    <published>2018-07-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-07-09T12:04:13+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Skipped Weeknotes 10. The arrival of Evelyn Ada Duckworth over that weekend meant those notes didn’t get turned into a blog post. Written but not published.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First day back from paternity leave. Working from home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sent an email to the programme team with some context about the birth etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Appreciate the environment and warm response from everyone in NHS Digital. Makes it easier to come back as well as plan some more time with my family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrote up some stuff for my personal development review. Found it tough going. Took inspiration from Matt Edgar and put in some tweets about my work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Took some time to go through some emails and prioritise work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arranged meetings through the week to catch up on work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Medical appointment for myself at lunch. A very painful one but sorting a long-term issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked through the user research show and tell I missed as well as accessibility review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed the new designer job descriptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked from home again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrote up some more personal review stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spent some time working on a new prototype content architecture for my service. We have hit a point where we need to expand what we point people to. As new needs emerge and services are developed, we need to be able to easily scale the site&amp;rsquo;s structure to handle this. Right now, we are hitting the natural scaling limit of the pattern we are using.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Went through a couple of stories on Jira and cleaned them up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Created a new interaction flow for a potential service integration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First day back in the office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cleaned up an issue on Jira for the development team. Got a lovely card and gift from the Thunderbird team. Really appreciated it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Checked up on the status of a ticket that really improves the user journey of our service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught up with the product manager for Thunderbird. She&amp;rsquo;s now in control for the two programme projects. Had a good catch up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arranged with a colleague to do a “hypothesis backlog generation” session. He had worked on the service before and we’re going to run a session we did when I arrived. Blog post coming soon!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked through with a colleague some page navigation work. Shared research and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cleaned up a developer point on a ticket.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Met up with the service owner and programme manager. We talked roadmap, future integrations and design work. They mentioned how much they needed me in the next few months which was nice to hear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught up quickly with the user research team. Quick word before the lab on Thursday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jumped into a call with the delivery manager for the NHS app. Arranged to meet up with the design and research team in the next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked through links and downloads with a colleague tasked to explore those issues. Shared some scenarios and ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NHS 70th birthday. Tweeted about my little service Easter egg.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Happy birthday NHS! My little Easter egg for today was making my service&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;date of birth&amp;rdquo; helper text the same as the NHS &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/nhs70?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;#nhs70&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://t.co/KZEbEQLVcE"&gt;pic.twitter.com/KZEbEQLVcE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Andrew Duckworth (@AndrewDuck_) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AndrewDuck_/status/1014764183555100675?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;July 5, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early start with a usability lab. The lab focused on mobile users and digging behind some numbers. The hypothesis was that many of our users preferred not to start the transaction on mobile. We wanted to see if that was true, and if so, why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also wanted to evidence if the service was easy to use on mobile. And that we weren&amp;rsquo;t the cause of people avoiding using mobile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some things we saw in the lab:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People really love the NHS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most people are willing to trade off personal data for the greater good&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Giving people a sense of control, even if they don&amp;rsquo;t choose to use it, influences people&amp;rsquo;s willingness to share data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Making authentication straightforward, clear and obvious increases people&amp;rsquo;s confidence in an organisation&amp;rsquo;s ability to handle sensitive data&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Service comprehension remains high&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having a dropdown/reveal near the service start green button caused a little confusion on mobile. Proximity appeared to cause more issues on mobile&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many of our users just prefer their laptops over mobiles&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon I walked over to the design huddle. Ben talked us through some of his research on icons. It was a great talk. Ben is one of my favourite people at NHS Digital. His talk was great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Late on remembered to share some data with a colleague. Couple of heatmaps showing how people ignore thumbnails on download pages. People prefer links. People just don&amp;rsquo;t click or hover over thumbnails.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of a thumbnail is in creating a pool of focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shorter work day due to my longer Thursday. Meetings most of the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quick update with the developer team and then lots of chats. Talked to the NHSUK redesign team about folding in work. Lots of stuff to do here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chatted to Ben about hub pages and differing styles of navigation. The key being consistent but also mixing things up when the need arrises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s very easy as a designer, with the whole website in your head, to over-value uniformity. Users don&amp;rsquo;t notice small differences. They notice if what they want to do is hard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught up with Matt (Head of Design). Chatted about my service and how it is going since live. Family. And how to make your siblings like you (by peeing up walls as an infant).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Things are different in live</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/06/26/things-are-different-in-live.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/06/26/things-are-different-in-live.html</id>
    <published>2018-06-26T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-07-10T14:07:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In May I had the privilege of hearing about the great work done by the NHS Business Services Authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the talk the team mentioned a particular question that encountered a lot of distrust during testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked if they’d seen the same since going public. They hadn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This matched a recent experience with research into the National Data Opt-out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We had a few issues that when under the magnifying glass of user labs, got an increased emphasis. Emphasis we didn’t see since going public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t to say everything has been like this. The things people liked in labs, they liked in the public service. And the things that annoyed them (and us) in labs, annoyed them since going public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a strength of user labs that they let you solve the issues that stop people from using your service. And you find speed bumps and things that lead people astray.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But they won’t iron out every issue. They also don’t reflect going public either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing we found performing better has been our “interruption card” component.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have a screen that acts as the sinew between the landing page and transactional service. This page lays out how to do the thing online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea behind it was to clear up the process of one-time authentication that’s needed. We found in Alpha that we had a sizeable user group that hadn’t done two-factor authentication before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the lab, these things performed okay. Some people zoomed past them. Some slowed down and got the info they needed to understand the journey they were about to take.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not a ringing endorsement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the issue was most users were happy to share their data with the NHS for research and planning purposes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Evaluating the component became difficult. We saw some users zoom through things they may have taken more time over at home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though it didn’t stop the zoomers in the lab, it did seem to support some users. We kept it for the public service. Partially because of a hunch that on scale it would prove its worth. And also because the evidence was that it did alright.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since going public, the indications have been that it’s been working better. Tracking cursor movements has seen lots of users track and read the text on the card. User journey recordings also show it. Likewise, with user feedback on that page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Empowering users is about them understanding what they are doing. And why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The value of letting users know how to do a thing is that they understand what to expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You don’t alway need to surface process, but we’re glad we have. It stopped users questioning why we were asking for their details to stop data being shared. It stopped some users feeling out of control and unable to use the online service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll never know for sure if something works. Things are different in live.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 09</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/06/08/weeknotes-09.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/06/08/weeknotes-09.html</id>
    <published>2018-06-08T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-06-11T15:48:49+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the week by finishing off. Wrote up and shared a prototype. Demonstrating what to show users who cannot save a choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chased up human resources team on an issue for a junior designer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked with the Thunderbird Product owner, Ruth. Position on a potential service. Interesting product. But in my mind, obsolete on go live. Solving a real problem, in the wrong place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More “Making it hard work to do something simple” than “Do the hard work to make it simple”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further work on leaflets and forms. How they sit within the content strategy for the site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Little bit of chat about design roadmaps with a colleague. Made me think about method. Wrote up some notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talk with product owner about the NHS number service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrote down some stuff I had been filtering through my mind about consent. Tried to categorise some patterns of capturing consent. And some related components.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="half"&gt;
  &lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/consent/IMG_20180604_155857.jpg" alt="Sticky notes arranged on a worktop. Grouping types of consent by being implicit or explicit. As well as patterns used to inform, rather than capture consent."/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;First go. Patterns to inform. Patterns to capture consent.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class="noir"&gt;

    &lt;img src="/images/consent/IMG_20180606_141529.jpg" alt="Sticknotes arranged in groups to express how patterns are active and passive."/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Passive and active patterns. And some examples of how those things are expressed and captured.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say. Lots of clean up and work through. But better out of the mind than in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Verified cookie and analytics solution in live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked with a programme business analyst to explain some dashboards. Talked through the numbers on the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walked the same BA through a concept prototype. Explained the hypothesis behind it. Risks and costs attached.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Content strategy meeting with the programme and content designer. A good hour thrashing out the next three months. Concerns to test. Ideas to explore and things we need to have a clear answer to by October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got a massive thank you for my intervention with the last minute request before live. Feels nice to be thanked for being yourself and standing up for what you believe in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sketched up a &amp;ldquo;hypotheses mapping&amp;rdquo; process. Method to generate one. Improve it. Categorise it. And choose what to work on next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
  &lt;img src="/images/consent/IMG_20180611_151355.jpg" alt="Notebook full of writing."/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Writing to teach helps you learn. It&amp;rsquo;s how I always try to write. Always helps me find clarity.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Said farewell to a colleague going off on maternity leave. Added benefit of catching up with a colleague I hadn&amp;rsquo;t seen in a while. What he&amp;rsquo;s currently working on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught an issue with one of the live error screens. Consequence of having to de-prioritise some work before go live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weekly design huddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walked through the NHS referral service design. Future design concepts. Talked about product roadmaps. Getting good user centred design at the heart of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cheeky pint with the designers from the huddle afterwards to end the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Triaged the error screen problem and offered two solutions. Immediate fix and an ideal long-term solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quick meeting with the service owner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a meeting with the new Thunderbird product owner. Caught up on the roadmap for two potential services she will be handling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spent a little time solving an NHS number-related keyboard on mobiles issue. Got a solution working across all devices. Some issues remain. Started writing up a blog post about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Packaged up a release for the NHSUK team. Surfaced a few issues. Planned next couple of releases with the programme team.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 08</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/06/01/weeknotes-08.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/06/01/weeknotes-08.html</id>
    <published>2018-06-01T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-06-04T10:00:56+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bank holiday. Kept things pretty chilled out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the day reviewing the activity on the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a call with the programme to talk through it. Put things into place for analysis. Combed over some numbers and cautioned for no conclusions. Some numbers weren’t pretty. But we don&amp;rsquo;t have enough users through the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Made a point of getting the programme director to commit to an in-person design session. Idea being, get everyone in a room. Review data. Co-design solutions and share issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my mind, we have three current concerns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are we letting the zoomers&amp;rsquo; zoom and the readers&amp;rsquo; read?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are people able to find their NHS number?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Are people able to authenticate? (on scale)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re too early to come to a position on any of those.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a Thunderbird team retro. Talked about issues holding us back and things we did well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After retro talked a little about future issues to solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the cookie elaboration for the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elaborated a bit more on the service’s cookie solution. A solution we had intended to pursue wasn’t quite a fit this second. Had to dig through some other privacy policy stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a few questions for the landing page. Resources for professionals etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Updated to a final release of a potential service prototype. Regardless if the service is a goer, feel pretty happy with the prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;DDC UX team meeting. Our lead researcher went through how we had been using hotjar. In Alpha, Private and now public beta. Limitations and workarounds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught up with the NHS account designers afterwards. Had a good laugh about a few things. Talked about the NHS and branding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finished the day having a long catch up with Emma James. Talked through content design. Question design. Content/interaction flows and the weekly design huddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emma agreed to talk through some of the stuff she had been working on at the huddle. Announced it on the design slack channel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the day with a quick technical review for the service’s cookie banner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cleaned up some design board stuff. Dean and David volunteered to give an update on the NHSUK redesign work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had an assignment review with the service owner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught up with Jordan, a graduate user researcher I am helping career manage. Planned in a performance review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also caught up with Sam. Graduate content designer (who dabbles with some interaction design). She was prototyping some questions up. Great to see her grow in confidence. From building her first prototype on the GDS course to using the NHS kit in the NHS account team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked to Emma over slack about input validation and error messages for NHS numbers. Sharing some stuff we found out in research. Then talked about user confusion with national insurance numbers and NHS numbers. Good chat through important stuff.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Went through error messaging hypotheses. Algorithm that you can use to validate NHS numbers. We agreed that there needs to be a standard approach to NHS numbers going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrote up a quick hypotheses for when a user enters a national insurance number into the NHS number field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed my designs for a “review your answers” page. Felt unhappy with it on mobile and made a few tweaks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walked over to BWP for the design huddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a great session. Particularly enjoyed talking through interaction/content design problems as a group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Head of Design tweeted about it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Leeds designers’ huddle &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/NHSDigital?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@NHSDigital&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/DoTheWords?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@DoTheWords&lt;/a&gt; sharing a gnarly content and interaction design challenge to make it simpler for people to sign in to NHS services online &lt;a href="https://t.co/GAO74YPJkO"&gt;pic.twitter.com/GAO74YPJkO&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Matt Edgar (@mattedgar) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/mattedgar/status/1002210556290486278?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;May 31, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started Friday with a design backlog review.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Provided some personal review feedback for members of the team. For their career managers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Product backlog review with service owner. Talked through some concerns and future design work. Not tons on the horizon. Though that always seems to change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunch in the sun. Caught up with some recent ex-Thunderbird team members.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bit of design work on leaflets and forms. We have a creeping set of landing page requirements that is worrying me.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 07</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/05/25/weeknotes-07.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/05/25/weeknotes-07.html</id>
    <published>2018-05-25T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-05-29T21:49:45+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started early.  Created two prototypes. Exploring different cookie consent banners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One with a simplified yes/no choice. Another that gave users more control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shared the prototypes with the rest of the “Cookie cutters” for feedback. Rather than chuck some hypotheses and proto-personas at the group, I arranged a call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shared the “NHS number” prototype with that team as well. Got given the analytics code to add and talked through research options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After my daily standup with Thunderbird I had the research planning call. Discussed the hypotheses behind the two versions of the cookie banner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hadn’t ever worked with the researchers before. You take for granted the chemistry you have with people. But the team was great and we quickly got on the same page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked through the ideas. Shaped the research plan. Some questions were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What users thought the banner was about?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What (if anything) they thought the banner was asking them to do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How they interacted with the banner&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Did they know what cookies were?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How much did they know about GDPR?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which prototype model did they prefer? Why?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What did they understand they were agreeing to?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What they understood by &amp;ldquo;third-party&amp;rdquo; and other terms?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plan was to get people with a range of digital skills through a pop-up in a library.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The researchers, Ana and Antonia, thought testing a third prototype would help them. So I got to crafting it while they shared the updated research plan in the Cookie cutter slack group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jumped onto verifying the service for go-live. Caught an issue with the footer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started an interaction flow in Sketch for the NHS number prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Took a call with programme about cookies and analytics for the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked to a developer on the gov.uk slack about why they needed their NHS number. They’d asked in a channel where you could find it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Late in the day heard back from the researchers with the pop-up results. We got six people through. Between the two concepts, users preferred having more immediate control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users understood what was being asked of them. And had heard about &amp;ldquo;cookies&amp;rdquo;. But they felt somewhat confused over the implications of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of this issue was that I had thrown the words together. And they weren’t great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other issue was that we were exploring the need for consent to advert placement/tracking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a scenario where you are asking people a simpler question, the binary yes/no option would excel. But, we had a scenario where we had finer grained layers. And as such, people liked that to be transparent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next iteration was then to fold in what we had learnt about simplifying the language. As well as drilling further into how to let people make an informed decision.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More prototyping.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dug into the cookies we were using. How to categorise them to something that’s easy to understand and doesn’t rely on web concepts or web terms. Tried to simplify things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We shifted to terms we thought were more commonly understood. Things like “social media”. (Yes, still too vague&amp;hellip;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explored addition concepts like “just in time” consent. This was more of a proof of concept. Not something we tested immediately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finished off the NHS number service interaction flow. Added more detail on errors and loops.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got the final feedback on pop-up sessions for the latest prototypes. Progress on simplifying the concepts we are trying to get across to people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our design worked well. But we had an issue again with the language. Recent Facebook and Cambridge Analytica stories changed how people perceived a few terms. Moving in the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improved the cookie banner based on the user feedback. Packaged up the prototype for implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later in the morning met up with a colleague from London to talk navigation. Love chatting to Graham but don’t get to talk face to face much. Nice change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Met up with Ben. Took the opportunity to grab lunch. Talked through some stuff we were working on. Respecting context in interaction design amongst other things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked to Adam from the Cookie cutter crew. Caught up with the implementation of the cooke banner. He&amp;rsquo;d made great progress on two versions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Said hello to an NHS graduate I met during the GDS course. Caught up how she was. What she is moving onto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught up with Ruth the product owner for the new NHS number service. Talked through where the service could live if it is a goer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shared the wireflow kit I used to create the NHS number interaction flow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Late in the day talked to a colleague from the NHSUK CMS team. About the prototype kit I made to explore their designs. Crafted up a starter kit for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though not announced until Friday, the Thunderbird team put the service live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All things healthy and good to go. Nice moment. Particularly for a small team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Took a bit of time to go deeper into the error validation and messaging for the NHS number prototype. With a small window until MVP it’s key to explore the end to end journey. Dead-ends and things we left too late on my current service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked to a content designer colleague about help text and dropdowns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shared some stuff we found in user testing. She also suggested some stuff. Improvements for the service and new prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got sight of some of the launch day comms. It had changed quite a bit from last time. The plan was to announce the service in every national newspaper. As well as places like radio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of speakers for the weekly design meetup had had to drop out. Life got in the way. I presented on a recent issue. Had planned for the chat to end with a sketching session. But debate and discussion took us to a more strategic than interface level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Launch day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
  &lt;img src="/images/thunderbird go live.jpg" alt="Group of colleagues standing in front of a whiteboard celebrating launching a national service"/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Thunderbird team celebrating go live!&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Colleagues collected newspaper cuttings and shared where they had seen the service advertised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did a little more on error messages. This time some validation rules for the prototype and then wording on end-pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helped the Thunderbird team on a range of issues and queries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chased up on some questions I had asked. Given some content for the service but bounced it back asking for clarification.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Went for lunch with the team and later in the day some drinks. Celebrated launching a service with a small, talented and motivated team.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 06</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/05/18/weeknotes-06.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/05/18/weeknotes-06.html</id>
    <published>2018-05-18T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-05-20T17:37:20+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Delivery Centre UX team update. Caught up in a meeting beforehand so turned up a few minutes late. Always enjoy hearing what colleagues are up to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later on got a very direct design requirement. One that came with the caveat that without it, no live service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me it was a solution we had no idea of the impact of that tried to solve a problem we had little to no evidence for. Pushed back but got told in no uncertain terms it wasn&amp;rsquo;t up for negotiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knocked me for six.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crafted up some HTML for a new privacy notice for the Thunderbird team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a great discussion with the Thunderbird developers later about an API we use. A small chat with the team. Thrashing out and balancing user experience and technical possibility. A great team co-design session amongst a sea of uncertainty and confusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of those moments you feel like as a team you could conquer anything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Catch up meeting with the user research team first thing. Talking through some things that will be coming our way. Mitigating some issues going forward and planning the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got an answer back RE: cookies and stuff for the 25th. Plot thickens a little but a clearer choice forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got asked a question. In light of the requirement on Monday I felt the need to state my opinion. Without reservation. Took my time to highlight precedence and GDS standards. Squashed the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Felt empowered I must admit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saw the impact of Monday&amp;rsquo;s design requirement&amp;rsquo;s on the service when a few colleagues opened the most recent prototype. It was a little bit like watching a car crash. It was a brutal insight into the confusion the design change will have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If I thought I was losing sleep over the issue before, this really worried me. On the train home I started drafting notes on how to reverse this requirement. Or mitigate some of the confusion it was causing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the day finishing off an email highlighting my case against the requirement. Built a case. Laid out the various ways forward. And prayed the email landed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helped kickstart a small project team &amp;ldquo;cookie cutters&amp;rdquo; swarm on stuff for the 25th May and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jumped on various issues throughout the day. Lots of pivots and changes. Many unneeded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prepared the ground work for a different project prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meeting with lead researcher and product owner on new &amp;ldquo;NHS number&amp;rdquo; project. Talked about a few issues. Doing one thing per page and the central hypothesis behind the first prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walked through something I had crafted together on the train into Leeds. Benefit of having a prototyping kit where you can glue things together to test and explore ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Changed up how I built this one in response to picking through the GDS kit. Doing more of the routing stuff on the server rather than on the frontend. Will see if it makes it more flexible for me or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had to jump onto an urgent call. At the end of the call reiterated my points about the requirement I disagreed with. Laid out my position. Final decision was with the senior responsible officer (SRO) later in the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ran across to the NHS Digital design away day. Heard lots of interesting stories. Saw lots of great designs in response to many challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got to meet up with lots of friends and the cool people from NHS BSA again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Really enjoyed the guest talk from the NHS BSA team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saw a pattern throughout the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those that shared their work early and often had a maturity and coherence to their work compared to those that didn&amp;rsquo;t. It&amp;rsquo;s the key to being a good designer. It&amp;rsquo;s hard. It&amp;rsquo;s scary. But sharing your work will make it better. Particularly before you hit that &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m comfortable with this&amp;rdquo; stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to have a great chat over lunch as I had to jump onto another urgent call. Bit upset. But that&amp;rsquo;s what happens when you are launching a national service in a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a great day though. Always feel sad when the day is over. Never enough time to talk to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walk back to the train station had a good chat with a colleague or two. Issues shared. Truths told.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my train back I heard news about the hard requirement I emailed about on Wednesday was being reversed. Moment of great relief. Promised to investigate the concern that caused the requirement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can stop losing sleep over it now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also had a good chat about cookies and GDPR and what stuff needs to happen to explore the impact of that too. Plans made.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finished off the first prototype for the new &amp;ldquo;NHS Number&amp;rdquo; project. Pretty happy with it all things considered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crafted up some screens for the cookie project. Wrote up and modelled some proto-personas. Evaluated and ranked some needs. Balanced user needs, business requirements and potential clinical risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When your website visitors may be having a heart attack. Or their child is struggling to breathe you have a duty not to get things wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explored the screens against various websites and pages. Judging the solution against different styles of page. And in different scenarios.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shared preliminary stuff with the cookie cutters. Tweaked a few things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Day then went a bit south. Ended up watching my wife connected to all sorts of machines and tests. Frustrating and very long day. All fine in the end. At times it didn&amp;rsquo;t sound like it would end well.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
