<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Andrew Duckworth</title>
  <subtitle>Designer, artist</subtitle>
  <id>https://grillopress.github.io/</id>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/"/>
  <link href="https://grillopress.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2023-11-02T18:40:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Making your research and insights make an impact (course)</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/02/influencing-and-communicating-research.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/11/02/influencing-and-communicating-research.html</id>
    <published>2023-11-02T18:40:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-11-02T19:46:17+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="ticket-box ticket-box__no-outer"&gt;

&lt;img src="/images/doing the analysis cropped.png" alt="Lots of small sticky notes and people in boxes artwork by Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;

&lt;ul class="unstyled"&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;date class="date-info__full-datetime"&gt;Friday, 1 December 2023&lt;/date&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;time class="p date-info__full-datetime"&gt;10:00 - 12:30 GMT&lt;/time&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;span&gt;£200 Early bird price (£300 full price)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;!-- Noscript content for added SEO --&gt;
&lt;noscript&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/e/influencing-and-communicating-research-registration-750744837017" rel="noopener noreferrer" target="_blank"&gt;Buy Tickets on Eventbrite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/noscript&gt;
&lt;!-- You can customise this button any way you like --&gt;
&lt;button id="eventbrite-widget-modal-trigger-750744837017" type="button"&gt;Buy a ticket&lt;/button&gt;


&lt;script src="https://www.eventbrite.co.uk/static/widgets/eb_widgets.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;
    var exampleCallback = function() {
    console.log('Order complete!');
    };

    window.EBWidgets.createWidget({
    widgetType: 'checkout',
    eventId: '750744837017',
    modal: true,
    modalTriggerElementId: 'eventbrite-widget-modal-trigger-750744837017',
    onOrderComplete: exampleCallback
    });
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Course details&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Join me for a hands-on workshop where you will learn how to make your research more impactful and influential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you passionate about sharing your research findings with a wider audience? Do you want to learn how to effectively communicate your work and influence others? Struggling to make the impact you want or improve your products and services?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve written a course for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What you&amp;rsquo;ll get out of the course&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Friday 01, December 2023 10:00:00 GMT (Greenwich Mean Time), you will gain valuable insights and practical tips on how to engage with different audiences and make your research impactful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Discover the power of storytelling and learn how to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make your research and insights more impactful to your team and stakeholders&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;explore innovative ways to present complex information in a compelling manner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;expand your knowledge of ways to visually illustrate your research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;develop a storytelling style for presentations and research findings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;learn how to lead stakeholders, your team and other teams to make better services and products&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether you&amp;rsquo;re a seasoned researcher/designer or just starting out, this event will equip you with the tools you need to effectively influence and communicate your research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don&amp;rsquo;t miss out on this unique opportunity to connect with like-minded individuals, expand your network, and enhance your research communication skills. Register now to secure your spot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A ticket also gives you access to resources and optional access to whatsapp support and advice for a year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Who this is for&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is for user researchers, service designers and anyone in an insight or strategy role who either conducts, leads or needs to influence others with user insights or research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;What it&amp;rsquo;ll cover&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The course is a hands-on 2.5 hour workshop. You&amp;rsquo;ll work in a very small group through a mixture of advice and practical activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ll cover:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;understanding, plotting out, and influencing the right people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;making sure your research aligns to your team&amp;rsquo;s needs and is able to influence people&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;using models and concepts to visually explain complex concepts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;developing your sketching and visual style&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;developing your story telling skills and presentation style&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll also get to discuss your experiences and tactics and learn from others in the small group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;button id="eventbrite-widget-modal-trigger-750744837017" type="button"&gt;Buy a ticket&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want me to run a group version of this for your team or company, &lt;a href="https://forms.gle/Y9UwPcxnSazTkzLF6"&gt;let me know with using this form&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Experience-threat modelling</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/10/29/experience-threat-modelling.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/10/29/experience-threat-modelling.html</id>
    <published>2023-10-29T13:36:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2023-11-02T18:24:24+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few years ago I was deep in the midst of working on covid-19 services. Of the major changing waves and pressures on the team I remember a period with an extreme focus on security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pace of delivery had dropped. It was still very high but there was a sudden change in atmosphere and shift from some new security people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the tasks the new security people wanted to do was a &amp;ldquo;threat modelling exercise&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seemed interesting. Threat modelling is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;A structured approach of identifying and prioritizing potential threats to a system, and determining the value that potential mitigations would have in reducing or neutralizing those threats&amp;rdquo;
- &lt;a href="https://cheatsheetseries.owasp.org/cheatsheets/Threat_Modeling_Cheat_Sheet.html"&gt;OWASP Threat modelling Cheat Sheet&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A team looks at the system/service they’re creating and thinks about all the ways it could be exploited or abused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s part “heuristic review”. Which is sort of an expert review by common rules or experience of the reviewers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="right noir fig-right"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/lots of people.jpeg" alt="Lots of small sticky notes and people in boxes artwork by Andrew Duckworth"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;&amp;ldquo;Done right, it’s also a way of creating a narrative about highlighting the potential risks in poor experience. And the areas where mitigation and change is needed.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a user experience view, this interested me. There are lots of potential abuses of a service. As well as threats to a service. Security is one of those. But poor experience can do as much damage. Especially in clinical systems. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if that seems a stretch, I know of a hospital where the way date of birth was shown was directly responsible for a chain of events that led to a death of a mother in birth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are lots of potential threats to your service. From malicious actors to accidents and mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scenario based workshop got me thinking of all the things that could impact a user’s experience. And importantly, how sustainable and useful the service would be to run.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Done right, it’s also a way of creating a narrative about highlighting the potential risks in poor experience. And the areas where mitigation and change is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can also help pinpoint things to get further user research and insight into.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Running an experience modelling exercise&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m still playing with the right process. But here is what I’ve done so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Prep&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get/Create a journey map or service map [journey + actors and systems underneath the journey to the user]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the people providing the service&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the people using the service&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the people who impact/influence those using the service [partners, kids, colleagues etc.]&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a list of people to involve in the review&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/service blueprint.png" alt="A service blueprint with lots of comments and notes on it"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Any size or shape of a service blueprint or similar can do. Make it something people can follow along&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Workshop&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Get members of the team together to run through steps and scenarios in a workshop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“subject matter experts”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;people involved in running the service&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;people who have designed similar services&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;people with tech skills. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;people without them&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;people from policy or governance teams&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For health services you will want clinicians too. You can also get people who use your services. In the NHS there are many ways of reaching patient representatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Decide the scope of the service you want to include. If it&amp;rsquo;s a change, you may want to focus on that journey more. But be careful to make sure it sits within a realistic context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your service is live. Do some groundwork to get data. Insights and visualise them alongside your journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the workshop:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Brief them about the goal. Unearthing the potential or known issues and outcomes of things going bad at each step.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Walk them through a section of the service. If a large team, split into smaller groups&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get individuals to create notes on the potential ways a user could misunderstand, misuse or get each step wrong. If split into small groups, get the smaller groups to discuss and create more risks as a group.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Return to the room and walk through the steps articulating the risks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rank the risks by likelihood and potential impact as a group. Voting if needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Move to the next section of the service. Rinse repeat&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you’ve done either the part you want to cover, or the full service. You’ll now have a list of potential issues per step and the guessed likelihood and impact of those risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have time you can then work out what to do next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Deciding what to do next&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you and the team struggled to represent your users. Do more research. Or involve them in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you got lots of risks. And you feel the process was realistic. The next thing to do is to choose what to do with the risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is, whether to resolve, reduce, mitigate or accept a risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By this I mean:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resolve risk&lt;/strong&gt; - Resolve a risk by removing the possibility entirely&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reduce risk&lt;/strong&gt; - Take steps to reduce the likelihood of something bad happening&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mitigate damage&lt;/strong&gt; - Take steps to reduce the potential damage in a step&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accept risk&lt;/strong&gt; - Accept it’s unlikely or impossible to stop&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example could be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resolve risk:&lt;/strong&gt;  don’t ask or save sensitive data so it can be leaked&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reduce risk:&lt;/strong&gt;  ask for two factor verification, or check against a database so it’s less likely that someone can access information they shouldn’t &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mitigate damage:&lt;/strong&gt;  only display partial information. Like half a postcode. This way if it leaks the damage is limited &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accept risk:&lt;/strong&gt;  Data is already public knowledge so don’t protect it. Or maybe a product replicates what’s happening in another product so accept this service would act in the same way&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doing this step helps make clear what you can do. And ranking the likelihood and impact helps frame whether to invest in solutions that resolve risks. Or when to accept or reduce risk too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if you do it with teams like security or clinical you can save yourself weeks and week of back and forth. And lots of misconceptions of each other&amp;rsquo;s perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re able to get teams like security involved in wider experience issues, you also get a good balance. Because risks are in context of journeys and likelihood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did this process with some clinicians and data folk for an elective care service. They wanted specific data items that would have been impossible for the users to know. Using the scenario approach, we could show them the burden it would create. And that they would stop any hospital staff from wanting to use the service. Which would be a bigger risk than the nice to have data items.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Why designers design forms</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/10/27/why-we-design-forms.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/10/27/why-we-design-forms.html</id>
    <published>2023-10-27T13:52:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2023-10-30T18:47:23+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Cathy Dutton asked if people have &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/cathy_dutton/status/1717540981526937636"&gt;any goto presentations on why we need to design forms&lt;/a&gt;. Not the process of how you do it. More the justification for it (other than it’s fun and gives me a job!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This made me think of how I approach this. Or the battle that I can sense underneath. Which is justifying the cost of research and design and their impact. And in places where subject matter experts are &amp;ldquo;good enough&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I try to spend as little time justifying my or other people’s existence as specialists. Taking a show/watch me approach or using local examples of improvement or failure. But sometimes you’ve got to have those chats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first thought was the &lt;a href="https://articles.centercentre.com/three_hund_million_button/"&gt;300 million button&lt;/a&gt; example. Though it took me a while to find it as I swore it was about airlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tried looking on gov.uk and though I found a few. The gov.uk blogs are missing designers talking about making measurable impacts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why do we design forms? And use specialists to do it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class="h3"&gt;Designers make sure policies, products and people are as successful as they can be&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it&amp;rsquo;s hard to complete a form then policies and products fail. Or make much less money or cost lots more. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good designers make &lt;a href="https://dl.acm.org/doi/epdf/10.1145/2556288.2557265"&gt;forms better and quicker and easier to complete&lt;/a&gt;. And find ways of making improvements to processes. Like the &lt;a href="https://designnotes.blog.gov.uk/2015/09/15/make-sure-this-is-right-a-new-email-confirmation-pattern/"&gt;register to vote team&lt;/a&gt; which improved how they captured emails helping 50,000 more people use the service each month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly designers make things more profitable by looking at the small details. &lt;a href="https://scholar.google.com/scholar?hl=en&amp;amp;as_sdt=0%2C5&amp;amp;q=ux+form&amp;amp;btnG=#d=gs_qabs&amp;amp;t=1698349420840&amp;amp;u=%23p%3DBjPQ7SL3NoIJ"&gt;Ebay made an additional $500 million a year just from redesigning a button&lt;/a&gt; on their mobile website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class="h3"&gt;Bad data undermines systems and businesses. Good form design reverses this&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Forms are a key way that organisations get data and information. Be they credit card details to complete a transaction. Or an email or a newsletter sign up form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But poor data stymies and undermines systems and products. The implications of poor quality data means:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;you have less user/customer satisfaction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;increased running costs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;inefficient decision-making processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lower performance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;lowered employee job satisfaction&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.econstor.eu/bitstream/10419/188448/1/v04-i02-p168_232-1425-1-PB.pdf"&gt;This interesting paper shows the evidence for this&lt;/a&gt;. The paper also highlights that bad data can have a revenue cost of 8-12% for many companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designers work closely with data, policy and technical teams to improve the quality of data. They do this by making the processes clearer for the people filling in forms. Making it clear what is being asked of or shown to users in a form based journey. This skill means users enter in better data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class="h3"&gt;Good form design can reduce support costs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expedia found out that the number one reason customers called them was to get their travel itineraries.  Their contact centre cost them over 100 million a year. Redesigning this reduced the need for support for this issue. Calls about this dropped from 58% to 15% (according to Medallia’s “Contact Center and Digital, Better Together”). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Improving the information at the end of a process for the &lt;a href="https://designnotes.blog.gov.uk/2016/10/21/improving-the-check-your-state-pension-service-in-public-beta/"&gt;State Pension team reduced enquiries by 51%&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The government spends millions every year in this support. A form stands in the way of them telling us things. Or getting access to something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good design team makes it easier to input data. And makes the information and data forms return easier to understand and action. This leads to a reduction in calls, support and complaints.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was part of a team that redesigned some paper forms that reduced the number and complexity of calls our contact centre got. The forms were built by subject matter experts but not design/form experts. Once we worked together we made it easier for our users to use our service. And reduced the cost to support the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class="h3"&gt;Bad forms request information we should already have or don&amp;rsquo;t need. Design looks to find ways to stop this&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designers make sure we don’t ask things we already know. At times for gov a statutory duty and if not, an efficiency and a way of ensuring validated data. Designers work with teams to understand why we are asking what we’re asking. And find other &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2019/03/18/do-the-hard-work-to-make-it-inclusive.html"&gt;options with lower risks or barriers for our users&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reducing what you ask, because you already know if don&amp;rsquo;t need it, also helps people to complete forms. Formstack found that they could &lt;a href="https://www.quicksprout.com/contact-form-conversion-rate/"&gt;improve conversation rates by up to 160%&lt;/a&gt; by reducing how many things they asked for. If you ask for less because you use what you already have, you improve completion rates too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class="h3"&gt;Designers make sure our services and products meet their legal requirements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designers help ensure that &lt;a href="https://blog.navapbc.com/structuring-a-complex-eligibility-form-for-healthcare-gov-37d79a5ad6?gi=12da7bf5ecf3"&gt;all people can use a service&lt;/a&gt;. Meeting people&amp;rsquo;s needs and making policies work first time and for all our communities. And by doing so meeting &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/guidance/accessibility-requirements-for-public-sector-websites-and-apps#:~:text=The%20accessibility%20regulations%20came%20into,accessibility%20statement%20on%20your%20website"&gt;legal and ethical standards&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of these technical requirements are open to interpretation. And need domain-knowledge to navigate and implement. Designers develop deep knowledge doing this and supporting teams in implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class="h3"&gt;Designers are experts at explaining and getting the right information in a form&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;div class="right fig-right"&gt;
  &lt;img src="/images/wireframes - andrew duckworth.jpeg" alt="Roy Litchenstien inspired artwork of UX wireframes"/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your product or service has a form. It needs information. And it may also use that form to display data in a process or flow. Designers are experts at designing the form and how it sits within a journey.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They do this so often they learn the rules and best practices and can ensure you follow them. So they can be quick and efficient by using best practice to improve things before you&amp;rsquo;ve invested in a solution and found out the hard way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 class="h3"&gt;But what about low volume forms and transactions?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just because something is low volume doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean the data or actions that sit off it are unimportant. I&amp;rsquo;ve worked on forms where there are at best 100 submitted a year. But when they are completed the work to process and manage the request is really high.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because designers come with lots of experience, they&amp;rsquo;re also well equipped to quickly help you pull together more generic forms. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The reasons you should still work with a designer are they:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;improve data accuracy and quality through form submissions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduce support requests or the use of other channels to do the thing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ensure legal compliance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use patterns to ensure people trust you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;make things consistent with branding and your values&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;identify or make sure of quick wins for usability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;avoid costly revisions because things don&amp;rsquo;t work or increase workload&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A form builder or design system will not give you these things. A team without a designer will find it harder to get this right.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good chunk of contact centre improvements I&amp;rsquo;ve made have started with poor data collection or bad processes that needed changing. And when teams look to design forms they also identify back office processes that need improving across the whole service. So you might start with the form but end up improving and optimising many processes and things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is why you design a form. For all these reasons. To make things easier for your user, get better data and meet your goals as an organisation.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Don't underestimate being at the heart of things</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/10/21/dont-underestimate-being-at-the-heart-of-things.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/10/21/dont-underestimate-being-at-the-heart-of-things.html</id>
    <published>2023-10-21T19:20:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2023-10-26T10:39:00+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A service I worked on from March is starting to roll out. When I landed in that team, needing some service design help and leadership, it felt they were the furthest away from making something real. And now it’s going to get very real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like all projects there’s lots to reflect on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Things you learnt. Could do better next time. Friendships and challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the things that went well was the speed of getting up to speed and making an impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I joined the team when they had gotten a massive scope shift. With the team reeling a little. But a week after I joined we had an end to end service design and broad hypothesis for what we wanted the service to look like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was lots more to do than that. But it felt great making an impact. And the feedback from the team and others was great too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a retro where some people were very nice about me and that impact it made me think about what helped me move things on. To make a useful impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having quite a lot of experience in health and the health and care sector helped. As did working in places learning how to do user centred design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the same was also true to how data services work. Even if when I joined the project I wasn’t aware it was going to involve yet another data pipeline and dashboards project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But even if those things weren’t true. And there have been plenty of projects were they haven’t. A thing that seems to work is being happy to, being active, in putting myself at the heart of facilitating and running meetings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a designer in a senior or leading role, your job is to help teams make better decisions. To design the right thing or the thing right. A way to help the team to achieve that is through your craft. But there’s another way. And one particularly important for a service designer. Which is to facilitate and help people run their processes in a user-centred way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can do that easier when you put yourself in the heart of the process. By offering to host, hold or run a meeting. From a retro to a planning session and everything in-between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/at the heart.jpeg" alt="Roy Lichtenstein style panel woman bluring into newspaper, hearts with empty speech bubble"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the project going live, I found myself running meetings from assumption mapping sessions to story mapping and sprint planning sessions. It ensured I was where decisions were made. And that when a decision was made. There was someone reflecting what users’ needed. And that we balanced lots of different perspectives and layers from the service. From policy, tech, users and service teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you’re feeling a little lost or out of the loop. Or want to make a bigger impact. Make a point of facilitating a meeting. Even a regular one or where there exists a person who sit in that role. It’ll help you be at the heart of things and facilitate the discussions and decisions you’ll need to do service design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take your delivery, product or project manager aside and say you want to run something. Either as personal experience or to help mix something up. Whatever it takes. Put the effort in and design the meeting to make it a success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally there’s a limit to what’s your role and be careful you’re not taking on work that’s not yours. Be clear you’re being helpful. And that this isn’t about taking notes or making coffee. It’s about making sure you and the team actually designs the service. So if the additional role doesn’t get you there be watchful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some teams or projects you may also find that the team is reluctant. Maybe that&amp;rsquo;s because you&amp;rsquo;re still needing to buy the space to lead things. Sometimes that&amp;rsquo;s just because the team isn&amp;rsquo;t ready. Sometimes that means you need others to take that leading role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But. Remember that most of service design is orchestration and facilitation of multiple viewpoints consciously designing and making the service. And that happens outside the craft of design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact the majority of service design happens outside the traditional craft of design. So don’t underestimate being at the heart of things. It’ll get you and your team further faster. Whatever way you can do it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Accessibility and inclusion isn't always going to be cost neutral</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/10/20/accessibility-and-inclusion-isnt-always-going-to-be-cost-neutral.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/10/20/accessibility-and-inclusion-isnt-always-going-to-be-cost-neutral.html</id>
    <published>2023-10-20T18:59:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2023-10-25T22:06:36+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Designing accessible inclusive interfaces is largely beneficial for all users. Making things more usable. And with things being usable. More profitable. More successful. With less failure demand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You see it in research where people will say they prefer an all at once on 1 page approach but don’t quite understand or get the thing. But when they use the more inclusive approach, and contrary to what they say about clicks or several pages, they go faster and get what they need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But like with anything. Sometimes doing the right thing comes at an cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s okay. That’s the point. It’s about opening things up for all. Not because we’re opening up every wallet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/wallets.jpeg" alt="lots of wallets"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes that definitely happens. But it’s not always going to be like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You shouldn’t underestimate what opening up your product can do. But it’s not a promise. An accessible product that meets no needs still meets no needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But really knowing and taking time to include different voices can be slow. Especially at first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s where the cost can be. The time it takes to make sure everyone can use the thing. Or the rework and tweaking of a live product that has to happen for a very subset of your users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it’s thing to a balance when explaining why we make things accessible and inclusive. Be clear about the benefits and strengths of an approach. But don’t sell out inclusion as just a cost saver or money spinner. Sometimes it will cost more. And that’s okay. That’s being human. And making things for all people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the same with your minimum legal requirements. They’re a good motivator and benchmark. But also only the most minimal approach. When they become the bar to meet you’ll find you’ll have something meeting the standard but not making everything possible or inclusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also lower the cost of doing things in an accessible and inclusive way if you do it early. Make your technical foundations something that makes it easy. And if you make being inclusive part of your day to day business. The cost reduces and you have longer to benefit from opening your product or service for all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, make your design technically accessible. And take an inclusive approach. It opens things up. But it doesn’t always cost less or open more wallets. Sometimes it’s the right thing to do. And if your principles don’t cost you anything or only make you money. Are they principles anyway?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Codesign and the carnivalesque</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://grillopress.github.io/2023/10/11/codesign-and-the-carnivalesque.html"/>
    <id>https://grillopress.github.io/2023/10/11/codesign-and-the-carnivalesque.html</id>
    <published>2023-10-11T19:14:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2023-10-25T22:12:34+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Andrew Duckworth</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Codesign is popular thing right now. I’ve heard it from lots of different corners of programme, project and delivery management. Nevermind research and design worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like codesign. It’s about involving the people who are impacted by your design in the design process. Of opening up and evening out power to create. But it’s something that gets said a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The promise of codesign is great. But the reality of how it’s done is often not so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of codesign reminds me of the “carnivalesque”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The carnivalesque&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="http://www.longwood.edu/staff/mcgeecw/notesoncarnivalesque.htm"&gt;carnivalesque&lt;/a&gt; is a literary and cultural concept. It refers to a temporary mode of subversion and rebellion against social norms and conventions. It originated from the medieval carnival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/pieter-bruegel.jpeg" alt="Carnival and debauchery on show in a painting from Pieter Bruegel the Elder, painted during the 16th century."/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Some sort of carnivalesque prototype of a knight going on in a Pieter Bruegel the Elder painting&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The carnival was a time when people would gather and engage in fun. Including role reversals, plays, masks, and other forms of transgression. The carnivalesque was a moment in time where roles are reversed. Activities that allowed people to challenge and undermine established hierarchies and power structures. Often by inverting or parodying them. And I&amp;rsquo;m sure often with lots of food and drink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the carnivalesque, the boundaries between sacred and profane, and normal and abnormal are blurred or even reversed. This leads to a sense of liberation and freedom. People are encouraged to express themselves and act outside of their usual roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jokes are had. Fun things take place. You get away from your normal roles and position in things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;What codesign and the carnivalesque share&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process of codesign and cocreation can be like the carnivalesque in several ways. Both involve a sense of playfulness and experimentation. People are encouraged to explore different ideas and possibilities in a non-conventional way. Like the carnivalesque, codesign and cocreation allow for the breaking down of barriers. And the crossing of boundaries between different disciplines, perspectives, and ways of thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both codesign and cocreation are collaborative processes. They involve a collective effort to create something new and innovative. This collaboration often leads to a disruption of traditional power structures. Participants are given an equal voice and agency in the design process. This is like carnivalesque’s inversion of power hierarchies and its emphasis on collective participation and democratic decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True carnivalesque is about unmanaged, unrefined sense of upheaval and fun bubbling under the surface that at any moment can strike hard at false certainties. Getting rid of “that’s how it works”. The carnivalesque is about upending roles. The lords become the peasants and those without power become the lords.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lots of design tools and techniques attempt to use this. None more so than codesign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And this is where codesign is the most powerful. Where it recreates this feeling. Where people who are typically excluded from decision making are in the room. The excluded are now making and producing with equal power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The shared flaws and limits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However. As with anything where there’s a transfer of power from those that have it to those that don&amp;rsquo;t. It’s scary. People will ask for “unrealistic things”. A strength. But also a threat. And with any threatening things, a risk to minimise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In organisations that are risk adverse. This happens all the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, codesign doesn’t happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Or if it does. It doesn’t actually influence or change anything beyond the moment of fun. Relegated to an hour of hope, exchanged in the long term for pessimism and sense that was a bloody waste of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And if that feels dramatic. I’ve seen it plenty. With people faithfully wanting to create the conditions to use what comes out of the chaos of codesign. But those in power having no acceptance or readiness to share power. Or take the fruits of codesign forward. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teams, communities and organisations then learn (rightfully) to distrust those with power. To roll their eyes. To say “we’ve heard this before”. And then they shun the next chance. Turning down any tickets to the show.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And who’d blame them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is also the main criticism of carnivaleseque. It isn’t something that creates lasting change. When the carnival closes everything goes back to the way it was. It’s not changing things in a lasting way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Codesign offers so much. But be careful that you can live up to the offer you make people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time you’re encouraging your users and communities to get involved. And take a codesign approach. Ask yourself: does your codesign project promise the carnival but leave your participants feeling like clowns?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
