<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2018-05-11T01:00:00+01:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 05</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/05/11/weeknotes-05.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/05/11/weeknotes-05.html</id>
    <published>2018-05-11T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-05-15T21:24:10+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bank holiday. Spent it in Cheshire. Sadly felt really ill for most of the day :/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked from home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looked into an issue with our analytics during public beta. We need to be clearer on capturing consent. Right now we don’t capture it quite to the standard needed (Post May 25th). There is an organisation-wide solution but it may not actually be ready for our cutoff. Asked a question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tweaked a couple of things on a prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got back to a colleague who had some questions about how we had evolved our site&amp;rsquo;s navigation. Hypothesis driven design to the rescue again. Every change we’ve used a set way of recording changes and the reasons for them. You can find more info on &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2017/12/10/hypothesis-driven-design.html"&gt;how we do Hypothesis driven design in this blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sketched some potential solutions. Issue being wow we handle important offline forms for very specialist groups. Mocked a few things up. Trying to find something that is sustainable. Something that can deal with shifting requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a meeting with the programme and NHSUK team about progress for go live. After that did a technical review of the pages. Caught a couple of small issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked a little on my part of the &amp;ldquo;Making UX Agile&amp;rdquo; talk. Emma Harvey (Head of Product) and I got asked if we could take the show on the road to Agile Manchester. Got told we had extremely positive reviews at UX in the City.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The potential audience was quite different.  So, although the narrative remained similar, I wanted to nail down the main takeaways. See Thursday for those!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Manchester for &amp;ldquo;Agile Manchester&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Couldn&amp;rsquo;t quite get into the swing of the event due to other work stuff. Was there with my delivery manager and she also had quite a few things to attend to as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had to duck out of the keynote to make an iteration on a prototype.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught an interesting talk from John Clapham called &amp;ldquo;Kaizen to Karõshi - sustainable pace and performance in teams&amp;rdquo;. Effectively, how and why people burn out. How agile can actually be an excuse for some bad behaviours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Made me pause for thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look after yourself, and each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Co-presented after lunch. Our talk was called &lt;a href="http://agilemanchester.net/2018/sessions/index.php?session=503"&gt;Making UX truly agile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talked about our journey. Starting from an agile-ish team but with some massive silos. To a well-connected, lean agile design into dev team. We&amp;rsquo;re facing new challenges everyday. But the team feels able to rise to the challenges.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was the only designer in the room. We had a mixture of developers, delivery staff and agile coaches. I asked how many people had experience of working with designers they felt were &amp;ldquo;agile&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;lean&amp;rdquo;. I got one half hand-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Room to improve designers!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My main points in the talk were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;1. Focus on the quality of conversations you have, much more than the quantity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make it easy to say things of substance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go where the conversations are happening&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;don’t do things - like stand ups etc. - because “that’s how we do things here”. Make sure they’re adding value. If they’re not, change it up&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;talk less, say more. Listen twice as much as you speak up and when you do, make sure it is productive&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if it feels like it would be awkward or difficult to talk about an issue, talk about it twice as much. Get things in the open. Get things cleaned up and sorted&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if you get a gut feeling like “really need to catch up with X”. Do it. Don’t delay&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do this and have less &amp;ldquo;WTF?&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Why wasn&amp;rsquo;t I told&amp;rdquo; moments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;2. You&amp;rsquo;ll never make design agile on your own&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you are the sole designer or have one designer in the team, you&amp;rsquo;ll need help. Empower your team to think about the user. Everyone impacts on the design. In exploration or implementation. Get everyone involved. Make it everyone&amp;rsquo;s problem with yourself (or your designer) as the lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduce user outcomes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;talk about it a lot and use the same language all the time&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;talk about users beyond the &amp;ldquo;UI&amp;rdquo; stuff. Non-functional things like security and performance are UX issues too!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;invite everyone to user research and design stuff&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proactively engage and elaborate design things with the development team. Be it your BA, product owner, developer or whatever. Co-craft the implementation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do this and you&amp;rsquo;ll be able to not only &amp;ldquo;keep ahead&amp;rdquo; of the development, but see what&amp;rsquo;s coming up. See what hasn&amp;rsquo;t been thought about. And spend less time telling people &amp;ldquo;you didn&amp;rsquo;t implement that right&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saving you time and energy to reinvest in the service or product you are building. And your own mental wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;3. Treat your design process like a design problem. Create, iterate, test, iterate, test, iterate, test&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Master your design workflow. Be sure how to take a problem and turn it into an outcome for your user. Make your process repeatable so you can keep iterating your design and iterating your service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;work out a simple stepped flow on how you finish a piece of design work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;add phases you&amp;rsquo;d like or should have (document, design review etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;use your process. Iterate. Test. Explore what works&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of building a process, &lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2018/01/08/kanban_for_interaction_design.html"&gt;I wrote up more about how we used a Kanban board to do just that in this blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you have a process ask yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What works?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What could you do better?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is too zoomed in? What am I obsessing over?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is too high level? What is important but isn&amp;rsquo;t being captured?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where am I holding things up?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Am I finishing things before starting the next lot of work?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Where and when do I get design tasks from?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And don&amp;rsquo;t forget to share your process. Talk about it to everyone who will listen. Share it early and often. It&amp;rsquo;s the only way to get better at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;4. There will always be a tension between design and delivery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that is okay. Design tries to get things right. And delivery is about making a thing real. There is always a need to balance making the right thing and making something real.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll never know for sure if something works until it is used by real people. So get something out in front of a user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being agile as a designer, or doing agile design, is about finding that path.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bit intense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our lead developer announced at standup he would be moving on. Really gutted to hear. He&amp;rsquo;s been great to work with and I will miss him.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To prepare for go live we had loads of attention and requests flying in. Very hectic day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll leave it at that :)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 04</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/05/04/weeknotes-04.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/05/04/weeknotes-04.html</id>
    <published>2018-05-04T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-05-07T21:51:02+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the week with some urgent medical care. My own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After dealing with that, jumped on some frontend tickets for the Thunderbird team. Updated the interruption card in the live service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We saw some mixed results using the latest version of the &amp;ldquo;interruption card&amp;rdquo;. It was either not interrupting enough or people were clicking icons. We had hoped that icons would make the card more arresting. But it has not. If anything, it made it more like a graphical element that people skipped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started on updating the error messages for the live service too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finished the error messages for pubic beta. Making the service&amp;rsquo;s error messages more actionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asked in the gov slack for advice. Got &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/document/d/1mbQPc_YATKR4h7inHMDvE8OLor7crEGP7f7Qd_QszqA/edit?usp=sharing"&gt;some great practical advice about writing error messages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked through screen recordings of the service. Digesting the feedback from the private beta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helped a colleague help a graduate prepare for an internal interview. Always enjoy helping others see how great they are. But also pushing them further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrote and presented at a show and tell. Great to see the researchers work through their findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I updated the wider project on the interruption card and upcoming design work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
  &lt;img src="/images/research_beta.png" alt="Two user researchers standing in front of a television screen"/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Emma and Katharine bossing it at the show and tell.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked on some more frontend cards for the Thunderbird team. This time SMS messages and emails. Took a chunk of the day. Had other personal stuff to deal with too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got some good news from some recruitment work I had helped lead on earlier in the year. Passed on that good news.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sent an email to the programme setting out my understanding of what to do for Friday. Took a few phonecalls to uncover requirements and pragmatic approaches going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the day with another call. Explored final content requirements and pragmatic approaches going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Halfway through the day got asked my opinion on some ministerial feedback. Dug out some stats from the private beta period to back up my position. Things like scroll depth, user journeys etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a few phonecalls to sort a range of issues that sprung out of that. Helped define a few small prototypes that could be of use to explore certain issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked on those for first thing Friday.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finished four prototypes. Three for the minister in the morning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sent a final call on the content and offline forms. Got all the content and packaged it up for a baselined prototype for the NHSUK team. Ready for go live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Received some updated terms and conditions for the live service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helped a junior colleague go through the process to make changes to the live service. Folding in a small content correction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exhausting end to a very exhausting week.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 03</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/04/28/weeknotes-03.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/04/28/weeknotes-03.html</id>
    <published>2018-04-28T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-04-29T16:47:37+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yet another busy week. Something of a pattern for April.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the week finishing off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Error messages. Form downloads for the offline service. Helping the Thunderbird team update the transactional service with some small tweaks. Bit of career management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Helped get a grad I met at the GDS training in touch with Thunderbird&amp;rsquo;s talented delivery manager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spent lunch with a friend from a different team. Ended up in a random Italian place. Talked about the tension of delivery and delivering the right thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Met with the service owner. Thrashed out how we are going to help all the teams on the same page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Folded in the new HTML email design into the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got told I had to use a real life photo on a slack instance. So, used the first one in my phone. Got trolled hard. Obviously just too saucy. Too Mills and Boon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class="noir right"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/mills_and_boon.png" alt="A joke mock-up of a Mills and Boon romance novel called 'Kanban at midnight' feating Andrew Duckworth's face"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;Available in all good bookstores&amp;hellip; Thanks Dean ;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lost count of the amount of people who told me the photo made me look fatter. Thanks. I think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spent some time with the user researchers. Ever since we had to move offices, the whole team hasn&amp;rsquo;t been able to sit together. Although Slack helps. For some people you need to get together face to face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked through the private beta findings. We used &lt;a href="https://www.usability.gov/how-to-and-tools/methods/system-usability-scale.html"&gt;&amp;ldquo;System Usability Scale&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; as well as a comprehension survey. Great usability scores. SUS scores place the service in the top 90%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comprehension is a worry. There was a recent phrase change that we can point to as causing a drop in comprehension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoyed going through the screen recordings. Will build the findings into a show and tell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Met with communications teams from various parts of the organisation. Working out how to help coordinate any old content and how that gets updated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked to a GDS designer about their prototyping kit. Some of the reasoning behind certain design decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prototyping kit is a tool that brings patterns into life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As such, less is often more. If you have too many patterns, or too low a bar for a pattern you increase the potential for teams to put in place things that are going to fail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, too few, or too high a bar for a pattern, then people will do what they need to do to get the job done right now. Often at the expense of the bigger picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got asked to produce something for the minister. Asked for clarity on a few things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a meeting with the service owner and content designer. Went through the transactional service. Talked errors, issues to implementation, emails and planning for planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Met up with a new designer, Alexandra. Working on the buying catalogue. A market place tool for procurement for CCGs. Interesting stuff. Hard challenges. Loads of potential. Was great to meet her. Had many questions about styles, patterns and standards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also talked about measuring usability and comprehension and how to get that in place for alpha.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large planning meeting with programme, Head of Product and Thunderbird tribe. Pretty productive. No fuss. Bit worried about the level of work I am touching on in the next few weeks. Need to sketch a plan of action. Will pair up with another designer again to get some of the design work into the product for the deadline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alongside planning had to pull in some changes for a prototype for
the minister. Took a fair chunk of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got invited to talk at Agile Manchester. Taking &lt;a href="http://uxinthecity.net/2018/manchester/sessions/index.php?session=311"&gt;&amp;ldquo;Making UX Agile&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; on tour.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Owned a lot of flexitime. Took some. Alongside a little bit of work on the prototype and the product.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spent some time exploring the GDS prototype kit and the inner workings. With the aim to pull in some features into my personal kit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learnt lots from all the prototypes I&amp;rsquo;ve built since early October last year for NHS Digital. Important not to get hung up on all the hacks. Also important to learn from them and make life easier next time.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 02</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/04/20/weeknotes-02.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/04/20/weeknotes-02.html</id>
    <published>2018-04-20T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-04-22T14:59:08+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Another busy week. Worked through some issues in implementing the service&amp;rsquo;s site on the NHSUK platform. Spent some time learning how GDS and gov.uk do design in London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the week talking design principles. We have some draft NHS design principles up on the wall in the Digital Delivery Centre. Right now we have nine principles. To kickstart conversation I asked what two principles people would remove. We had a pretty healthy debate.  It was interesting to see slight differences between interaction and service designers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the principles may actually be better described as behaviours.  “What makes someone a good designer” rather than “what makes something a good design”. Something to think about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ran into Stephen Corbett who was in his last week. Talked about service design with him and the world of “UX”. Going to miss Stephen. Always good fun and a smart mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a sprint retrospective with the Thunderbird tribe. Then walked through some storyboards for a side project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attended the Digital Delivery Centre experience design team meet up. Talked about the progress of the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked from home. Crafted a sitemap for the service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcomed new member of the design community via Slack. Always make a point to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Travelled down to London later in the day. Had a 40 min delay due to a passenger medical emergency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got to my hotel fine. Right next to the tower of London and tower bridge. Missed out on being able to catch my brother before he left work and a friend. Worked out meeting my friend on Thursday though. Next time I have to stay over in London I will arrange something with a friend or a colleague beforehand. Felt bored. Had a wonder and took some photos to relieve the boredom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="/images/london/tower_bridge.jpg" alt="Tower Bridge in black and white with heavy shadows"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a wonder up to Whitechapel after strolling around St Katharine’s. Beautiful place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First day of the GDS course. Talking principles, user stories, service design and journey mapping. Before getting into interaction flows with Tim Paul. Some of the day seemed out of sync. We did journey mapping before research. Seemed in the wrong order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a great lunch from a local street market. £5 for a massive chicken tikka roll, meat samosa and a drink.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src="/images/london/team_with_tikka.jpg" alt="Four designers eating Chicken tikka wraps in a street market"/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption class="noir"&gt;Street food on a Yorkshire budget&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoyed spending the day with a group of people doing digital stuff for government. Paired with a graduate from NHS Digital, Sam as well. Enjoyed it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a night out with the team from NHS Digital. Had a blast. Pizza. Beers and good company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next day at the training started with content design. Sam shone here. It’s always great to see people doing what they love. We also heard from Ed “from slack” Horsford about the journey to create the passport service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed doing an interaction design review with Tim Paul. Piped up a little too much. Particularly here. But interaction design is my jam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later on after work met a friend. Had some beers by the river. Funny how far we’d come from when we first met in a small publishing company in Birmingham.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last day in London. Started it early by touring around the City of London and enjoying the sights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="half"&gt;
  &lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/london/noir_gerk.jpg" alt="The Gherkin building in London in black and white with heavy shadows"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Gherkin. Always swamped and surrounded by other buildings but standing out by its shape.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
  &lt;figure class="noir"&gt;
    &lt;img src="/images/london/lloyds.jpg" alt="The Lloyd's building in London in black and white with heavy shadows"/&gt;
    &lt;figcaption&gt;The Lloyd&amp;rsquo;s building. Brutally showing its bowels.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training was about using the gov.uk prototyping kit. A couple of the NHS Digital grads didn&amp;rsquo;t get IT to put the kit on their machines. Tried to use a browser based option. But all the platforms had issues. Either with gulp.js (glitch) or with a need for a credit card (Cloud9, Koding) or some bizarre no access to a terminal on free accounts (codio).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bit frustrating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I paired with one of the graduates and let her use my machine. It was great to see the GDS designers and frontenders there to help. Being able to cobble together an interactive prototype is a fun and powerful thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The room benefitted from there being plenty of examples in the kit as well. Lots of lessons for NHS Digital.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had to catch up and jump into many conversations through the day about my normal work. Found it a touch stressful as the project is gearing up to go live and not being in Leeds.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 01</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/04/13/weeknotes-01.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/04/13/weeknotes-01.html</id>
    <published>2018-04-13T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-04-14T15:14:04+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m going to give weeknotes a try. A round-up of my work week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Planned out some content changes for our prototype with the content designer. Folded some changes into it. Took a good chunk of the day. Enabled the programme to review content and site structure in preparation for going public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wrote a little more on personas for an interaction design course I am creating. Editing it led me to reading &lt;a href="https://www.cooper.com/journal/2008/05/the_origin_of_personas"&gt;Alan Cooper&amp;rsquo;s The origin of personas&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mucked about with a screen recording tools or two in preparation to record the course. In-built Mac tools turned out to be the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Played a &amp;ldquo;silence game&amp;rdquo; imagined up by our delivery manager Sophie to review the product backlog. Worked pretty well. We all agreed she needed to write it up and patent it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src="/images/silence_game/having_fun.jpg" alt="Thunderbird team having fun playing the silence game"/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption id="silence-game"&gt;The Thunderbird tribe having fun. Quietly.&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lent a helping hand later to take a couple of people from GDS on a tour around the Digital Delivery Centre. Talked a little about the way we had evolved our design process on my project to keep it agile and outcome focused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They raised some interesting points.  You need to make sure you don’t just provide the business with the ability to make decisions. But also help them make the right ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Worked from home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Took some time to design how offline forms are going to work on the service. Explored current solutions used by the NHS Choices website and DVLA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed the designs with several other designers. Found out that a colleague getting married soon (Congratulations Karl! Pizza in the post please).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can&amp;rsquo;t underestimate the value and importance of sharing work early and often. Got some great ideas and questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very intense day started in a usability lab. A lab with a focus on how contact centre staff would do assisted digital journeys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was impressed with the problem solving from the call centre staff. Guiding users and developing and remixing the call centre scripts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Made me think about organisations like Automattic that ensure their developers spend a week a year doing phone support. The idea being to keep them  aware of the problems their users face. Feels like a concept that would help designers building software for the NHS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src="/images/canalside.jpg" alt="A canal in Leeds"/&gt;
  &lt;figcaption id="canalside"&gt;I walked a lot. Between three offices. Luckily the walk is pretty&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Caught up with a graduate I have been mentoring. Talked to his assignment manager too, a product manager on the project he was on. Seemed like a really nice team. Got invited to their next show and tell by the product manager. Will make a special effort to attend.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asked a question in the design slack and on Twitter about the use of personas. interesting debate and discussion. Will write it up soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hosted the design huddle. Heard from the delightful Dean about the “redesign” work. They’re working on foundational elements for the rest of the organisation. Raised the issue of forms and transactional service design. Talked a little about my forms as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a few more changes and questions from the programme but got all the content approved and ready for public beta!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chased up the status on the service&amp;rsquo;s offline forms and handed over design and content to the NHSUK migration team, in readiness for the site going live in May.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bumped into some of the redesign team. Was nice to chat. Got invited to talk forms and redesign. Will need to find a day or half-day to come over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a coffee and chat about design at NHS Digital with one of my favourite people, the magnificent Tero!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a good catch up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Didn’t get to talk double diamond enough. Need to make sure we don’t leave it to goodbyes to talk our favourite subject.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Start pages</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/02/03/start-pages.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/02/03/start-pages.html</id>
    <published>2018-02-03T16:45:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2018-02-13T12:49:39+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the last couple of months I have been designing for “comprehension”. Helping users understand a very complicated and emotive subject.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although not “done”, recent success in user labs has given us some scope to focus on other risks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We want to make sure that people start our service understanding the thing they are doing. And what they need to have to complete that journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have been looking at how we inform users of the process they’ll about to undertake. How best we can let them know if they are able to complete the journey online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This led me to read a few things about start pages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class='weekly-link-list'&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;“It means people can use services much quicker, and they have detailed information in the place they most need it”&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
First was
&lt;a href="https://designnotes.blog.gov.uk/2013/12/20/start-pages-within-guides/" target="_blank"&gt;"start pages within guides". &lt;/a&gt;
A blog post from 2013.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In it the team behind the carer’s allowance explained how they integrated their start page into the guide itself. Reducing the steps required to get the allowance and making it clearer that users could make a claim&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you are dealing with quite a complicated subject, you don’t want to dilute the message with the practicalities of how to start an online transactional journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet it makes sense to have the journey start from where users are. Where they can jump back and forward and get the information they need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='link-to'&gt;
Read more:
&lt;a href="https://designnotes.blog.gov.uk/2013/12/20/start-pages-within-guides/" target="_blank"&gt;Start pages within guides&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;“You’ll only be able to ask users clear questions when the process itself is clear”&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
As I kept googling I re-read the
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/service-manual/design/check-before-you-start" target="_blank"&gt;“Check before you start”&lt;/a&gt;
pattern. This is where you take users through a set of questions that pre-checks whether they are able to use the service in question.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The “before you start” pattern was something we toyed with in an earlier prototype but the journey felt like we were begging the question. The outcomes were too simple and as such didn’t add much value to the transaction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where I see this filter pattern or similar really shining, is when you have several closely aligned transactions or services. Services with a single entry point that users might not immediately see significant difference between.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way, the filter works like visiting a GP. You know what symptoms you have and the expert (the service) through well thought-out questions kickstarts your journey into the appropriate part of the service.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='link-to'&gt;
Read more:
&lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/service-manual/design/check-before-you-start" target="_blank"&gt;Check before you start&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;“We have been able to dramatically reduce the amount of content on the start page”&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Another thing I looked at was the
&lt;a href="https://home-office-digital-patterns.herokuapp.com/patterns/interruption-card" target="_blank"&gt;“interruption card”&lt;/a&gt;
pattern on the Home Office digital pattern library.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This pattern matched something we had been trying to design before users got presented with a form to fill in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Often you want to create a frictionless journey for your users. But when you need them to understand something, you need to introduce friction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interruption card does this well. It looks different and therefore surprises the user somewhat. But isn’t so different that they think they have gone to another website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It summarizes the journey and requirements well, combining with the start page to increase user comprehension over two pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pattern benefits from being within the journey of the service. Once a user has started a journey or transaction, they appear to take the information more seriously. Or at least, a lot more seriously than they do on the start page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The advice in the pattern page calls for caution. Not to use the interruption card pattern too often. What is interesting about this is that the instances of the card I have seen use it quite extensively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than an interruption card, it becomes a journey within a journey. A phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='link-to'&gt;
Read more:
&lt;a href="https://home-office-digital-patterns.herokuapp.com/patterns/interruption-card" target="_blank"&gt;Interruption card pattern&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
