<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Blog Name</title>
  <subtitle>Blog subtitle</subtitle>
  <id>http://blog.url.com/</id>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/"/>
  <link href="http://blog.url.com/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2018-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Blog Author</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Questions for your questions</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/12/05/questions-for-your-questions.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/12/05/questions-for-your-questions.html</id>
    <published>2018-12-05T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2018-12-05T17:10:19+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, to no fan-fair, I put live a significant iteration to the non-digital service. The service helps users make a choice on how their children&amp;rsquo;s data can be used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Part of the new process was an iteration on a previous form. The work brought together:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;new visual system&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;reduced list of identity documents required&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;simplified process to prove parental responsibility&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;user focused words and ways of asking questions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Redesigning the forms with the team meant questioning everything. Things we held self-evident. Rules that were stuck-in-stone. Policy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happily the whole team leapt into this work. Sam (grad content designer) and I had no need to canvas for support to charge ahead with this work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It made me realise that you could better explore the tough parts of any service with the non-digital version first. That is, inputting information, reading it and processes. But not just pretend stuff (paper prototypes). But actual real life submissions. Paper is cheap. Easy to iterate. But live. If your service is a policy-driven thing. What better way to test drive whether that policy delivers what it needs to?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also felt that there are many questions you ask when you need to get information from a user. That is, questions that all services, digital or not, should answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote some of these questions down and shared them. And in the spirit of making things open. Here is my first go at questions to ask yourself when designing services and forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Questions for your questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is your user trying to do?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What information do you need to get them to their goal?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why are you asking for this information?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If any of it isn&amp;rsquo;t necessary, why are you asking for it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is what you&amp;rsquo;re asking for, the least you can get away with asking?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could you get the information you need from them without directly asking?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How would you ask the user in person for this information?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How would a user describe what they&amp;rsquo;re being asked for?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is there any format restrictions? (Age by number or specific date etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will the things you are asking for be expected or natural?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will the context of the service, or where the user is, change how appropriate the question is? (Sexual health, prison, on behalf of another etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Will the location of the user change how easy to answer the question is? (Mobile, home, abroad, in an emergency)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What happens if the user can&amp;rsquo;t or won&amp;rsquo;t answer the question?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If there is a restriction, what happens if the user doesn&amp;rsquo;t meet it?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Questions to help your questions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do other services ask for this currently?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How effective is this? What do they say works or doesn&amp;rsquo;t work? If  they could click their fingers and it happen, would they change anything?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What help does other systems provide to help people answer it? (Before they fill it in)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What help does it provide if the answer isn&amp;rsquo;t filled in?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What help does it provide if the format is wrong?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What happens when a user doesn&amp;rsquo;t meet the requirements? (For example, they are too young)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 16</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/11/02/weeknotes-16.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/11/02/weeknotes-16.html</id>
    <published>2018-11-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2018-11-06T07:10:43+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back on the Weeknotes wagon. See how long this&amp;rsquo;ll last&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Monday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A fair chunk of Monday spent reviewing the work done on the paper forms. Sam (graduate designer) took a day last week to get heads down on the forms. We worked through some issues and translated her content into the new design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The forms have come a long way. Even from September. Much of that credit to the team jumping into this issue. And Sam&amp;rsquo;s hard work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon the national data opt-out team met up to talk about the research roadmap. We reviewed what we had planned. Including the paper forms and the accessibility audit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some extra work planned in for December. Had a good discussion with the programme manager about what we needed to do next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We also looked at how we are evaluating comprehension. There were a few questions that when we wrote them they worked well enough but now we could see how to improve them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Tuesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sent over the finished paper forms to the user researchers to help them do a live test of their lab plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Backlog review for the national data opt out service. Talked through a few cards and bugs I created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spent much of the day with the senior members of the design community talking about design culture. Both in the community and wider organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We celebrated the &lt;a href="https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/the-future-of-healthcare-our-vision-for-digital-data-and-technology-in-health-and-care/the-future-of-healthcare-our-vision-for-digital-data-and-technology-in-health-and-care"&gt;new vision for health tech&lt;/a&gt; released by the department of health and social care.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few of us in the room had written the NHS design principles. But we also pondered how we can get our organisation to talk more about design and its value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had a productive chat with the developers about the future product. Not my role, but talked though technical architecture. We talked through how we could make the most developer friendly set up. Whilst maintaining the most device/platform agnostic frontend possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ended the day talking to the audit and transparency team about user research. Design questions and content questions. Always enjoy talking to Lucy, Will and Sam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Wednesday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the day talking to Will (researcher on audit and transparency) about problem statements. The problem statement had gone through many changes. But there wasn&amp;rsquo;t a confirmed one. I felt we had one pretty much there. With enough scope not to allow for a pivot. We agreed to go for it in the steering group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had my first steering group show and tell for audit and transparency. Everything was very positively received. Make sure Sam&amp;rsquo;s good work on the content discovery was front and centre too. One of the clinicians raised a great point. When giving users a look at their medical record you have to be aware there are risks that they are being treated for things they may not think they are. Or how it is recorded in their medical record may make it look more serious than it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the call switched back to the opt-out service&amp;rsquo;s paper forms. Went through the initial feedback and lab plan with the user researchers. A few small things to change and some to watch in the lab next week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the issues was having nothing but a PO address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I thought the lack of a service name or title for the postal address would make that seem creepy. Rather than secure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon we had a long user stories review and writing session. Cleared out some older ones. Wrote some cornerstones. More work to do. Good session though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finished the day chatting about information architecture to Sam. The picture of the NHS website platform and our user&amp;rsquo;s needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Thursday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Started the day with a chat with the NHS website team with how to get access to edit the website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got the audit and transparency team together to talk through content. We talked:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As is picture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Search terms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Referrers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Organisational strategy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the &amp;ldquo;to be&amp;rdquo; picture&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best thing we got out of the day was a better understanding of the whole galaxy that our users navigate. When it comes to finding out about their health records, users often start with their GP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over lunch heard about what Well Digital have been up to. The format was pretty well organised. It was nice to hear they cared about the human processes behind the digital and not the computers bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing overran but would have asked about clinical risks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked about the new audit service we are building at the design huddle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talked through our design principles and design constraints. Pitched a short sketching challenge too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could tell from a few faces that the designers thought the challenge was obvious. But when we talked things through it wasn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of us in that room have apps and use services that let us audit our activity. In the app or service (energy usage, milage, spend) and some that let us audit how the data about us is generated or shared. Like Uber, Google etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Friday&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not as productive as I&amp;rsquo;d like. Lots of small things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gave a colleague a review of some of the stuff I sent another team. A situation where I tried to help nudge and review some work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Created some materials for the upcoming lab. Wasn&amp;rsquo;t as straight forward as I had hoped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reviewed the paper forms once last time with Sam. Took a decision on a few items that were left outstanding. Everything ready for the lab next Tuesday.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Dashing dashboards</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/10/06/dashing-dashboards.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/10/06/dashing-dashboards.html</id>
    <published>2018-10-06T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-10-06T22:11:34+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A little while back I was talking to a colleague about dashboards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key value of a dashboard is insight and clarity. Not data. Not numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your service’s KPIs are indicators, not the story. And not an insight in itself. You need to give people a clear direction of what’s happening, why and what to do next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I worked in publishing the data team created a tool to help visualise publishing topics. The idea being to give editors insight into lucrative areas to publish in. How topics related. And the potential market size.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tool was great engineering. But added no value. The issue  was that the only people who could get value out of it, knew the topics and relationships already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a nice tool. But one that only provided insight to those who could already see the big picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is often the problem with dashboards. Understandable for the creators. Not for the stakeholders. Consumers and decision makers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When creating dashboards ask yourself what do we (and/or our users) need to know? What insights are important?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A great place to start is with problem statements. If you don’t have them, they’re worth generating retrospectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ask yourself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What have we seen and what are we trying to solve?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How will we know when we&amp;rsquo;ve solved that problem or created that outcome?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be tempting to inject numbers into a dashboard. Particularly as a team that understands them or can interpret them. Things like time on site, bounce rates, response times, scroll depth are all interesting things. But what do they say?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If those terms are new or unknown, they say nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to tell the story of whether users a doing a thing, make that immediately clear. Clear without need to interpret numbers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is a hierarchy. An important thing to explain. Follow the fundamental design principle of making that hierarchy clear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A dashboard that asks you to interpret data doesn’t offer insight. It may provide you with enough to get there in raw ingredients. But will everyone with 60 seconds understand and see the story? If you provide the raw elements to understand the live service, it&amp;rsquo;s like offering someone a burger. And then giving them wheat and raw mince.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is your dashboard counting how many eggs you have, or making an omelette?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Advice for aspiring junior UX designers</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/10/01/advice-for-aspiring-junior-ux-designers.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/10/01/advice-for-aspiring-junior-ux-designers.html</id>
    <published>2018-10-01T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-10-01T20:06:42+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A while back I helped recruit a junior designer. I got to talk to many talented junior designers on the phone and face to face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the process I made a note of some general advice I felt could help many of the candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following tips are my advice for aspiring user experience designers. Though many of the points could apply to any role.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;CV advice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to your CV keep it simple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is plenty of general advice about CVs that also holds for designers. Keep it short as possible. To the point and easy to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can be tempting as a designer to spend too much time on the visual design flourishes of your CV. But for user experience roles, the key thing to get across is that you understand your user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your user cares about being able to scan information about you. Keep it neat. Keep it clean and minimal and easy to read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Make sure your CV works on different devices and the links actually go where you expect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the job role and related info and check you have what they need. On each criteria write one-line of how you’ve shown you have that skill. With the ones that you are less confident on, how can you show how you are developing that skill?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This list helps form your CV, cover letter and interview answers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the role is for a junior post, companies will be expecting some weaker areas. They need you to be able to show understanding, passion as much as actual experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passion and willingness to learn isn’t something an employer can teach. HTML is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have lots of gaps (things you can’t even show you are trying to address as a weakness), don’t apply. Don’t waste your time on something you are not a good fit on. You’re not going to get past the CV sift where it is as much matching keywords as it is your potential. If it is a dream job, you now have a list of things to get good at and prove.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t to say you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t apply for a role you&amp;rsquo;re a nearly match for. Those you should. Job roles are perfect fits. No one is perfect. But don&amp;rsquo;t waste your time and emotional energy on something  you&amp;rsquo;re not a good fit on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Cover letter advice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In your cover letter match the language the company uses. If the job post talks about interaction design, call it that. If they call it user interface design, likewise. Like mirroring someone’s body language, mirror their conventions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Portfolio advice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to your portfolio make sure you have a strong narrative. You should write them using a schema like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Summary. A short description of what you did. Tweet length&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Context. Provide the background. Where it was. What it was for etc. in one or two paragraphs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process. Describe the broad strokes of your design process. This should be the meatiest part. Ensure you describe how you put the user at the heart of your process!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Outcomes. What did you produce and what outcome did it create for your user?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lessons. What did you learn and what would you do next time? A key skill to a good designer is learning from mistakes and applying those learnings&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is hard to underestimate the importance of being able to explain your design process. You must be able to explain what you did, how you did it and why you did it. This isn&amp;rsquo;t to say it&amp;rsquo;s easy. But you&amp;rsquo;ll stand out as a candidate if you can take someone through your process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Interview advice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As with your portfolio, it is vital you are able to explain your design process. The steps you go through to design something.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many face to face interviews you’ll have to take someone through a portfolio item. Or tackle a design challenge. Being able to explain your process will make you stand out. More so than eye-catching visuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A caveat to this advice to not to be rigid in your process. Be flexible. Understand that there are techniques appropriate in some situations. For some problems, you need to be very lean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A textbook large-scale discovery isn&amp;rsquo;t the only tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t confuse good client management with user testing. Unless your client is the only person to use a system, it is likely they aren’t the user you are looking for. A/B testing with a client does not replace user testing. Client driven design is not user centred design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your goal as a designer is creating a product that works for your client’s users. Do this and your client will see the rewards from happy users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Post-interview advice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of how well it went, try to ask for advice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you didn’t get the job, ask why. Remember that it is often being able to demonstrate your skills as having them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interviewer cannot assume you have skills. They need you to state them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;General advice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be yourself. Be your best self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ve got this! Good luck. If you want any further help, feel free to message me.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Treat your design process like a design problem</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/09/29/treat-your-design-process-like-a-design-process.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/09/29/treat-your-design-process-like-a-design-process.html</id>
    <published>2018-09-29T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-09-29T19:31:20+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Before going on leave I got to work with a graduate designer (Sam) who will be joining me on a couple of projects. Over three days we covered interaction flows, content architecture and paper forms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Sam joining me, it made me think about design process. Creating a good one. A repeatable, efficient process that creates great outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst working on the National Data Opt-out we (myself and a junior designer Dan) crafted a process that helped us explore a massive range of ideas and issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The process didn’t appear fully-formed. It took many iterations. It evolved through experience and being worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://grillopress.github.io/2018/01/08/kanban_for_interaction_design.html"&gt;I blogged about the journey&lt;/a&gt;, centring on our use of a kanban board.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key to creating a great design process is to treat it like a design problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Start by stating the issue you want to solve&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sketch out crude flows and processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a prototype and use it in anger&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Iterate over things again and again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Seek feedback from those around you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Articulate and defend your ideas to expose flaws and strengths&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kanban board felt the best mechanism to control and test the process.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With new work and a new team, it&amp;rsquo;s a great time to explore our process again.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Weeknotes 15</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://blog.url.com/2018/09/14/weeknotes-15.html"/>
    <id>http://blog.url.com/2018/09/14/weeknotes-15.html</id>
    <published>2018-09-14T01:00:00+01:00</published>
    <updated>2018-09-14T19:16:10+01:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Article Author</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Trying to keep these even leaner. Going to focus on a few themes from a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Paper forms&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a personal crusade with paper forms right now. We have three for patients. And soon have some for prisoners (filled in by prison medical staff on behalf of a prisoner).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re not good enough. People can muddle through them. But they&amp;rsquo;re not the standard we need to be hitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the back of a great session at the design huddle with Caroline Jarrett I had a strong action plan. I even tweeted it for feedback:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;Any other solid ways of researching paper forms?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re doing:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;+ looking at real paper form submissions&lt;br&gt;+ working with team who get forms and action them&lt;br&gt;+ user lab focused on paper forms&lt;br&gt;+ Challenging the need for stuff in the forms 😁&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Andrew Duckworth (@AndrewDuck_) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AndrewDuck_/status/1039789320792666112?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;September 12, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And got even greater feedback and connections to people willing to help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The programme agreed to do everything to make them better. With a bit of campaigning we&amp;rsquo;ve got access to the current filled in forms and will review them next Wednesday as a team. We&amp;rsquo;ve also booked in a lab and potentially some pop-up testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve created a clean form system. Brutally simple graphic design system. Now to make our process brutally simple for our users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Design meet up!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week it was the quarterly all-hands design meet. In London this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoy going to London. That said, though the venue was great, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t as iconic or scenic a walk this time. And it was also a rather painfully long day. Thanks trains!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the day I got to express my inner artiste:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote class="twitter-tweet" data-lang="en"&gt;&lt;p lang="en" dir="ltr"&gt;The best name badge I ever did have. Thank you &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/AndrewDuck_?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;@AndrewDuck_&lt;/a&gt; 🦄 &lt;a href="https://t.co/cH2DBkcFRu"&gt;pic.twitter.com/cH2DBkcFRu&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&amp;mdash; Louise Mushet (@louisemushet) &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/louisemushet/status/1039883809553084416?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw"&gt;September 12, 2018&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;script async src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And hang with lots of cool people. (Special shout out to Louise Mushet who made the day extra fun without a few of my design besties!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the day the rapid paced 5 min show and tells worked well in quickly letting everyone show a thing. Be present. Be the centre of attention. But they also too short and leave no room for chats.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I nicked time in each talk to ask a question. So when people were swapping over I&amp;rsquo;d ask a question. But they left me wanting more. Much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you get together so many smart people I feel you have to give space to comments. That freeform discussion space is where designers shine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunch was amazing. Hat tip to Pete &amp;ldquo;Two sheds but actually I only have one right now because I gave my son a shed&amp;rdquo; Smith. We had to walk for it but I had a great plate of chicken kabab and chips.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all it was a great day. Loads of smart, fun people in the room. Really well put together by the London design gang!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Stuff for admin users&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that popped up at the design away day. And reviewing some work recently, is the attitude towards professional/admin users by designers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something I&amp;rsquo;ve heard elsewhere was lots of excuses how &amp;ldquo;that&amp;rdquo; group of users are different. Like they can&amp;rsquo;t be overworked. Distracted. Confused. Need full love and attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happily we have lots of designers who care. But plenty don&amp;rsquo;t. Plenty throw away solid patterns because things aren&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;citizen facing&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like admin staff aren&amp;rsquo;t &amp;ldquo;citizens&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, if a user does a thing 20 times a day, certain patterns may need to be tweaked. Tweaked not destroyed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Designers should be responding to user needs not preconceptions. And it makes me shudder when those preconceptions don&amp;rsquo;t have a date with user testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does your user do that thing 20 times a day?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I asked this question recently to a designer and the answer was 3 times a year. That isn&amp;rsquo;t an interface that they know by heart. That isn&amp;rsquo;t an interface they have muscle memory developed for.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
